Song of Solomon

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8

The Song of Solomon

1

1  The song of songs, which is Solomon’s.

2  Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth: [*]for [†]thy love is better than wine. 3  Because of the savour of thy good ointments thy name is as ointment poured forth, therefore do the virgins love thee. 4 [*] Draw me, we will run after thee: the king hath brought me into his chambers: we will be glad and rejoice in thee, we will remember thy love more than wine: [∥]the upright love thee. 5 I am black, but comely, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, as the tents of Kedar, as the curtains of Solomon. 6  Look not upon me, because I am black, because the sun hath looked upon me: my mother’s children were angry with me; they made me the keeper of the vineyards; but mine own vineyard have I not kept.

7  Tell me, O thou whom my soul loveth, where thou feedest, where thou makest thy flock to rest at noon: for why should I be [∥]as one that turneth aside by the flocks of thy companions?

8 ¶ If thou know not, O thou fairest among women, go thy way forth by the footsteps of the flock, and feed thy kids beside the shepherds’ tents. 9  I have compared thee, O my love, to a company of horses in Pharaoh’s chariots. 10  Thy cheeks are comely with rows of jewels, thy neck with chains of gold. 11  We will make thee borders of gold with studs of silver.

12 ¶ While the king sitteth at his table, my spikenard sendeth forth the smell thereof. 13  A bundle of myrrh is my wellbeloved unto me; he shall lie all night betwixt my breasts. 14  My beloved is unto me as a cluster of [∥]camphire in the vineyards of En-gedi. 15 [*]Behold, thou art fair, [∥]my love; behold, thou art fair; thou hast doves’ eyes. 16 Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant: also our bed is green. 17  The beams of our house are cedar, and our [∥]rafters of fir.

2

1 I am the rose of Sharon, and the lily of the valleys. 2  As the lily among thorns, so is my love among the daughters.

3  As the apple tree among the trees of the wood, so is my beloved among the sons. [†]I sat down under his shadow with great delight, and his fruit was sweet to my [†]taste. 4  He brought me to the [†]banqueting house, and his banner over me was love. 5  Stay me with flagons, [†]comfort me with apples: for I am sick of love. 6 [*] His left hand is under my head, and his right hand doth embrace me. 7 [†][*] I charge you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and by the hinds of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.

8 ¶ The voice of my beloved! behold, he cometh leaping upon the mountains, skipping upon the hills. 9 [*] My beloved is like a roe or a young hart: behold, he standeth behind our wall, he looketh forth at the windows, [†]shewing himself through the lattice. 10  My beloved spake, and said unto me, Rise up, my love, my fair one, and come away. 11  For, lo, the winter is past, the rain is over and gone; 12  The flowers appear on the earth; the time of the singing of birds is come, and the voice of the turtle is heard in our land; 13  The fig tree putteth forth her green figs, and the vines with the tender grape give a good smell. Arise, my love, my fair one, and come away.

14 ¶ O my dove, that art in the clefts of the rock, in the secret places of the stairs, let me see thy countenance, let me hear thy voice; for sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely. 15  Take us the foxes, the little foxes, that spoil the vines: for our vines have tender grapes.

16 ¶ [*]My beloved is mine, and I am his: he feedeth among the lilies. 17 [*] Until the day break, and the shadows flee away, turn, my beloved, and be thou [*]like a roe or a young hart upon the mountains [∥]of Bether.

3

1  By night on my bed I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not. 2  I will rise now, and go about the city in the streets, and in the broad ways I will seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not. 3  The watchmen that go about the city found me: to whom I said, Saw ye him whom my soul loveth? 4  It was but a little that I passed from them, but I found him whom my soul loveth: I held him, and would not let him go, until I had brought him into my mother’s house, and into the chamber of her that conceived me. 5 [*] I charge you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and by the hinds of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.

6 ¶ [*]Who is this that cometh out of the wilderness like pillars of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, with all powders of the merchant?

7  Behold his bed, which is Solomon’s; threescore valiant men are about it, of the valiant of Israel. 8  They all hold swords, being expert in war: every man hath his sword upon his thigh because of fear in the night. 9  King Solomon made himself [∥]a chariot of the wood of Lebanon. 10  He made the pillars thereof of silver, the bottom thereof of gold, the covering of it of purple, the midst thereof being paved with love, for the daughters of Jerusalem. 11  Go forth, O ye daughters of Zion, and behold king Solomon with the crown wherewith his mother crowned him in the day of his espousals, and in the day of the gladness of his heart.

4

1 [*]Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; thou hast doves’ eyes within thy locks: thy hair is as a [*]flock of goats, [∥]that appear from mount Gilead. 2  Thy teeth are like a flock of sheep that are even shorn, which came up from the washing; whereof every one bear twins, and none is barren among them. 3  Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet, and thy speech is comely: thy temples are like a piece of a pomegranate within thy locks. 4  Thy neck is like the tower of David builded for an armoury, whereon there hang a thousand bucklers, all shields of mighty men. 5 [*] Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins, which feed among the lilies. 6 [*] Until the day [†]break, and the shadows flee away, I will get me to the [‡]mountain of myrrh, and to the hill of frankincense. 7 [*]Thou art all fair, my love; there is no spot in thee.

8 ¶ Come with me from Lebanon, my spouse, with me from Lebanon: look from the top of Amana, from the top of Shenir [*]and Hermon, from the lions’ dens, from the mountains of the leopards. 9  Thou hast [∥]ravished my heart, my sister, my spouse; thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, with one chain of thy neck. 10  How fair is thy love, my sister, my spouse! [*]how much better is thy love than wine! and the smell of thine ointments than all spices! 11  Thy lips, O my spouse, drop as the honeycomb: honey and milk are under thy tongue; and the smell of thy garments is like the smell of Lebanon. 12  A garden [†]inclosed is my sister, my spouse; a spring shut up, a fountain sealed. 13  Thy plants are an orchard of pomegranates, with pleasant fruits; [∥]camphire, with spikenard, 14  Spikenard and saffron; calamus and cinnamon, with all trees of frankincense; myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices:

15  A fountain of gardens, a well of living waters, and streams from Lebanon.

16 ¶ Awake, O north wind; and come, thou south; blow upon my garden, that the spices thereof may flow out. Let my beloved come into his garden, and eat his pleasant fruits.

5

1  I am come into my garden, my sister, my spouse: I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk: eat, O friends; drink, [∥]yea, drink abundantly, O beloved.

2 ¶ I sleep, but my heart waketh: it is the voice of my beloved that knocketh, saying, Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled: for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night. 3  I have put off my coat; how shall I put it on? I have washed my feet; how shall I defile them? 4  My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door, and my bowels were moved [∥]for him. 5  I rose up to open to my beloved; and my hands dropped with myrrh, and my fingers with [†]sweet smelling myrrh, upon the handles of the lock. 6  I opened to my beloved; but my beloved had withdrawn himself, and was gone: my soul failed when he spake: I sought him, but I could not find him; I called him, but he gave me no answer. 7  The watchmen that went about the city found me, they smote me, they wounded me; the keepers of the walls took away my veil from me. 8  I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, if ye find my beloved, [†]that ye tell him, that I am sick of love.

9 ¶ What is thy beloved more than another beloved, O thou fairest among women? what is thy beloved more than another beloved, that thou dost so charge us? 10  My beloved is white and ruddy, [†]the chiefest among ten thousand. 11  His head is as the most fine gold, his locks are [∥]bushy, and black as a raven. 12 [*] His eyes are as the eyes of doves by the rivers of [‡]waters, washed with milk, and [†]fitly set. 13  His cheeks are as a bed of spices, as [∥]sweet flowers: his lips like lilies, dropping sweet smelling myrrh. 14  His hands are as gold rings set with the beryl: his belly is as bright ivory overlaid with sapphires. 15  His legs are as pillars of marble, set upon sockets of fine gold: his countenance is as Lebanon, excellent as the cedars. 16 [†] His mouth is most sweet: yea, he is altogether lovely. This is my beloved, and this is my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem.

6

1  Whither is thy beloved gone, O thou fairest among women? whither is thy beloved turned aside? that we may seek him with thee. 2  My beloved is gone down into his garden, to the beds of spices, to feed in the gardens, and to gather lilies. 3 [*]I am my beloved’s, and my beloved is mine: he feedeth among the lilies.

4 ¶ Thou art beautiful, O my love, as Tirzah, comely as Jerusalem, terrible as an army with banners. 5  Turn away thine eyes from me, for [∥]they have overcome me: thy hair is [*][‡]as a flock of goats that appear from Gilead. 6  Thy teeth are as a flock of sheep which go up from the washing, whereof every one beareth twins, and there is not one barren among them. 7  As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples within thy locks. 8  There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, and virgins without number. 9  My dove, my undefiled is but one; she is the only one of her mother, she is the choice one of her that bare her. The daughters saw her, and blessed her; yea, the queens and the concubines, and they praised her.

10 ¶ Who is she that looketh forth as the morning, fair as the moon, clear as the sun, and terrible as an army with banners?

11  I went down into the garden of nuts to see the fruits of the valley, and to see whether the vine flourished, and the pomegranates budded. 12 [†] Or ever I was aware, my soul [∥]made me like the chariots of Amminadib. 13  Return, return, O Shulamite; return, return, that we may look upon thee. What will ye see in the Shulamite? As it were the company [∥]of two armies.

7

1  How beautiful are thy feet with shoes, O prince’s daughter! the joints of thy thighs are like jewels, the work of the hands of a cunning workman. 2  Thy navel is like a round goblet, which wanteth not [†]liquor: thy belly is like an heap of wheat set about with lilies. 3 [*] Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins. 4  Thy neck is as a tower of ivory; thine eyes like the fishpools in Heshbon, by the gate of Bath-rabbim: thy nose is as the tower of Lebanon which looketh toward Damascus. 5  Thine head upon thee is like [∥]Carmel, and the hair of thine head like purple; the king is [†]held in the galleries. 6  How fair and how pleasant art thou, O love, for delights! 7  This thy stature is like to a palm tree, and thy breasts to clusters of grapes. 8  I said, I will go up to the palm tree, I will take hold of the boughs thereof: now also thy breasts shall be as clusters of the vine, and the smell of thy nose like apples; 9  And the roof of thy mouth like the best wine for my beloved, that goeth down [†]sweetly, causing the lips [∥]of those that are asleep to speak.

10 ¶ [*]I am my beloved’s, and his desire is toward me. 11  Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the field; let us lodge in the villages. 12  Let us get up early to the vineyards; let us see if the vine flourish, whether the tender grape [†]appear, and the pomegranates bud forth: there will I give thee my loves. 13  The [*]mandrakes give a smell, and at our gates are all manner of pleasant fruits, new and old, which I have laid up for thee, O my beloved.

8

1  O that thou wert as my brother, that sucked the breasts of my mother! when I should find thee without, I would kiss thee; yea, [†]I should not be despised. 2  I would lead thee, and bring thee into my mother’s house, who would instruct me: I would cause thee to drink of [*]spiced wine of the juice of my pomegranate. 3 [*] His left hand should be under my head, and his right hand should embrace me. 4 [*] I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, [†]that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, until he please.

5 [*]Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness, leaning upon her beloved? I raised thee up under the apple tree: there thy mother brought thee forth: there she brought thee forth that bare thee.

6 ¶ Set me as a seal upon thine heart, as a seal upon thine arm: for love is strong as death; jealousy is [†]cruel as the grave: the coals thereof are coals of fire, which hath a most vehement flame. 7  Many waters cannot quench love, neither can the floods drown it: if a man would give all the substance of his house for love, it would utterly be contemned.

8 ¶ We have a little sister, and she hath no breasts: what shall we do for our sister in the day when she shall be spoken for? 9 If she be a wall, we will build upon her a palace of silver: and if she be a door, we will inclose her with boards of cedar. 10 I am a wall, and my breasts like towers: then was I in his eyes as one that found [†]favour. 11  Solomon had a vineyard at Baal-hamon; he let out the vineyard unto keepers; every one for the fruit thereof was to bring a thousand pieces of silver. 12  My vineyard, which is mine, is before me: thou, O Solomon, must have a thousand, and those that keep the fruit thereof two hundred.

13  Thou that dwellest in the gardens, the companions hearken to thy voice: cause me to hear it.

14 ¶ [†]Make haste, my beloved, and be thou like to a roe or to a young hart upon the mountains of spices.

* 1.2 ch. 4. 10.

† 1.2 Heb. thy loves.

* 1.4 John 6. 44.

∥ 1.4 Or, they love thee uprightly.

∥ 1.7 Or, as one that is veiled.

∥ 1.14 Or, cypress.

* 1.15 ch 4 1. &c 5 12.

∥ 1.15 Or, my companion.

∥ 1.17 Or, galleries.

† 2.3 Heb. I delighted and sat down, &c.

† 2.3 Heb. palate.

† 2.4 Heb. house of wine.

† 2.5 Heb. straw me with apples.

* 2.6 ch. 8 3.

† 2.7 Heb I adjure you.

* 2.7 ch 3. 5. &c 8. 4.

* 2.9 ver. 17.

† 2.9 Heb flourishing.

* 2.16 ch. 6. 8. &c 7. 10.

* 2.17 ch. 4. 6.

* 2.17 ch 8 14.

∥ 2.17 Or, of division.

* 3.5 ch. 2. 7. &c 8 4.

* 3.6 ch. 8 5.

∥ 3.9 Or, a bed.

* 4.1 ch. 1. 15. &c 5. 12.

* 4.1 ch. 6. 5, 6.

∥ 4.1 Or, that eat of, &c.

* 4.5 ch. 7 3.

* 4.6 ch. 2. 17.

† 4.6 Heb. breathe.

‡ 4.6 [1611 mountains]

* 4.7 Eph. 5. 27.

* 4.8 Deut. 3. 9.

∥ 4.9 Or, taken away my heart.

* 4.10 ch. 1. 2.

† 4.12 Heb. barred.

∥ 4.13 Or, cypress.

∥ 5.1 Or, and be drunken with loves.

∥ 5.4 Or, (as some read) in me.

† 5.5 Heb. passing, or, running about.

† 5.8 Heb. what.

† 5.10 Heb. a standard-bearer.

∥ 5.11 Or, curled.

* 5.12 ch. 1. 15. &c 4. 1.

‡ 5.12 [1611 water]

† 5.12 Heb. sitting in fulness, that is, fitly placed, and set as a precious stone in the foil of a ring.

∥ 5.13 Or, towers of perfumes.

† 5.16 Heb. His palate.

* 6.3 ch. 2. 16. &c 7. 10.

∥ 6.5 Or, they have puffed me up.

* 6.5 ch 4 1, 2.

‡ 6.5 [1611 omits as]

† 6.12 Heb. I knew not.

∥ 6.12 Or, set me on the chariots of my willing people.

∥ 6.13 Or, of Mahanaim.

† 7.2 Heb. mixture.

* 7.3 ch. 4. 5.

∥ 7.5 Or, crimson.

† 7.5 Heb. bound.

† 7.9 Heb. straightly.

∥ 7.9 Or, of the ancient.

* 7.10 ch. 2. 16. &c 6. 3.

† 7.12 Heb. open.

* 7.13 Gen. 30. 14.

† 8.1 Heb. they should not despise me.

* 8.2 Prov. 9. 2.

* 8.3 ch. 2. 6.

* 8.4 ch. 2. 7. &c 3 5.

† 8.4 Heb. why should ye stir up, or why, &c.

* 8.5 ch. 3. 6.

† 8.6 Heb. hard.

† 8.10 Heb. peace.

† 8.14 Heb. Flee away.

Susanna

The History of Susanna [in Daniel]

Set apart from the beginning of Daniel, because it is not in Hebrew, as neither the Narration of [*]Bel and the Dragon.

1

1 There dwelt a man in Babylon, called [a]Joacim:

2 And he took a wife, whose name was [b]Susanna, the daughter of [a]Chelcias, a very [x]fair woman, and one that feared the Lord.

3 Her parents also were [c]righteous, and taught their daughter according to the law of Moses.

4 Now Joacim was [d]a great rich man, and had a [e]fair garden joining unto his house: and to him resorted the Jews; because he was more honourable than all others.

5 [f]The same year were appointed two of the [g]ancients of the people to be judges, such as the [h]Lord spake of, [i]that wickedness came from Babylon from ancient judges, who [j]seemed to govern the people.

6 These [k]kept much at Joacim’s house: and all that had any suits in law came unto them.

7 Now when the people departed away [l]at noon, Susanna went into her husband’s [e]garden to walk.

8 And the two elders saw her going in every day, and walking; so that their lust was inflamed toward her.

9 And [m]they perverted their own mind, and turned away their eyes, that they might not look unto heaven, nor remember just judgments.

10 And albeit they both were [n]wounded with her love, yet durst not one shew another his grief.

11 For they were ashamed to declare their lust, that they desired to have to do with her.

12 Yet they watched diligently from day to day to see her.

13 And the one said to the other, Let us now go home: [l]for it is dinner time.

14 So when they were gone out, they parted the one from the other, and turning back again they came to the same place; and after that they had asked one another the cause, they acknowledged their lust: then appointed they a time both together, when they might find her alone.

15 And it fell out, as they watched a [o]fit time, she went in [*]as before with two maids only, and she was desirous to wash herself in the [e]garden: for it was hot.

16 And there was no body there save the two elders, that had hid themselves, and watched her.

17 Then she said to her maids, Bring me oil and washing balls, and shut the [e]garden doors, that I may wash me.

18 And they did as she bade them, and shut the [e]garden doors, and went out themselves at [*]privy doors to fetch the things that she had commanded them: but they saw not the elders, because they were hid.

19 Now when the maids were gone forth, the two elders rose up, and ran unto her, saying,

20 Behold, the garden doors are shut, that no man can see us, and we are in love with thee; therefore consent unto us, and lie with us.

21 If thou wilt not, we will bear witness against thee, that a young man was with thee: and therefore thou didst send away thy maids from thee.

22 Then Susanna [p]sighed, and said, I am straitened on every side: for if I do this thing, [q]it is death unto me: and if I do it not I cannot escape your hands.

23 It is better for me to fall into your hands, and not do it, than to sin in the sight of the Lord.

24 With that Susanna cried with a loud voice: and the two elders cried out against her.

25 Then ran the one, and opened the garden door.

26 So when the servants of the house heard the cry in the garden, they rushed in at the [r]privy door, to see what was done unto her.

27 But when the elders had declared their matter, the servants were greatly ashamed: for there was never such a report made of Susanna.

28 And it came to pass the next day, [s]when the people were assembled to her husband Joacim, the two elders came also full of mischievous [t]imagination against Susanna [q]to put her to death;

29 And said before the people, Send for Susanna, the daughter of [a]Chelcias, [a]Joacim’s wife. And so they sent.

30 So she came with her father and mother, her children, and all her kindred.

31 Now Susanna was a very [u]delicate woman, and [x]beauteous to behold.

32 And these wicked men commanded to uncover her face, ([y]for she was covered) that they might be filled with her beauty.

33 Therefore [z]her friends and all that saw her wept.

34 Then the two elders stood up in the midst of the people, and [a]laid their hands upon her head.

35 And she weeping looked up toward heaven: for her heart trusted in the Lord.

36 And the elders said, As we walked in the garden alone, this woman came in with two maids, and shut the garden doors, and sent the maids away.

37 Then a young man, who there was hid, came unto her, and lay with her.

38 Then we that stood in a corner of the garden, seeing this wickedness, ran unto them.

39 And when we saw them together, the man we could not hold: for he was stronger than we, and opened the door, and leaped out.

40 But having taken this woman, we asked who the young man was, but she would not tell us: these things do we testify.

41 Then the assembly believed them as those that were [b]the elders and judges of the people: so [c]they condemned her to death.

42 Then Susanna cried out with a loud voice, and said, O everlasting God, [d]that knowest the secrets, and [e]knowest all things before they be:

43 Thou knowest that they have borne false witness against me, and, behold, I must die; whereas I never did such things as these men have maliciously invented against me.

44 And the Lord heard her voice.

45 Therefore [f]when she was led [c]to be put to death, [g]the Lord raised up the holy spirit of a young youth whose name was Daniel:

46 Who cried with a loud voice, [h]I am clear from the blood of this woman.

47 Then all the people turned them toward him, and said, What mean these words that thou hast spoken?

48 So he standing in the midst of them said, Are ye such fools, ye sons of Israel, that without examination or knowledge of the truth ye have condemned [n]a daughter of Israel?

49 Return again to the place of judgment: for they have borne false witness against her.

50 Wherefore all the people turned again in haste, and [b]the elders said unto him, Come, [i]sit down among us, and shew it us, seeing God hath given thee the honour of an elder.

51 Then said Daniel unto them, Put these two aside one far from another, and I will examine them.

52 So when they were put asunder one from another, he called one of them, and said unto him, O thou that art waxen old in wickedness, now thy sins which thou hast committed aforetime are come to light.

53 For thou hast pronounced false judgment and hast condemned the innocent and hast let the guilty go free; albeit the Lord saith, [j]The innocent and righteous shalt thou not slay.

54 Now then, if thou hast seen her, tell me, Under what tree sawest thou them companying together? Who answered, Under a [*]mastick tree.

55 And Daniel said, Very well; thou hast lied against thine own head; for even now the angel of God hath received the sentence of God to [k]cut thee in two.

56 So he put him aside, and commanded to bring the other, and said unto him, O thou seed of [l]Chanaan, and not of Juda, beauty hath deceived thee, and lust hath [m]perverted thine heart.

57 Thus have ye dealt with [n]the daughters of Israel, and they for fear companied with you: but [n]the daughter of Juda would not abide your wickedness.

58 Now therefore tell me, Under what tree didst thou take them companying together? Who answered, Under an [*]holm tree.

59 Then said Daniel unto him, Well; thou hast also lied against thine own head: for the angel of God waiteth with the sword to [k][o]cut thee in two, that he may destroy you.

60 With that all [p]the assembly cried out with a loud voice, and praised God, who saveth [q]them that trust in him.

61 And they arose against the two elders, for [r]Daniel had convicted them of false witness by their own mouth:

62 And [s]according to the law of Moses they did unto them in such sort as they maliciously intended to do to their neighbour: and they put them to death. Thus the innocent blood was saved the same day.

63 Therefore [t]Chelcias and his wife praised God for their daughter Susanna, with Joacim her husband, and all the kindred, because there was no dishonesty found in her.

64 From that day forth was Daniel had in great reputation in the sight of the people.

* Gr. Bel’s Dragon. Bel and Drag., title.

a 1.1 ver. 29, 63. Comp. Baruch 1. 7?

b 1.2 Comp. Luke 8. 3.

a 1.2 ver. 29, 63. Comp. Baruch 1. 7?

x 1.2 ver. 2 (Gk.).

c 1.3 Luke 1. 6.

d 1.4 Comp. Tobit 1. 13, 14, 22.

e 1.4 ver. 7, 15, 17, 18 (Gk.). See Ecclus. 24. 30.

f 1.5 Comp. Esth. 3. 8.

g 1.5 ver. 41, 50 (Gk.). See Judith 6. 16.

h 1.5 See Ecclus. 34. 24.

i 1.5 Comp. Jer. 29. 22,23.

j 1.5 Mark 10. 42 (Gk.).

k 1.6 See Acts 2. 42 (Gk.). So ver. 28.

l 1.7 Gen. 43. 16. ver. 13.

e 1.7 ver. 7, 15, 17, 18 (Gk.). See Ecclus. 24. 30.

m 1.9 So Num. 15. 39 (Gk.). ver. 56.

n 1.10 See Ecclus. 14. 1.

l 1.13 Gen. 43. 16. ver. 13.

o 1.15 See Luke 9. 62.

* 1.15 Gr. as yesterday and the day before. 1 Macc. 9. 44. See Gen. 31. 2 marg.

e 1.15 ver. 7, 15, 17, 18 (Gk.). See Ecclus. 24. 30.

e 1.17 ver. 7, 15, 17, 18 (Gk.). See Ecclus. 24. 30.

e 1.18 ver. 7, 15, 17, 18 (Gk.). See Ecclus. 24. 30.

* 1.18 Or, side doors. ver. 26.

p 1.22 2 Macc. 6. 30. Mark 8. 12 in the Gk.

q 1.22 ver. 28, 41, 45. See Lev. 20. 10.

r 1.26 ver. 18 marg.

s 1.28 So ver. 6.

t 1.28 Heb. 4. 12. 1 Pet. 4. 1 in the Gk.

q 1.28 ver. 28, 41, 45. See Lev. 20. 10.

a 1.29 ver. 29, 63. Comp. Baruch 1. 7?

a 1.29 ver. 29, 63. Comp. Baruch 1. 7?

u 1.31 Baruch 4. 26.

x 1.31 ver. 2 (Gk.).

y 1.32 Gen. 24. 65 or 2 Sam. 15. 30. & 19. 4.

z 1.33 1 Macc. 2. 15, 17. Mark 3. 21 in the Gk. Comp. ver. 30.

a 1.34 Lev. 24. 14.

b 1.41 ver. 5 (Gk.).

c 1.41 ver. 22.

d 1.42 See Acts 1. 24.

e 1.42 So Ps. 139. 1–4.

f 1.45 See Baruch 6. 18.

c 1.45 ver. 22.

g 1.45 2 Chr. 36. 22. Hagg. 1. 14 in the Gk.

h 1.46 Matt. 27. 24 (Gk.).

n 1.48 Comp. ver. 48.

b 1.50 ver. 5 (Gk.).

i 1.50 Comp. Luke 2. 46.

j 1.53 Cited from Exod. 23. 7.

* 1.54 Gr. lentisk tree.

k 1.55 So ver. 59. Matt. 24. 51. Luke 12. 46. Comp. Jer. 1. 11, 12. Dan. 5. 25–28.

l 1.56 Ezek. 16. 3. Hos. 12. 7 marg.

m 1.56 So ver. 9.

n 1.57 Comp. ver. 48.

n 1.57 Comp. ver. 48.

* 1.58 Or, kind of oak.

k 1.59 So ver. 59. Matt. 24. 51. Luke 12. 46. Comp. Jer. 1. 11, 12. Dan. 5. 25–28.

o 1.59 Heb. 11 37 (Gk.).

p 1.60 ver. 41.

q 1.60 So ver. 35.

r 1.61 Ecclus. 42. 8 marg.

s 1.62 Deut. 19. 16–19. So Prov. 19. 5.

t 1.63 ver. 2, 29.

Titus

1
2
3

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO TITUS

1

1  Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the faith of God’s elect, and the acknowledging of the truth which is after godliness; 2 [∥] In hope of eternal life, which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world began; 3  But hath in due times manifested his word through preaching, which is committed unto me according to the commandment of God our Saviour; 4  To Titus, mine own son after the common faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ our Saviour.

5  For this cause left I thee in Crete, that thou shouldest set in order the things that are [∥]wanting, and ordain elders in every city, as I had appointed thee: 6  If any be blameless, the husband of one wife, having faithful children not accused of riot or unruly. 7  For a bishop must be blameless, as the steward of God; not selfwilled, not soon angry, [*]not given to wine, no striker, not given to filthy lucre; 8  But a lover of hospitality, a lover of [∥]good men, sober, just, holy, temperate; 9  Holding fast the faithful word [∥]as he hath been taught, that he may be able by sound doctrine both to exhort and to convince the gainsayers. 10  For there are many unruly and vain talkers and deceivers, specially they of the circumcision: 11  Whose mouths must be stopped, who subvert whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre’s sake. 12  One of themselves, even a prophet of their own, said, The Cretians are alway liars, evil beasts, slow bellies. 13  This witness is true. Wherefore rebuke them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith; 14  Not giving heed to Jewish fables, and commandments of men, that turn from the truth. 15  Unto the pure all things are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure; but even their mind and conscience is defiled. 16  They profess that they know God; but in works they deny him, being abominable, and disobedient, and unto every good work [∥]reprobate.

2

1  But speak thou the things which become sound doctrine: 2  That the aged men be [∥]sober, grave, temperate, sound in faith, in charity, in patience. 3  The aged women likewise, that they be in behaviour as becometh [∥]holiness, not [∥]false accusers, not given to much wine, teachers of good things; 4  That they may teach the young women to be [∥]sober, to love their husbands, to love their children, 5  To be discreet, chaste, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed. 6  Young men likewise exhort to be [∥]sober minded. 7  In all things shewing thyself a pattern of good works: in doctrine shewing uncorruptness, gravity, sincerity, 8  Sound speech, that cannot be condemned; that he that is of the contrary part may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of you. 9  Exhort servants to be obedient unto their own masters, and to please them well in all things; not [∥]answering again; 10  Not purloining, but shewing all good fidelity; that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things. 11  For the grace of God [∥]that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men, 12  Teaching us that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly, in this present world; 13  Looking for that blessed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ; 14  Who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himself a peculiar people, zealous of good works. 15  These things speak, and exhort, and rebuke with all authority. Let no man despise thee.

3

1  Put them in mind to be subject to principalities and powers, to obey magistrates, to be ready to every good work, 2  To speak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, shewing all meekness unto all men. 3  For we ourselves also were sometimes foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving divers lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another. 4  But after that the kindness and [∥]love of God our Saviour toward man appeared, 5  Not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to his mercy he saved us, by the washing of regeneration, and renewing of the Holy Ghost; 6  Which he shed on us [†]abundantly through Jesus Christ our Saviour; 7  That being justified by his grace, we should be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life. 8  This is a faithful saying, and these things I will that thou affirm constantly, that they which have believed in God might be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable unto men. 9  But avoid foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, and strivings about the law; for they are unprofitable and vain. 10  A man that is an heretick after the first and second admonition reject; 11  Knowing that he that is such is subverted, and sinneth, being condemned of himself.

12  When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, be diligent to come unto me to Nicopolis: for I have determined there to winter. 13  Bring Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey diligently, that nothing be wanting unto them. 14  And let ours also learn to [∥]maintain good works for necessary uses, that they be not unfruitful. 15  All that are with me salute thee. Greet them that love us in the faith. Grace be with you all. Amen.

It was written to Titus, ordained the first bishop of the church of the Cretians, from Nicopolis of Macedonia.

∥ 1.2 Or, For.

∥ 1.5 Or, left undone.

* 1.7 1 Tim. 3. 3.

∥ 1.8 Or, good things.

∥ 1.9 Or, in teaching.

∥ 1.16 Or, void of judgment.

∥ 2.2 Or, vigilant.

∥ 2.3 Or, holy women.

∥ 2.3 Or, makebates.

∥ 2.4 Or, wise.

∥ 2.6 Or, discreet.

∥ 2.9 Or, gainsaying.

∥ 2.11 Or, that bringeth salvation to all men, hath appeared.

∥ 3.4 Or, pity.

† 3.6 Gr richly.

∥ 3.14 Or, profess honest trades.

Tobit

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14

The Book of Tobit

1

1 The book of the [*]words of Tobit, son of Tobiel, the son of Ananiel, the son of Aduel, the son of Gabael, of the seed of Asael, of the tribe of Nephthali;

2 Who in the time of [*]Enemessar king of the Assyrians [a]was led captive out of [b]Thisbe, which is at [c]the right hand of that city, which is called [*]properly Nephthali in Galilee above Aser.

3 I Tobit have walked all the days of my life in the ways of truth and justice, and [d]I did many almsdeeds to my brethren, and my nation, who came with me to Nineve, into the land of the Assyrians.

4 And when I was in mine own country, in the land of Israel being but young, [e]all the tribe of Nephthali my father fell from the house of Jerusalem, which was chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, that all the tribes should sacrifice there, where the temple of the habitation of the most High was consecrated and built [f]for all ages.

5 Now all the tribes which together revolted, and the house of my father Nephthali, sacrificed [*]unto the [g]heifer Baal.

6 But I alone went often to Jerusalem at the feasts, [h]as it was ordained unto all the people of Israel by an everlasting decree, having [i]the firstfruits and [j]tenths of increase, with [k]that which was first shorn; and them gave I at the altar to the priests the children of Aaron.

7 The first tenth part of all increase I gave to the sons of [*]Aaron, who ministered at Jerusalem: [l]another tenth part I sold away, and went, and spent it every year at Jerusalem:

8 And the third I gave unto them to whom it was meet, as Debora my father’s mother had commanded me, because I was left an orphan by my father.

9 Furthermore, when I was come to the age of a man, I married Anna [m]of mine own kindred, and of her I begat Tobias.

10 And when [a]we were carried away captives to Nineve, all my brethren and those that were of my kindred [n]did eat of the bread of the Gentiles.

11 But I kept [*]myself from eating;

12 Because I remembered God with all my heart.

13 And the most High gave me grace and favour before Enemessar, so that I was his [*]purveyor.

14 And I went into Media, and left in trust with Gabael, [nn]the brother of Gabrias, at [o]Rages [*]a city of [p]Media ten talents of silver.

15 Now when Enemessar was dead, Sennacherib his son reigned in his stead; [*]whose estate was troubled, that I could not go into [p]Media.

16 And in the time of Enemessar [d]I gave many alms to my brethren, and [q]gave my bread to the hungry,

17 [q]And my clothes to the naked: and if I saw any of my nation dead, or cast [*]about the walls of Nineve, [r]I buried him.

18 And if the king Sennacherib had slain any, when he was come, and [s]fled from Judea, I buried them privily; for in his wrath he killed many; but the bodies were not found, when they were sought for of the king.

19 And when one of the Ninevites went and complained of me to the king, that I buried them, and hid myself; understanding that I was sought for to be put to death, I withdrew myself for fear.

20 Then all my goods were forcibly taken away, neither was there any thing left me, beside [t]my wife Anna and my son Tobias.

21 And there passed not five and fifty days, before [u]two of his sons killed him, and they fled into the mountains of [u]Ararath; and [*][u]Sarchedonus his son reigned in his stead; who appointed over his father’s accounts, and over all his affairs, Achiacharus my brother Anael’s son.

22 And Achiacharus intreating for me, I returned to Nineve. Now Achiacharus was [w]cupbearer, and [x]keeper of the signet, and steward, and overseer of the accounts: and [*]Sarchedonus appointed him [y]next unto him: and he was my [z]brother’s son.

2

1 Now when I was come home again, and my wife Anna was restored unto me, with my son Tobias, in [a]the feast of Pentecost, which is [a]the holy feast of the seven weeks, there was a good dinner prepared me, in the which I sat down to eat.

2 And when I saw abundance of meat, I said to my son, Go and bring what poor man soever thou shalt find out of our brethren, who is mindful of the Lord; and, lo, I tarry for thee.

3 But he came again, and said, Father, one of our nation is strangled, and is cast out in the marketplace.

4 Then before I had tasted of any meat, I started up, and took him up into a room until the going down of the sun.

5 Then I returned, and washed myself, and ate my meat in heaviness,

6 Remembering that prophecy of Amos, as he said, [b]Your feasts shall be turned into mourning, and all your mirth into lamentation.

7 Therefore I wept: and after the going down of the sun I went and made a grave, and [c]buried him.

8 But my neighbours mocked me, and said, This man is not yet afraid to be put to death for this matter: [d]who fled away; and yet, lo, he burieth the dead again.

9 The same night also I [e]returned from the burial, and slept by the wall of my [f]courtyard, [g]being polluted and my face was uncovered:

10 And I knew not that there were [*]sparrows in the wall, and mine eyes being open, the sparrows muted warm dung into mine eyes, and [*]a whiteness came in mine eyes: and I went to the physicians, but they helped me not: moreover [h]Achiacharus did nourish me, until I went into [i]Elymais.

11 And my wife Anna [*]did take women’s works to do.

12 And when she had sent [*]them home to the owners, they paid her wages, and gave her also besides a kid.

13 And when it was in my house, and began to cry, I said unto her, From whence is this kid? is it not stolen? render it to the owners; [k]for it is not lawful to eat any thing that is stolen.

14 But she replied upon me, It was given for a gift more than the wages. Howbeit I did not believe her, but bade her render it to the owners: and I was abashed at her. [l]But she replied upon me, Where are thine alms and [m]thy righteous deeds? [*]behold, thou and all thy works are known.

3

1 Then I being grieved did weep, and in my sorrow prayed, saying,

2 [a]O Lord, thou art just, and all thy works and all thy ways are mercy and truth, and thou judgest truly and justly for ever.

3 Remember me, and look on me, punish me not for my sins and [b]ignorances, and the sins of my fathers, who have sinned before thee:

4 For they obeyed not thy commandments: wherefore thou hast delivered us [c]for a spoil, and unto captivity, and unto death, and for [d]a proverb of reproach to all the nations among whom we are dispersed.

5 And now thy judgments are many and true: deal with me according to my sins and my fathers’: because we have not kept thy commandments, neither have walked in truth before thee.

6 Now therefore [e]deal with me as seemeth best unto thee, and [f]command my spirit to be taken from me, that I may be [*]dissolved, and become earth: [f]for [g]it is profitable for me to die rather than to live, because [h]I have heard false reproaches, and have much sorrow: command therefore that I may now be delivered out of this distress, and go into the everlasting place: [i]turn not thy face away from me.

7 It came to pass the same day, that in [k]Ecbatane a city of [l]Media Sara the daughter of Raguel was also reproached by her father’s maids;

8 Because that she had been married to seven husbands, whom [m]Asmodeus the evil spirit had killed, before they had lain with her. Dost thou not know, said they, that thou hast strangled thine husbands? thou hast had already seven husbands, neither wast thou named after any of them.

9 Wherefore dost thou beat us for them? if they be dead, go thy ways after them, let us never see of thee either son or daughter.

10 When she heard these things, she was very sorrowful, so that she thought to have strangled herself; and she said, I am the only daughter of my father, and if I do this, it shall be a reproach unto him, and [n]I shall bring his old age with sorrow unto the grave.

11 Then she prayed [o]toward the window, and said, [oo]Blessed art thou, O Lord my God, and thine holy and glorious name is blessed and honourable for ever: [p]let all thy works praise thee for ever.

12 And now, O Lord, [q]I set mine eyes and my face toward thee,

13 And say, [r]Take me out of the earth, that I may hear no more the reproach.

14 Thou knowest, Lord, that I am pure from all sin with man,

15 And that I never polluted my name, nor the name of my father, in the land of my captivity: I am the only daughter of my father, neither hath he any child to be his heir, neither any near [*]kinsman, nor any son of his alive, to whom I may keep myself for a wife: my seven husbands are already dead; and why should I live? but if it please not thee that I should die, command some regard to be had of me, and pity taken of me, that I hear no more reproach.

16 So the prayers of them both were heard before the majesty of the great God.

17 And [s]Raphael was sent to heal them both, that is, to [t]scale away the whiteness of Tobit’s eyes, and to give Sara the daughter of Raguel for a wife to Tobias the son of Tobit; and to bind [m]Asmodeus the evil spirit; because [u]she belonged to Tobias by right of inheritance. [x]The selfsame time came Tobit home, and entered into his house, and Sara the daughter of Raguel came down from her upper chamber.

4

1 In that day Tobit remembered [a]the money which he had committed to Gabael in Rages of Media,

2 And said with himself, [b]I have wished for death; wherefore do I not call for my son Tobias that I may signify to him of the money before I die?

3 And when he had called him, he said, My son, when I am dead, bury me; and [c]despise not thy mother, [d]but honour her all the days of thy life, and do that which shall please her, and grieve her not.

4 Remember, my son, that she saw many dangers for thee, when thou wast in her womb: and when she is dead, bury her by me in one grave.

5 My son, be mindful of the Lord our God all thy days, and [e]let not thy will be set to sin, or to transgress his commandments: do uprightly all thy life long, and follow not the ways of unrighteousness.

6 For if thou deal truly, thy doings shall prosperously succeed to thee, and to all them that live justly.

7 [f]Give alms of thy substance; and when thou givest alms, [g]let not thine eye be envious, [h]neither turn thy face from any poor, and [i]the face of God shall not be turned away from thee.

8 [j]If thou hast abundance give alms accordingly: if thou have but a little, be not afraid to give according to that little:

9 For thou [k]layest up a good treasure for thyself against the day of necessity.

10 Because that [l]alms do deliver from death, and suffereth not to come into darkness.

11 For alms is a good gift unto all that give it in the sight of the most High.

12 [m]Beware of all whoredom, my son, and chiefly take a wife of the seed of thy fathers, and take not a strange woman to wife, which is not of thy father’s tribe: for we are the children of the [n]prophets, Noe, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob: remember, my son, that our fathers from the beginning, even that they all married wives of their own kindred, and were blessed in their children, and their seed shall inherit the land.

13 Now therefore, my son, love thy brethren, and despise not in thy heart thy brethren, the sons and daughters of thy people, in not taking a wife of them: for [o]in pride is destruction and much trouble, and in [p]lewdness is decay and great want: for [p][q]lewdness is the mother of famine.

14 [r]Let not the wages of any man, which hath wrought for thee, tarry with thee, but give him it out of hand: for if thou serve God, he will also repay thee: be [s]circumspect my son, in all things thou doest, and be wise [t]in all thy conversation.

15 [u]Do that to no man which thou hatest: [x]drink not wine to make thee drunken: neither let drunkenness go with thee in thy journey.

16 [y]Give of thy bread to the hungry, and of thy garments to them that are naked; and [z]according to thine abundance give alms: and [a]let not thine eye be envious, when thou givest alms.

17 [b]Pour out thy bread on the burial of the just, but give nothing to the wicked.

18 Ask counsel of all that are wise, and despise not any counsel that is profitable.

19 Bless the Lord thy God alway, and desire of him that [c]thy ways may be directed, and that all thy paths and counsels may prosper: for every nation hath not counsel; but [d]the Lord himself giveth all good things, and he humbleth whom he will, as he will; now therefore, my son, remember my commandments, neither let them be put out of thy mind.

20 And now I signify this to they that I committed ten talents to Gabael [*]the son of Gabrias at Rages in Media.

21 And fear not, my son, that [e]we are made poor: for [f]thou hast much wealth, if thou fear God, and depart from all sin, and do that which is pleasing in his sight.

5

1 Tobias then answered and said, Father, I will do all things which thou hast commanded me:

2 But how can I receive the money, seeing I know him not?

3 Then he gave him [a]the handwriting, and said unto him, Seek thee a man which may go with thee, whiles I yet live, and I will give him wages: and go and receive the money.

4 Therefore when he went to seek a man, he found [aa]Raphael that was an angel.

5 But he knew not; and he said unto him, Canst thou go with me to [b]Rages? and knowest thou those places well?

6 To whom the angel said, I will go with thee, and I know the way well: for I have lodged with our brother Gabael.

7 Then Tobias said unto him, Tarry for me, till I tell my father.

8 Then he said unto him, Go and tarry not. So he went in and said to his father, Behold, I have found one which will go with me. Then he said, Call him unto me, that I may know of what tribe he is, and whether he be a trusty man to go with thee.

9 So he called him, and he came in, and they saluted one another.

10 Then Tobit said unto him, Brother, shew me of what tribe and family thou art.

11 To whom he said, Dost thou seek for a tribe or family, or an hired man to go with thy son? Then Tobit said unto him, I would know, brother, thy kindred and name.

12 Then he said, I am Azarias, the son of Ananias the great, and of thy brethren.

13 Then Tobit said, [bb]Thou art welcome, brother; be not now angry with me, because I have enquired to know thy tribe and thy family; for thou art my brother, of [c]an honest and good stock: for I know Ananias and Jonathas, sons of that great Samaias, [d]as we went together to Jerusalem to worship, and offered the firstborn, and the tenths of the fruits; and they were not seduced [e]with the error of our brethren: my brother, thou art of a good stock.

14 But tell me, what wages shall I give thee? wilt thou [f]a drachm a day, and things necessary, as to mine own son?

15 Yea, moreover, if ye return safe, I will add something to thy wages.

16 So they were well pleased. Then said he to Tobias, Prepare thyself for the journey, and God send you a good journey. And when his son had prepared all things for the journey, his father said, Go thou with this man, and God, which dwelleth in heaven, prosper your journey, and the angel of God keep you company. So they went forth both, and [g]the young man’s dog with them.

17 But Anna his mother wept, and [h]said to Tobit, Why hast thou sent away our son? is he not the staff of our hand, [i]in going in and out before us?

18 [*]Be not greedy to add money to money: but let it be as refuse in respect of our child.

19 [*]For that which the Lord hath given us to live with doth suffice us.

20 Then said Tobit to her, Take no care, [l]my sister; he shall return in safety, and thine eyes shall see him.

21 For [m]the good angel will keep him company, and his journey shall be prosperous, and he shall return safe.

22 Then she made an end of weeping.

6

1 And as they went on their journey, they came in the evening to the river [a]Tigris, and they lodged there.

2 And when the young man went down to wash himself, a fish leaped out of the river, and would have devoured him.

3 Then the angel said unto him, Take the fish. And the young man laid hold of the fish, and [*]drew it to land.

4 To whom the angel said, Open the fish, and take the heart and the liver and the gall, and put them up safely.

5 So the young man did as the angel commanded him; and when they had roasted the fish, they did eat it: then they both went on their way, till they drew near to [b]Ecbatane.

6 Then the young man said to the angel, Brother Azarias, to what use is the heart and the liver and the gal of the fish?

7 And he said unto him, Touching the heart and the liver, if a devil or an [c]evil spirit trouble any, we must make a smoke thereof before the man or the woman, and the party shall be no more vexed.

8 As for the gall, it is good [cc]to anoint a man that hath whiteness in his eyes, and he shall be healed.

9 And when they were come near to [d]Rages,

10 The angel said to the young man, Brother, to day we shall lodge with [e]Raguel, who is thy cousin; he also hath [f]one only daughter, named Sara; I will speak for her, that she may be given thee for a wife.

11 For to thee doth the [*][g]right of her appertain, seeing thou only art of her kindred.

12 And the maid is fair and wise: now therefore hear me, and I will speak to her father; and when we return from [d]Rages we will celebrate the marriage: for I know that Raguel cannot marry her to another according [g]to the law of Moses, but [h]he shall be guilty of death, because the right of inheritance doth rather appertain to thee than to any other.

13 Then the young man answered the angel, I have heard, brother Azarias that this maid hath been given to seven men, who all died in [i]the marriage chamber.

14 And now I am the only son of my father, and I am afraid, lest if I go in unto her, I die, as the other before: for a [j]wicked spirit loveth her, which hurteth no body, [k]but those which come unto her; wherefore I also fear lest I die, and [l]bring my father’s and my mother’s life because of me to the grave with sorrow: for they have no other son to bury them.

15 Then the angel said unto him, Dost thou not remember the precepts which thy father gave thee, [m]that thou shouldest marry a wife of thine own kindred? wherefore hear me, O my brother; for she shall be given thee to wife; and make thou no reckoning of [j]the evil spirit; for this same night shall she be given thee in marriage.

16 And when thou shalt come into [i]the marriage chamber, thou shalt take the [*]ashes of perfume, and shalt lay upon them some of the heart and liver of the fish, and shalt make a smoke with it:

17 And [j]the devil shall smell it, and flee away, and never come again any more: but when thou shalt come to her, rise up both of you, and pray to God which is merciful, who will have pity on you, and save you: fear not, for she is appointed unto thee from the beginning; and thou shalt preserve her, and she shall go with thee. Moreover I suppose that she shall bear thee children. Now when Tobias had heard these things, he loved her, and his heart was [*]effectually joined to her.

7

1 And when they were come to [a]Ecbatane, they came to the house of Raguel, and Sara met them: and after they had saluted one another, she brought them into the house.

2 Then said Raguel to Edna his wife, How like is this young man to Tobit my cousin!

3 And Raguel asked them, From whence are ye, brethren? To whom they said, We are [b]of the sons of Nephthalim, which are captives in Nineve.

4 Then he said to them, Do ye know Tobit our kinsman? And they said, We know him. [c]Then said he, Is he in good health?

5 And they said, He is both alive, and in good health: and Tobias said, He is my father.

6 Then Raguel leaped up, and kissed him, and wept,

7 And blessed him, and said unto him, Thou art the son of [d]an honest and good man. But when he had heard that Tobit was blind, he was sorrowful, and wept.

8 And likewise Edna his wife and Sara his daughter wept. Moreover they [e]entertained them cheerfully; and after that they had killed [*]a ram of the flock, they set store of meat on the table. Then said Tobias to [f]Raphael, Brother Azarias, speak of those things of which thou didst talk in the way, and let this business be dispatched.

9 So he communicated the matter with Raguel: and Raguel said to Tobias, Eat and drink, and make merry:

10 For it is meet that thou shouldest marry my daughter: nevertheless I will declare unto thee the truth.

11 I have given my daughter in marriage to seven men, who died that night they came in unto her: nevertheless for the present be merry. But Tobias said, I will eat nothing here, till we agree and swear one to another.

12 Raguel said, Then take her from henceforth [g]according to the [*]manner, for thou art her cousin, and she is thine, and the merciful God give you good success in all things.

13 Then he called his daughter Sara, and she came to her father, and he took her by the hand, and gave her to be wife to Tobias, saying, Behold, take her [h]after the law of Moses, and lead her away to thy father. And he blessed them;

14 And called [i]Edna his wife, and took [k]paper, and did write an instrument of covenants, and [l]sealed it.

15 Then they began to eat.

16 After Raguel called his wife Edna, and said unto her, [m]Sister, prepare another [n]chamber, and bring her in thither.

17 Which when she had done as he had bidden her, she brought her thither: and she wept, and she [*]received the tears of her daughter, and said unto her,

18 [o]Be of good comfort, my daughter; the Lord of heaven and earth give thee joy for this thy sorrow: [o]be of good comfort, my daughter.

8

1 And when they had supped, they brought Tobias in unto her.

2 And as he went, he remembered the words of [a]Raphael, and took the [*]ashes of the perfumes, and put the heart and the liver of the fish thereupon, and made a smoke therewith.

3 The which smell when [b]the evil spirit had smelled, he fled into the utmost parts of Egypt, and [c]the angel bound him.

4 And after that they were both shut in together, Tobias rose out of the bed, and said, [d]Sister, arise, and let us pray that God would have pity on us.

5 Then began Tobias to say, [e]Blessed art thou, O God of our fathers, and blessed is thy holy and glorious name for ever; let the heavens bless thee, and all thy creatures.

6 [f]Thou madest Adam, and gavest him Eve his wife for an helper and stay: of them came mankind: thou hast said, [g]It is not good that man should be alone; let us make unto him an aid like unto himself.

7 And now, O Lord, I take not this my [d]sister for lust but uprightly: therefore mercifully ordain that we may become aged together.

8 And she said with him, Amen.

9 So they slept both that night. And Raguel arose, and went and made a grave,

10 Saying, I fear lest he also be dead.

11 But when Raguel was come into his house,

12 He said unto his wife Edna. Send one of the maids, and let her see whether he be alive: if he be not, that we may bury him, and no man know it.

13 So the maid opened the door, and went in, and found them both asleep,

14 And came forth, and told them that he was alive.

15 Then Raguel praised God, and said, O God, thou art [e]worthy to be praised with all pure and holy praise; therefore [h]let thy saints praise thee with all thy creatures; and [i]let all thine angels and [k]thine elect praise thee for ever.

16 Thou art [e]to be praised, for thou hast made me joyful; and that is not come to me which I suspected; but thou hast dealt with us according to thy great mercy.

17 Thou art [e]to be praised because thou hast had mercy of two that were the only begotten children of their fathers: grant them mercy, O Lord, and finish their life in health with joy and mercy.

18 Then Raguel bade his servants to fill the grave.

19 And he kept [l]the wedding feast [m]fourteen days.

20 For before the days of the marriage were finished, Raguel had said unto him by an oath, that he should not depart till [n]the fourteen days of the marriage were expired;

21 And then he should take [o]the half of his goods, and go in safety to his father; and should have the rest when [p]I and my wife be dead.

9

1 Then Tobias called [a]Raphael, and said unto him,

2 Brother Azarias, take with thee a servant, and two [b]camels, and go to [c]Rages of Media to Gabael, and bring me [c]the money, and bring him to the wedding.

3 For [d]Raguel hath sworn that I shall not depart.

4 But [e]my father counteth the days; and if I tarry long, he will be very sorry.

5 So [a]Raphael went out, and lodged with Gabael, and gave him [f]the handwriting: who brought forth bags which were sealed up, and gave them to him.

6 And early in the morning they went forth both together, and came to the wedding: and [*]Tobias blessed his wife.

10

1 Now Tobit his father [a]counted every day: and when the days of the journey were expired, and they came not,

2 Then Tobit said, Are they detained? or is Gabael dead, and there is no man to give him the money?

3 Therefore he was very sorry.

4 Then his wife said unto him, My son is dead, seeing he stayeth long; and she began to wail him, and said,

5 Now I care for nothing, my son, since I have let thee go, [b]the light of mine eyes.

6 To whom Tobit said, Hold thy peace, take no care, for he is safe.

7 But she said, Hold thy peace, and deceive me not; my son is dead. And she went out every day into the way which they went, and did eat no meat on the daytime, and ceased not whole nights to bewail her son Tobias, [c]until the fourteen days of the wedding were expired, which Raguel had sworn that he should spend there. Then Tobias said to Raguel, Let me go, for my father and my mother look no more to see me.

8 But his father in law said unto him, Tarry with me, and I will send to thy father, and they shall declare unto him how things go with thee.

9 But Tobias said, No; but let me go to my father.

10 Then Raguel arose, and gave him Sara his wife, and [d]half his goods, [e]servants, and cattle, and money:

11 And he blessed them, and sent them away, saying, The God of heaven give you a prosperous journey, my children.

12 And he said to his daughter, Honour thy father and thy mother in law, which are now thy parents, that I may hear good report of thee. And he kissed her. Edna also said to Tobias, The Lord of heaven restore thee, my dear brother, and grant that I may see thy children of my daughter Sara before I die, that I may rejoice before the Lord: behold, I [f]commit my daughter unto thee [*]of special trust; where are do not entreat her evil.

11

1 After these things Tobias went his way, praising God that he had given him a prosperous journey, and blessed Raguel and Edna his wife, and went on his way till they drew near unto Nineve.

2 Then [a]Raphael said to Tobias, Thou knowest, brother, how thou didst leave thy father:

3 Let us haste before thy wife, and prepare the house.

4 And take in thine hand [b]the gall of the fish. So they went their way, and [c]the dog went after them.

5 Now [d]Anna sat looking about toward the way for her son.

6 And when she espied him coming, she said to his father, Behold, thy son cometh, and the man that went with him.

7 Then said [a]Raphael, I know, Tobias, that thy father will open his eyes.

8 Therefore anoint thou his eyes with [b]the gall, and being pricked therewith, he shall rub, and the whiteness shall fall away, and he shall see thee.

9 Then Anna ran forth, and [e]fell upon the neck of her son, and said unto him, Seeing I have seen thee, my son, from henceforth I am content to die. And they wept both.

10 Tobit also went forth toward the door, and stumbled: but his son ran unto him,

11 And took hold of his father: and he strake of [b]the gall on his fathers’ eyes, saying, [f]Be of good hope, my father.

12 And when his eyes began to smart, he rubbed them;

13 And the whiteness [g]pilled away from the corners of his eyes: and when he saw his son, [e]he fell upon his neck.

14 And he wept, and said, [h]Blessed art thou, O God, and blessed is thy name for ever; and blessed are all thine [i]holy angels:

15 For [k]thou hast scourged, and hast taken pity on me: for, behold, I see my son Tobias. And his son went in rejoicing, and told his father the great things that had happened to him in Media.

16 Then Tobit went out to meet his daughter in law at the gate of Nineve, rejoicing and praising God: and they which saw him go marvelled, because he had received his sight.

17 But Tobias gave thanks before them, because God had mercy on him. And when he came near to Sara his daughter in law, he blessed her, saying, [l]Thou art welcome, daughter: [h]God be blessed, which hath brought thee unto us, and blessed be thy father and thy mother. And there was joy among all his brethren which were at Nineve.

18 And [m]Achiacharus, [*]and Nasbas his [n]brother’s son, came:

19 And Tobias’ [o]wedding was kept [p]seven days with great joy.

12

1 Then Tobit called his son Tobias, and said unto him, My son, see that the man have [a]his wages, which went with thee, and thou must give him more.

2 And Tobias said unto him, O father, it is no harm to me to give him half [b]of those things which I have brought:

3 For he hath [c]brought me again to thee in safety, and [d]made whole my wife, and [e]brought me the money, and [f]likewise healed thee.

4 Then the old man said, It is due unto him.

5 So he called the angel, and he said unto him, Take half of all that ye have brought and go away in safety.

6 Then he took them both apart, and said unto them, Bless God, [g]praise him, and magnify him, and [g]praise him for the things which he hath done unto you in the sight of all that live. It is good to praise God, and exalt his name, and [*]honourably to shew forth the works of God; therefore be not slack to praise him.

7 [h]It is good to keep close the secret of a king, but it is honourable to reveal the works of God. [i]Do that which is good, and no evil shall touch you.

8 [j]Prayer is good with fasting and [k]alms and [k]righteousness. [l]A little with righteousness is better than much with unrighteousness. It is better to give alms than to lay up gold:

9 [m]For alms doth deliver from death, and shall purge away all sin. [k]Those that exercise alms and righteousness shall be filled with life:

10 But [n]they that sin are enemies to their own life.

11 Surely I will keep close nothing from you. For I said, [h]It was good to keep close the secret of a king, but that it was honourable to reveal the works of God.

12 Now therefore, when [o]thou didst pray, and [p]Sara thy daughter in law, [q]I did bring the remembrance of your prayers before the Holy One: and [r]when thou didst bury the dead, I was with thee likewise.

13 And [s]when thou didst not delay to rise up, and leave thy dinner, [*]to go and cover the dead, thy good deed was not hid from me: but I was with thee.

14 And now God hath sent me to heal [f]thee and [d]Sara thy daughter in law.

15 I am [t]Raphael, one of [u]the seven [v]holy angels, [w]which present the prayers of the saints, and [x]which go in and out before the glory of the Holy One.

16 Then they were [y]both troubled, and [z]fell upon their faces: for they feared.

17 But he said unto them, Fear not, for it shall go well with you; praise God therefore.

18 For not of any favour of mine, but by the will of our God I came; wherefore praise him for ever.

19 All these days I did appear unto you; but [a]I did neither eat nor drink, but ye did see a vision.

20 Now therefore [b]give God thanks: for [c]I go up to him that sent me; but write all things which are done in a book.

21 And when they arose, they saw him no more.

22 Then they [b]confessed the great and wonderful works of God, and how the angel of the Lord had appeared unto them.

13

1 Then Tobit wrote a prayer of rejoicing, and said, Blessed be God that liveth for ever, and blessed be his kingdom.

2 For [a]he doth scourge, and hath mercy: [b]he leadeth down to hell, and bringeth up again: neither is there any that can avoid his hand.

3 [c]Confess him before the Gentiles, ye children of Israel: for [d]he hath scattered us among them.

4 There declare his greatness, and extol him before all the living: for he is our Lord, and he is the God our Father for ever.

5 And [a]he will scourge us for our iniquities, and will have mercy again, and [e]will gather us out of all nations, among whom he hath scattered us.

6 If ye turn to him [f]with your whole heart, and with your whole mind, and deal uprightly before him, then will he turn unto you, and will not hide his face from you. Therefore see what he will do with you, and [c]confess him with your whole mouth, and praise the Lord of might, and extol [g]the everlasting King. [d]In the land of my captivity do I [c]praise him, and declare his might and majesty to a sinful nation. O ye sinners, turn and do justice before him: [h]who can tell if he will accept you, and have mercy on you?

7 I will extol my God, and my soul shall praise [i]the King of heaven, and shall rejoice in his greatness.

8 Let all men speak, and let all [c]praise him for his righteousness.

9 O Jerusalem, [j]the holy city, [*]he will scourge thee for thy children’s works, and will have mercy again on [k]the sons of the righteous.

10 [c]Give praise to the Lord, for he is good: and praise [g]the everlasting King, that his tabernacle may be builded in thee again with joy, and [*]let him make joyful there in thee those that are captives, and love in thee [l]for ever those that are miserable.

11 [m]Many nations shall come from far to the name of the Lord God [n]with gifts in their hands, even gifts to [i]the King of heaven; all generations shall praise thee with great joy.

12 Cursed are all they which hate thee, and [o]blessed shall all be which love thee for ever.

13 Rejoice and be glad for [k]the children of the just: for they shall be gathered together, and shall bless the Lord of the just.

14 O [o]blessed are [p]they which love thee, for they shall rejoice in thy [*]peace: blessed are [p]they which have been sorrowful for all thy scourges; for they shall rejoice for thee, when they have seen all thy glory, and shall be glad for ever.

15 Let my soul bless God [q]the great King.

16 For [r]Jerusalem shall be built up with [r]sapphires and [r]emeralds, and precious stone: thy walls and towers and battlements with pure gold.

17 And the streets of Jerusalem shall be paved with [r]beryl and carbuncle and stones of [s]Ophir.

18 And all her streets shall say, [t]Alleluia; and they shall praise him, saying, Blessed be God, which hath extolled it for ever.

14

1 So Tobit made an end of [a]praising God.

2 And he was eight and fifty years old when he lost his sight, which was restored to him after eight years: and he gave alms, and he [*]increased in the fear of the Lord God, and [a]praised him.

3 And when he was very aged he called his son, and the sons of his son, and said to him, My son, take thy children; for, behold, I am aged, and am ready to depart out of this life.

4 Go into [b]Media my son, for I surely believe those things which [c]Jonas the prophet spake of Nineve, that it shall be overthrown; and that for a time peace shall rather be in Media; and that [d]our brethren shall lie scattered in the earth from that good land: and [d]Jerusalem shall be desolate, and [d]the house of God in it shall be burned, and shall be desolate for a time;

5 And that again God will have mercy on them, and bring them again into the land, where [e]they shall build a temple, but [f]not like to the first, until the time of that age be fulfilled; and [g]afterward they shall return from all places of their captivity, and build up Jerusalem gloriously, and the house of God shall be built in it [*]for ever with a glorious building, as the prophets have spoken thereof.

6 And [h]all nations shall turn, and fear the Lord God truly, and [i]shall bury their idols.

7 So shall all nations praise the Lord, and his people shall [a]confess God, and the Lord shall exalt his people; and all [k]those which love the Lord God in truth and justice shall rejoice, shewing mercy to our brethren.

8 And now, my son, depart out of Nineve, because that those things which [c]the prophet Jonas spake shall surely come to pass.

9 But keep thou the law and the commandments, and shew thyself merciful and just, [l]that it may go well with thee.

10 And bury me decently, and thy mother with me; but tarry no longer at Nineve. Remember, my son, how Aman handled [m]Achiacharus that brought him up, how [n]out of light he brought him into darkness, and how he rewarded him again: yet Achiacharus was [*]saved, but the other had his reward: for he went down into darkness. [*]Manasses gave alms, and escaped the snares of death [*]which they had set for him: but Aman fell into the snare, and perished.

11 Wherefore now, my son, consider [o]what alms doeth, and how righteousness doth deliver. When he had said these things, he gave up the ghost in the bed, [p]being an hundred and eight and fifty years old; and [*]he buried him honourably.

12 And when Anna his mother was dead, he buried her with his father. But Tobias departed with his wife and children to [q]Ecbatane to Raguel his father in law,

13 Where he became old with honour, and he buried his father and mother in law honourably, and he [*]inherited their substance, and his father Tobit’s.

14 And he died at [q]Ecbatane in [b]Media, being an hundred and seven and twenty years old.

15 But before he died he heard of the destruction of Nineve, which was taken by Nabuchodonosor and [r]Assuerus: and before his death he rejoiced over Nineve.

* 1.1 Or, acts.

* 1.2 [Or, Shalmaneser].

a 1.2 2 Kin. 17. 3, 23. & 18. 9. ver. 10.

b 1.2 Comp. 1 Kin. 21. 18.

c 1.2 See 1 Sam. 23. 19 marg.

* 1.2 Or, Kedes of Nephthali in Galilee. Judg. 4. 6. See Josh. 19. 37. Comp. 2 Kin. 15. 29.

d 1.3 ver. 16 (Gk.). Acts 9. 36.

e 1.4 1 Kin. 12. 19, 20, 28. Comp. ch. 5. 13.

f 1.4 ch. 13. 10 (Gk.). So Eph. 3. 21 (Gk.).

* 1.5 Or, to the power of Baal, or, the god Baal.

g 1.5 1 Kin. 12. 30.

h 1.6 See Deut. 16. 16.

i 1.6 Exod. 22. 29. Deut 12. 6.

j 1.6 ch. 5. 13 (Gk.).

k 1.6 Deut. 18. 4.

* 1.7 Or, Levi. See Numb. 18. 21.

l 1.7 Deut. 14. 25, 26.

m 1.9 Numb. 36. 7.

a 1.10 2 Kin. 17. 3, 23. & 18. 9. ver. 10.

n 1.10 See Acts 10. 14. Comp. Gen. 43. 32. Acts 15. 20.

* 1.11 Gr. my soul. ver. 12 (Gk.). See Esther 9. 31.

* 1.13 Gr. buyer.

nn 1.14 Comp. ch. 4. 20.

o 1.14 ch. 4. 1. & 5. 5. & 6. 12. & 9. 2. So ch. 6. 9. Judith 1. 5, 15.

* 1.14 Or, in the land. or, country of Media.

p 1.14 ch. 3. 7. & 14. 4, 14. See Acts 2. 9.

* 1.15 Gr. the ways of whom were unsettled.

p 1.15 ch. 3. 7. & 14. 4, 14. See Acts 2. 9.

d 1.16 ver. 16 (Gk.). Acts 9. 36.

q 1.16 ch. 4. 16. So Job 31. 17, 19, 20.

q 1.17 ch. 4. 16. So Job 31. 17, 19, 20.

* 1.17 Or, behind the walls.

r 1.17 2 Esdr. 2. 23. ch. 2. 7, 8. & 8. 12. & 12. 12. So 2 Sam 2. 5, 6.

s 1.18 2 Kin. 19. 35, 36. Isai. 37. 36, 37. Ecclus. 48. 18, 21. 1 Macc. 7. 41. 2 Macc. 8. 19. & 15. 22.

t 1.20 ver. 9. ch. 2. 1.

u 1.21 2 Kin. 19. 37. Isai. 37. 38. So 2 Chr. 32. 21.

u 1.21 2 Kin. 19. 37. Isai. 37. 38. So 2 Chr. 32. 21.

* 1.21 Or, Esarhaddon.

u 1.21 2 Kin. 19. 37. Isai. 37. 38. So 2 Chr. 32. 21.

w 1.22 See Neh 1. 11.

x 1.22 See Gen. 41. 42.

* 1.22 Or, Esarhaddon.

y 1.22 So Gen. 41. 40.

z 1.22 ch. 11. 18.

a 2.1 See Exod. 34. 22. & Acts 2. 1.

a 2.1 See Exod. 34. 22. & Acts 2. 1.

b 2.6 Cited from Amos 8. 10. So 1 Mac. 1. 39.

c 2.7 See ch. 1. 17.

d 2.8 ch. 1. 19.

e 2.9 See Wisd. 2. 1.

f 2.9 See Rev. 11. 2.

g 2.9 Numb. 19. 11.

* 2.10 Or, swallows.

* 2.10 Or, white films. ch. 3. 17. & 6. 8. & 11. 8, 13.

h 2.10 ch. 1. 22. & 11. 18. & 14. 10.

i 2.10 1 Macc. 6. 1. See Isai. 11. 11.

* 2.11 Or, was hired to spin in the women’s rooms.

* 2.12 Or, her work.

k 2.13 Deut. 22. 1.

l 2.14 Job 2. 9. Comp. ch. 5. 17, 18. Ecclus. 11. 23.

m 2.14 See Matt. 6. 1 [marg.]. So ch. 12. 8, 9. & 14. 11.

* 2.14 Or, lo, all things are known to thee. Comp. Acts 15. 18 (Gk.).

a 3.2 Ps. 119. 137. See Ezra 9. 13.

b 3.3 Ecclus. 23. 2. So 1 Esdr. 8. 75. Ecclus. 23. 3. See Lev. 4. 2.

c 3.4 See Judith 9. 4.

d 3.4 Deut. 28. 15, 37.

e 3.6 See 1 Sam. 3. 18.

f 3.6 Jonah 4. 3.

* 3.6 Or, dismissed, or, delivered. So ver. 13.

f 3.6 Jonah 4. 3.

g 3.6 Luke 17. 2 (Gk.).

h 3.6 ch. 2. 14.

i 3.6 2 Chr. 30. 9. So ch. 4. 7.

k 3.7 Ezra 6. 2? ch. 6. 5. & 7. 1. & 14. 12, 14. Judith 1. 1, 2. 2 Macc. 9. 3.

l 3.7 ch. 1. 14, 15.

m 3.8 ver. 17. So ch. 6. 14, 15, 17. & 8. 3. Comp. Wisd. 18. 25. Rev. 9. 11. See Job 26. 6.

n 3.10 So ch. 6. 14. See Gen. 42. 38.

o 3.11 Dan. 6. 10.

oo 3.11 See ch. 8. 5.

p 3.11 Ps. 145. 10.

q 3.12 So Ps. 123. 1.

r 3.13 So ver. 6.

* 3.15 Or, brother. Gk. as ch. 7. 4, 12.

s 3.17 ch. 5. 4. & 7. 8. & 8. 2. & 9. 1, 5. & 11. 2, 7. & 12. 15.

t 3.17 ch. 11. 13 (Gk.). So Acts 9. 18.

m 3.17 ver. 17. So ch. 6. 14, 15, 17. & 8. 3. Comp. Wisd. 18. 25. Rev. 9. 11. See Job 26. 6.

u 3.17 So ch. 6. 11 (Gk.), 12.

x 3.17 ver. 7.

a 4.1 See ch. 1. 14.

b 4.2 ch. 3. 6.

c 4.3 Prov. 23. 22.

d 4.3 See Exod. 20. 12. So Ecclus. 7. 27.

e 4.5 1 Tim. 5. 11 (Gk.).

f 4.7 See Prov. 3. 9. So Deut. 15. 7, 8. Ecclus. 3. 30. & 4. 1, 5. & 7. 10. & 12. 3. & 14. 13. & 17. 22. & 29. 12. ver. 16. Luke 11. 41.

g 4.7 ver. 16. So Ecclus. 14. 10. & 35. 10. See 2 Cor. 9. 7.

h 4.7 Ecclus. 4. 4.

i 4.7 So ch. 3. 6.

j 4.8 So ver. 16.

k 4.9 1 Tim. 6. 19.

l 4.10 ch. 12. 9. Comp. Ecclus. 29. 12, 13.

m 4.12 See 1 Thess. 4. 3.

n 4.12 See Gen. 20. 7. So Ps. 105. 15. Wisd. 7. 27.

o 4.13 So Prov. 11. 2. Comp. Gen. 3. 5.

p 4.13 So Matt. 25. 30 (Gk.).

p 4.13 So Matt. 25. 30 (Gk.).

q 4.13 So Prov. 6. 10, 11.

r 4.14 See Lev. 19. 13.

s 4.14 Exod. 23. 13. Wisd. 12. 21. Ephes. 5. 15 (English).

t 4.14 See 1 Pet. 1. 15.

u 4.15 Matt. 7. 12. Luke 6. 31.

x 4.15 See Eph. 5. 18.

y 4.16 ch. 1. 16, 17. Luke 14. 13. See ver. 7.

z 4.16 So ver. 8. Comp. Matt. 6. 1.

a 4.16 ver. 7.

b 4.17 Baruch 6. 32. Comp. Jer. 16. 7. Ezek. 24. 17. Ecclus. 7. 33. & 30. 18.

c 4.19 See Ps. 119. 5.

d 4.19 So Jam. 1. 17.

* 4.20 [ch. 1. 14, the brother].

e 4.21 ch. 1. 20.

f 4.21 1 Tim. 6. 6. Comp. Rom. 8. 17.

a 5.3 ch. 9. 4.

aa 5.4 See ch. 3. 17.

b 5.5 See ch. 1. 14.

bb 5.13 ch. 11. 17.

c 5.13 ch. 7. 7. Luke 8. 15.

d 5.13 ch. 1. 6, 7.

e 5.13 ch. 1. 4, 5.

f 5.14 So Matt. 20. 2.

g 5.16 ch. 11. 4.

h 5.17 Comp. ch. 2. 14.

i 5.17 See Num. 27. 17.

* 5.18 [Gk.]. Let not money be added, but be the koffscouring of our son.

* 5.19 Or, So long as God hath granted us to live, this is sufficient.

l 5.20 ch. 7. 16. & 8. 4, 7. See Cant. 4. 9.

m 5.21 ver. 16.

a 6.1 Gen. 2. 14. Dan. 10. 4. in the Gk. Judith 1. 6. Ecclus. 24. 25.

* 6.3 [Or,] cast it upon the land.

b 6.5 See ch. 3. 7.

c 6.7 Luke 7. 21. & 8. 2. & 11. 26 (Gk.). Acts 19. 12, 13, 15, 16.

cc 6.8 ch. 11. 4, 8, 11–13.

d 6.9 So ver. 12. See ch. 1. 14.

e 6.10 ch. 3. 7.

f 6.10 ch. 3. 10, 15.

* 6.11 Or, inheritance. So ch. 3. 17. ver. 12. ch. 7. 10.

g 6.11 Numb. 27. 8. & 36. 8. So ch. 7. 13.

d 6.12 So ver. 12. See ch. 1. 14.

g 6.12 Numb. 27. 8. & 36. 8. So ch. 7. 13.

h 6.12 See Numb. 35. 31 (Engl.).

i 6.13 ver. 16. Matt. 9. 15. Mark 2. 19. Luke 5. 34.

j 6.14 Gk. as ver. 17. ch. 8. 3. See ch. 3. 8.

k 6.14 ch. 3. 8.

l 6.14 See ch. 3. 10.

m 6.15 ch. 4. 12.

j 6.15 Gk. as ver. 17. ch. 8. 3. See ch. 3. 8.

i 6.16 ver. 16. Matt. 9. 15. Mark 2. 19. Luke 5. 34.

* 6.16 Or, imbers. ch. 8. 2.

j 6.17 Gk. as ver. 17. ch. 8. 3. See ch. 3. 8.

* 6.17 Or, vehemently. Ecclus. 17. 26.

a 7.1 See ch. 3. 7.

b 7.3 ch. 1. 3, 4.

c 7.4 So Gen. 43. 27, 28.

d 7.7 See ch. 5. 13.

e 7.8 See Luke 10. 38.

* 7.8 a sucking ram, or, lamb, Junius. Comp. Ex. 12. 3 marg, 5.

f 7.8 See ch. 3. 17.

g 7.12 So Neh. 8. 18 (Heb. & Gk.).

* 7.12 Or, law. Gk. not as ver. 13.

h 7.13 Numb. 36. 6. So ch. 6. 11.

i 7.14 So Gen. 24. 55.

k 7.14 Lat. as 2 Esdr. 15. 2.

l 7.14 Jer. 32. 10. So Dan. 6. 17. See Esther 3. 12.

m 7.16 See ch. 5. 20.

n 7.16 See Matt. 6. 6.

* 7.17 Or, licked.

o 7.18 Gk. as ch. 11. 11.

o 7.18 Gk. as ch. 11. 11.

a 8.2 See ch. 3. 17.

* 8.2 Or, imbers. ch. 6. 16.

b 8.3 ch. 6. 14, 15 in the Gk., 17. See ch. 3. 8.

c 8.3 Comp. Rev. 20. 2.

d 8.4 See ch. 5. 20.

e 8.5 ch. 3. 11. & 11. 14, 17. So ver. 15, 16, 17 in the Gk.

f 8.6 Gen. 2. 7, 22.

g 8.6 Gen. 2. 18.

d 8.7 See ch. 5. 20.

e 8.15 ch. 3. 11. & 11. 14, 17. So ver. 15, 16, 17 in the Gk.

h 8.15 Ps. 145. 10.

i 8.15 Ps. 103. 20. & 148. 2.

k 8.15 Ecclus. 17. 10.

e 8.16 ch. 3. 11. & 11. 14, 17. So ver. 15, 16, 17 in the Gk.

e 8.17 ch. 3. 11. & 11. 14, 17. So ver. 15, 16, 17 in the Gk.

l 8.19 2 Esdr. 9. 47. ch. 11. 19 (Gk.). See Matt. 22. 2.

m 8.19 Comp. ch. 11. 19.

n 8.20 ch. 9. 3. & 10. 7.

o 8.21 ch. 10. 10.

p 8.21 Comp. Ex. 18. 4.

a 9.1 See ch. 3. 17.

b 9.2 Gen. 24. 10. Ezra 2. 67. Job 1. 3, &c.

c 9.2 See ch. 1. 14.

c 9.2 See ch. 1. 14.

d 9.3 See ch. 8. 20.

e 9.4 So ch. 10. 1.

a 9.5 See ch. 3. 17.

f 9.5 ch. 5. 3.

* 9.6 Or, Gabael blessed Tobias and his wife. Junius.

a 10.1 So ch. 9. 4.

b 10.5 Comp. Prov. 15. 30. Baruch 3. 14.

c 10.7 See ch. 8. 20.

d 10.10 ch. 8. 21.

e 10.10 See Rev. 18. 13.

f 10.12 See 1 Pet. 4. 19.

* 10.12 Or, to be safely kept. 1 Tim. 6. 20. 2 Tim. 1. (12), 14.

a 11.2 See ch. 3. 17.

b 11.4 ch. 6. 8.

c 11.4 ch. 5. 16.

d 11.5 ch. 10. 7.

a 11.7 See ch. 3. 17.

b 11.8 ch. 6. 8.

e 11.9 Gen. 46. 29. Luke 15. 20.

b 11.11 ch. 6. 8.

f 11.11 ch. 7. 18 (Gk.).

g 11.13 See ch. 3. 17.

e 11.13 Gen. 46. 29. Luke 15. 20.

h 11.14 See ch. 8. 5.

i 11.14 ch. 12. 15. See Matt. 25. 31.

k 11.15 See ch. 13. 2.

l 11.17 ch. 5. 13.

h 11.17 See ch. 8. 5.

m 11.18 See ch. 2. 10.

* 11.18 Junius, who is also called Nasbas. Comp. ch. 14. 10 marg.

n 11.18 ch. 1. 22.

o 11.19 See ch. 8. 19.

p 11.19 Gen. 29. 27. Judg. 14. 12. Comp. ch. 8. 19.

a 12.1 ch. 5. 14, 15.

b 12.2 ch. 10. 10.

c 12.3 ch. 6. 2, 3.

d 12.3 ch. 8. 2. ver. 14.

e 12.3 ch. 9. 5.

f 12.3 ch. 11. 7, 8. ver. 14.

g 12.6 ver. 20 (Gk.).

g 12.6 ver. 20 (Gk.).

* 12.6 Or, with honour.

h 12.7 ver. 11.

i 12.7 1 Pet. 3. 13.

j 12.8 See Matt. 17. 21.

k 12.8 ver. 9. ch. 14. 11. So ch. 2. 14 See Matt. 6. 1 [marg.].

k 12.8 ver. 9. ch. 14. 11. So ch. 2. 14 See Matt. 6. 1 [marg.].

l 12.8 Ps. 37. 16. See Prov. 15. 16.

m 12.9 ch. 4. 10. So ch. 14. 11.

k 12.9 ver. 9. ch. 14. 11. So ch. 2. 14 See Matt. 6. 1 [marg.].

n 12.10 So Rom. 6. 23.

h 12.11 ver. 11.

o 12.12 ch. 3. 1–6.

p 12.12 ch. 3. 11–15.

q 12.12 See Acts 10. 4.

r 12.12 See ch. 1. 17.

s 12.13 ch. 2. 3, 4.

* 12.13 Gr. to go and bury.

f 12.14 ch. 11. 7, 8. ver. 14.

d 12.14 ch. 8. 2. ver. 14.

t 12.15 See ch. 3. 17.

u 12.15 Rev. 8. 2. See Rev. 1. 4.

v 12.15 ch. 11. 14.

w 12.15 Rev. 8. 3, 4.

x 12.15 Comp. Luke 1. 19.

y 12.16 ver. 6.

z 12.16 Josh. 5. 14. See Ezek. 1. 28.

a 12.19 Judg. 13. 16. Comp. Gen. 18. 8. & 19. 3.

b 12.20 Gk. as ver. 6, 22. See ch. 13. 3.

c 12.20 Comp. John 16. 5.

b 12.22 Gk. as ver. 6, 22. See ch. 13. 3.

a 13.2 ch. 11. 15. ver. 5. See Deut. 32. 39.

b 13.2 1 Sam. 2. 6. Wisd. 16. 13.

c 13.3 ch. 12. 6 (Gk.), 20 (Gk.), 22. ver. 6, 8 (Gk.), 10 (Gk.). ch. 14. 1, 2 (Gk.), 7.

d 13.3 ch. 1. 2. So ver. 6.

a 13.5 ch. 11. 15. ver. 5. See Deut. 32. 39.

e 13.5 See Deut. 30. 3.

f 13.6 See Deut. 6. 5.

c 13.6 ch. 12. 6 (Gk.), 20 (Gk.), 22. ver. 6, 8 (Gk.), 10 (Gk.). ch. 14. 1, 2 (Gk.), 7.

g 13.6 ver. 10. 1 Tim. 1. 17 (Gk.).

d 13.6 ch. 1. 2. So ver. 6.

c 13.6 ch. 12. 6 (Gk.), 20 (Gk.), 22. ver. 6, 8 (Gk.), 10 (Gk.). ch. 14. 1, 2 (Gk.), 7.

h 13.6 See Jonah 3. 9.

i 13.7 ver. 11. See 1 Esdr. 4. 46.

c 13.8 ch. 12. 6 (Gk.), 20 (Gk.), 22. ver. 6, 8 (Gk.), 10 (Gk.). ch. 14. 1, 2 (Gk.), 7.

j 13.9 Dan. 9. 24. Ecclus. 24. 11 marg. See Neh. 11. 1.

* 13.9 Or, He will lay a scourge upon the works of thy children.

k 13.9 ver. 13 (Gk.).

c 13.10 ch. 12. 6 (Gk.), 20 (Gk.), 22. ver. 6, 8 (Gk.), 10 (Gk.). ch. 14. 1, 2 (Gk.), 7.

g 13.10 ver. 10. 1 Tim. 1. 17 (Gk.).

* 13.10 Or, to make.

l 13.10 See ch. 1. 4.

m 13.11 So Isai. 60. 5. ch. 14. 6. Rev. 21. 24.

n 13.11 Comp. Ps. 72. 10, 11.

i 13.11 ver. 11. See 1 Esdr. 4. 46.

o 13.12 ver. 14. So Ps. 122. 6.

k 13.13 ver. 13 (Gk.).

o 13.14 ver. 14. So Ps. 122. 6.

p 13.14 So Isai. 66. 10. ch. 14. 7.

* 13.14 Or, prosperity.

p 13.14 So Isai. 66. 10. ch. 14. 7.

q 13.15 Ps. 48. 3. Matt. 5. 35.

r 13.16 Rev. 21. 18–20.

r 13.16 Rev. 21. 18–20.

r 13.16 Rev. 21. 18–20.

r 13.17 Rev. 21. 18–20.

s 13.17 See 1 Kin. 9. 28.

t 13.18 Rev. 19. 1, 3, 4, 6.

a 14.1 See ch. 13. 3.

* 14.2 Or, did more and more fear. See Luke 19. 11.

a 14.2 See ch. 13. 3.

b 14.4 See ch. 1. 14.

c 14.4 Jonah 3. 4. ver. 8.

d 14.4 2 Kin. 25. 9–11.

d 14.4 2 Kin. 25. 9–11.

d 14.4 2 Kin. 25. 9–11.

e 14.5 Ezra 3. 8. & 6. 14.

f 14.5 Ezra 3. 12. Hagg. 2. 3.

g 14.5 Comp. Jer. 31. 1–14. & 50. 4, 5. Baruch 4. 36, 37. & 5. 5–9.

* 14.5 for ever is not in the Roman copy.

h 14.6 See ch. 13. 11.

i 14.6 So Isai. 2. 18. Mic 5. 13. Zech. 13. 2.

a 14.7 See ch. 13. 3.

k 14.7 ch. 13. 14.

c 14.8 Jonah 3. 4. ver. 8.

l 14.9 See Deut. 4. 40.

m 14.10 See ch. 2. 10.

n 14.10 Comp. Job 18. 18. Ps. 112. 4.

* 14.10 Or, preserved. ch. 6. 17.

* 14.10 Junius readeth. Nitzba. ch. 11. 18.

* 14.10 Rom. Which he had set.

o 14.11 See ch. 12. 8, 9.

p 14.11 Comp. ver. 2.

* 14.11 Or, they.

q 14.12 See ch. 3. 7.

* 14.13 Or, possessed. 1 Macc. 2. 10 (Gk.).

q 14.14 See ch. 3. 7.

b 14.14 See ch. 1. 14.

r 14.15 Dan. 9. 1 ?

Wisdom

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19

The Book of Wisdom or The Wisdom of Solomon

1

1 [a]Love righteousness, ye that be judges of the earth: think of the Lord with a good (heart,) and in simplicity of heart seek him.

2 For he will be found of them that tempt him not; and [b]sheweth himself unto such as do not distrust him.

3 For froward thoughts separate from God: and his power, when it is tried, [*]reproveth the unwise.

4 For into a malicious soul wisdom shall not enter; nor dwell in the body that is subject unto sin.

5 For the holy spirit of discipline will flee deceit, and [c]remove from thoughts that are without understanding, and [*]will not abide when unrighteousness cometh in.

6 For wisdom is a [d]loving spirit; and will not acquit a blasphemer of his [*]words: for [e]God is witness of his reins, and a true [f]beholder of his heart, and a hearer of his tongue.

7 For [g]the Spirit of the Lord filleth [h]the world: and that which [*]containeth all things [i]hath knowledge of the voice.

8 Therefore he that speaketh unrighteous things cannot be hid: neither shall vengeance, when it [k]punisheth, pass by him.

9 For inquisition shall be made into the counsels of the ungodly: and the sound of his words shall come unto the Lord for the [*]manifestation of his wicked deeds.

10 For the ear of [l]jealousy heareth all things: and the noise of [m]murmurings is not hid.

11 Therefore beware of [m]murmuring, which is unprofitable; and refrain your tongue from [n]backbiting: for [o]there is no word so secret, that shall go for nought: and the mouth that [*]belieth [oo]slayeth the soul.

12 [p]Seek not death in the error of your life: and [p]pull not upon yourselves destruction with the works of your hands.

13 [q]For God made not death: [r]neither hath he pleasure in the destruction of the living.

14 For he created all things, that they might have their being: and [s]the generations of the world were healthful; and there is no poison of destruction in them, nor the kingdom of death upon the earth:

15 (For righteousness is immortal:)

16 But [t]ungodly men with their works and words called it to them: for when they thought to have it their friend, they consumed to nought, and [u]made a covenant with it, because they are worthy [x]to take part with it.

2

1 For [a]the ungodly said, reasoning with themselves, but not aright, [b]Our life is short and tedious, and [c]in the death of a man there is no remedy: neither was there any man known to have [d]returned from the grave.

2 For we are born at all adventure: and [e]we shall be hereafter as though we had never been: for the breath in our nostrils is as [f]smoke, and a little spark in the moving of our heart:

3 Which being extinguished, [g]our body shall be turned into ashes, and our spirit shall vanish as the [*]soft air,

4 And [h]our name shall be forgotten in time, and no man shall have our works in remembrance, and [i]our life shall pass away as the trace of a cloud, and shall be dispersed as a mist, that is driven away with the beams of the sun, and [*]overcome with the heat thereof.

5 For our time is [j]a very shadow that passeth away; and after our end there is no returning: for [*]it is [k]fast sealed, so that no man cometh again.

6 Come on therefore, [l]let us enjoy the good things that are present: and let us [*]speedily use the creatures like as in youth.

7 Let us fill ourselves with costly wine and ointments: and let no flower of the spring pass by us:

8 Let us [ll]crown ourselves with rosebuds, before they be withered:

9 Let none of us go without his part of our [*]voluptuousness: let us leave tokens of our joyfulness in every place: [m]for this is our portion, and our lot is this.

10 Let us oppress the poor righteous man, let us not spare the widow, nor reverence the ancient gray hairs of the aged.

11 Let our strength be the law of justice: for that which is feeble [n]is found to be nothing worth.

12 Therefore [o]let us lie in wait for the righteous; because he is not for our turn, and he is clean contrary to our doings: he upbraideth us with our offending the law, and objecteth to our infamy the transgressings of our education.

13 He professeth to have the knowledge of God: and he calleth himself the child of the Lord.

14 [p]He was made [q]to reprove our thoughts.

15 [r]He is grievous unto us even to behold: for his life is not like other men’s, his ways are of another fashion.

16 We are esteemed of him as [*][s]counterfeits: he abstaineth from our ways as from filthiness: [t]he pronounceth the end of the just to be blessed, and [u]maketh his boast that God is his father.

17 Let us see if his words be true: and let us prove what shall happen in [w]the end of him.

18 For [x]if the just man be [u]the son of God, he will help him, and deliver him from the hand of his enemies.

19 [y]Let us examine him with despitefulness and torture, that we may know his [z]meekness, and prove his [a]patience.

20 Let us condemn him with a shameful death: for [b]by his own saying he shall be [c]respected.

21 Such things they did imagine, and were deceived: for [d]their own wickedness hath blinded them.

22 As for the [e]mysteries of God, they knew them not: neither hoped they for the wages of righteousness, nor [*]discerned a reward for blameless souls.

23 [f]For God created man to be immortal, and made him to be [g]an image of his own eternity.

24 Nevertheless [h]through envy of the devil came death into the world: and [i]they that do hold of his side do find it.

3

1 But the souls of the righteous are [a]in the hand of God, and there shall no torment touch them.

2 In the sight of [b]the unwise they seemed to die: and their [c]departure is taken for misery,

3 And their going from us to be [d]utter destruction: but they are in peace.

4 For though they be punished in the sight of men, yet is their [e]hope full of immortality.

5 And [f]having been a little chastised, they shall be greatly [*]rewarded: for [g]God proved them, and found them [*]worthy for himself.

6 [h]As gold in the furnace hath he tried them, and received them as a burnt offering.

7 And in the time of their [i]visitation [k]they shall shine, and run to and fro like sparks among the stubble.

8 [l]They shall judge the nations, and have dominion over the people, and [m]their Lord shall reign for ever.

9 They that put their trust in him [n]shall understand the truth: [*]and such as be faithful in love shall [o]abide with him: for [p]grace and mercy is to his saints, [p]and he hath [i]care for his [q]elect.

10 But [r]the ungodly shall be punished according to their own imaginations, which have neglected the righteous, and forsaken the Lord.

11 For whoso [s]despiseth wisdom and nurture, he is miserable, and their hope is vain, their labours unfruitful, and their works unprofitable:

12 Their wives are [*]foolish, and their children wicked:

13 Their offspring is cursed. Wherefore blessed is the barren that is [t]undefiled, which hath not known the sinful [t]bed: [u]she shall have fruit in the [i]visitation of souls.

14 And blessed is [u]the eunuch, which with his hands hath wrought no iniquity, nor imagined wicked things against God: for unto him shall be given [*]the special gift of faith, and an inheritance [*]in [u]the temple of the Lord more acceptable to his mind.

15 For glorious is the fruit of good labours: and [v]the root of wisdom shall never fall away.

16 As for [w]the children of adulterers, [x]they shall not [*]come to their perfection, and the seed of an unrighteous bed shall be rooted out.

17 For though they live long, yet shall they be nothing regarded: and their last age shall be without honour.

18 Or, if they die quickly, [y]they have no hope, neither [z]comfort in the day of [*]trial.

19 For horrible is the end of the unrighteous generation.

4

1 Better it is to have no children, and to have virtue: for the memorial thereof is immortal: because it is [*]known [a]with God, and with men.

2 When it is present, men take example at it; and when it is gone, they desire it: [b]it weareth a crown, and triumpheth for ever, having gotten the victory, [c]striving for undefiled rewards.

3 But the multiplying brood of the ungodly shall not thrive, [d]nor take deep rooting from bastard slips, nor lay any fast foundation.

4 For [e]though they flourish in branches for a time; yet standing not fast, [e]they shall be shaken with the wind, and through the force of winds they shall be rooted out.

5 The [f]imperfect branches [g]shall be broken off, their fruit unprofitable, not ripe to eat, yea, meet for nothing.

6 [h]For children begotten of unlawful [*]beds are witnesses of wickedness against their parents in their trial.

7 But though the righteous be [i]prevented with death, yet shall he be in rest.

8 For honourable age is not that which standeth in length of time, nor that is measured by number of years.

9 But wisdom is the gray hair unto men, and an unspotted life is old age.

10 [j]He pleased God, and was beloved of him: so that living among sinners he was translated.

11 Yea [k]speedily was he taken away, lest that wickedness should alter his understanding, or deceit beguile his soul.

12 For the bewitching of naughtiness [l]doth obscure things that are honest; and the wandering of concupiscence doth [*]undermine the simple mind.

13 He, [m]being made [*]perfect in a short time, fulfilled a long time:

14 For [j]his soul pleased the Lord: therefore hasted he to take him away from among the wicked.

15 This the people saw, and understood it not, neither laid they up this in their minds, That his [n]grace and mercy is with his saints, and that he hath [nn]respect unto his chosen.

16 Thus the righteous that is [o]dead shall [oo]condemn the ungodly which are living; and [p]youth that is soon perfected the many years and old age of the unrighteous.

17 For [q]they shall see the end of the wise, and shall not understand what God in his counsel hath decreed of him, and to what end the Lord hath set him in safety.

18 They shall see him, and despise him; but God shall laugh them to scorn: and they shall hereafter be a vile carcase, and a reproach among the dead for evermore.

19 For he shall rend them, and cast them down headlong, that they shall be speechless; and he shall shake them from the foundation; and they shall be utterly laid waste, and be in sorrow; and [r]their memorial shall perish.

20 And [*]when they cast up the accounts of their sins, they shall come with fear: and their own iniquities shall convince them to their face.

5

1 Then shall the righteous man [a]stand in great boldness before the face of such as have afflicted him, and made no account of his labours.

2 When they see it, they shall be troubled with terrible fear, and shall be amazed at the strangeness of his salvation, so far beyond all that they looked for.

3 And they repenting and groaning for [b]anguish of spirit shall say within themselves, This was he, whom we had sometimes in derision, and a [*]proverb of reproach:

4 We [c]fools accounted his life madness, and his end to be without honour:

5 How is he numbered among the children of God, and his lot is among the saints!

6 Therefore have we erred from the way of truth, and the light of righteousness hath not shined unto us, and the sun of righteousness rose not upon us.

7 We [*]wearied ourselves in the way of wickedness and destruction: yea, we have gone through deserts, where [d]there lay no way: but as for the way of the Lord, we have not known it.

8 What hath pride profited us? or what good hath riches with our vaunting brought us?

9 All those things are passed away [e]like a shadow, and [f]as a post that hasted by;

10 And [g]as a ship that passeth over the waves of the water, which when it is gone by, the trace thereof cannot be found, neither the pathway of the keel in the waves;

11 Or [g]as when a bird [*]hath flown through the air, there is no [h]token of her way to be found, but the light air being beaten with the stroke of her wings and parted with the violent noise and motion of them, is passed through, and therein afterwards no sign where she went is to be found;

12 Or like as when an arrow is shot [i]at a mark, it parteth the air, which immediately cometh together again, so that a man cannot know where it went through:

13 Even so we in like manner, as soon as we were born, began to draw to our end, and had no sign of virtue to shew; but were consumed in our own wickedness.

14 For [k]the hope of the ungodly is like [*]dust [l]that is blown away with the wind; like a [*]thin froth that is driven away with the storm; [m]like as the smoke which is dispersed here and there with a tempest, and passeth away as the remembrance of a guest that tarrieth but a day.

15 But the righteous live for evermore; [n]their reward also is with the Lord, and the care of them is with the most High.

16 Therefore shall they receive a glorious [*]kingdom, and a beautiful [o]crown from the Lord’s hand: for [p]with his right hand shall he cover them, and with his arm shall he protect them.

17 He shall take to him [q]his jealousy for [r]complete armour, and [t]make the creature his weapon for the revenge of his enemies.

18 [s]He shall put on righteousness as a breastplate, and [ss]true judgment instead of an helmet.

19 He shall take [*]holiness for an invincible shield.

20 His severe wrath shall he sharpen for a sword, and [t]the world shall fight with him against the unwise.

21 Then shall the right aiming thunderbolts go abroad; and from the clouds, [u]as from a well drawn bow, shall they fly [i]to the mark.

22 And [v]hailstones full of wrath shall be cast as out of a stone bow, and the water of the sea shall rage against them, and [w]the floods shall cruelly drown them.

23 Yea, [x][y]a mighty wind shall stand up against them, and [y]like a storm shall blow them away: thus iniquity shall lay waste the whole earth, and ill dealing shall overthrow [z]the thrones of the mighty.

6

1 [a]Hear therefore, O ye kings, and understand; learn, ye that be judges of the ends of the earth.

2 Give ear, ye that rule the people, and glory in the multitude of nations.

3 For [b]power is given you of the Lord, and sovereignty from the Highest, who shall try your works, and search out your counsels.

4 Because, being [c]ministers of his kingdom, ye have not judged aright, nor kept the law, nor walked after the counsel of God;

5 Horribly and speedily shall he come upon you: for a sharp judgment shall be to them that be in high places.

6 For [d]mercy will soon pardon the meanest: but [e]mighty men shall be mightily tormented.

7 For he which is Lord over all [f]shall fear no man’s person, neither shall he stand in awe of any man’s greatness: for he hath made the small and great, and [g]careth for all alike.

8 But a sore trial shall come upon the mighty.

9 Unto you therefore, O kings, do I speak, that ye may learn wisdom, and not [h]fall away.

10 For they that keep holiness holily shall be [*]judged holy: and they that have learned such things shall find [*]what to answer.

11 Wherefore set your affection upon my words; desire them, and ye shall be instructed.

12 Wisdom is glorious, and never fadeth away: yea, [i]she is easily seen of them that love her, and found of such as seek her.

13 She [j]preventeth them that desire her, in making herself first known unto them.

14 Whoso [k]seeketh her early shall have no great travail: for he shall find her sitting at his doors.

15 To think therefore upon her is perfection of wisdom: and whoso watcheth for her shall quickly be [l]without care.

16 For she goeth about seeking such as are worthy of her, sheweth herself favourably unto them in the ways, and meeteth them in every thought.

17 For the very true beginning of her is the desire of [*]discipline; and the care of [*]discipline is love;

18 And [m]love is the keeping of her laws; and the giving heed unto her laws is the assurance of incorruption;

19 And incorruption maketh us near unto God:

20 Therefore the desire of wisdom bringeth to [n]a kingdom.

21 If your delight be then in [o]thrones and sceptres, O ye kings of the people, honour wisdom, [n]that ye may reign for evermore.

22 As for wisdom, what she is, and how she came up, I will tell you, and will not hide mysteries from you: but will seek her out from the beginning of her nativity, and bring the knowledge of her into light, and will not pass over the truth.

23 Neither [p]will I go with consuming envy; for such a man shall have no fellowship with wisdom.

24 But [q]the multitude of the wise is the welfare of the world: and a wise king is the upholding of the people.

25 Receive therefore instruction through my words, and it shall do you good.

7

1 I myself also am a mortal man, like to all, and the offspring [a]of him that was first made of the earth,

2 And in my mother’s womb was fashioned to be flesh in the time of ten months, [b]being compacted in blood, of the seed of man, and the pleasure that came with [c]sleep.

3 And when I was born, I drew in the common air, and fell upon the earth, which is [d]of like nature, and the first voice which I uttered was crying, as all others do.

4 I was nursed in [e]swaddling clothes, and that with cares.

5 For there is no king that had any other beginning of birth.

6 For [f]all men have one entrance into life, and the like [g]going out.

7 Wherefore [h]I prayed, and understanding was given me: I [i]called upon God, and the spirit of wisdom came to me.

8 I preferred her before [k]sceptres and thrones, and [l]esteemed riches nothing in comparison of her.

9 Neither compared I unto her any [*][m]precious stone, because all gold in respect of her is as a little sand, and silver shall be counted as clay before her.

10 I loved her above [n]health and beauty, and chose to have her [o]instead of light: for the light that cometh from her never goeth out.

11 [p]All good things together came to me with her, and [p]innumerable riches in her hands.

12 And I rejoiced in them all, because wisdom goeth before them: and I knew not that she was the mother of them.

13 I learned [*]diligently, and do communicate her [*]liberally: [pp]I do not hide her riches.

14 For she is [q]a treasure unto men that never faileth: which they that use [*][qq]become the friends of God, being [r]commended for the gifts that come from [rr]learning.

15 [*]God hath granted me to speak as I would, and to conceive as is meet for the things that [*]are given me: because it is he that leadeth unto wisdom, and directeth the wise.

16 For in his hand are both we and our words; all wisdom also, and knowledge of workmanship.

17 For he hath given me certain knowledge of the things that are, namely, to know how the world was made, and the operation of the elements:

18 The beginning, ending, and midst of the times: the alterations of [s]the turning of the sun, and the change of seasons:

19 The circuits of years, and the [t]positions of stars:

20 The natures of living creatures, and the furies of wild beasts: the violence of winds, and the [u]reasonings of men: the diversities of plants and the virtues of roots:

21 And all such things as are either secret or manifest, them I know.

22 For wisdom, which is [v]the worker of all things, taught me: for in her is an understanding spirit holy, [*]one only, manifold, subtil, lively, [w]clear, undefiled, plain, not subject to hurt, [x]loving the thing that is good quick, which cannot be letted, ready to do good,

23 Kind to man, steadfast, sure, [y]free from care, having all power, overseeing all things, and going through all understanding, pure, and most subtil, spirits.

24 For wisdom is more moving than any motion: she passeth and goeth through all things by reason of her pureness.

25 For she is the [*]breath of the power of God, and a pure [*]influence flowing from the glory of the [z]Almighty: therefore can no defiled thing fall into her.

26 For she is [a]the brightness of the everlasting light, the unspotted [aa]mirror of the power of God, and [b]the image of his goodness.

27 And being but one, she can do all things: and remaining in herself, she [*]maketh all things new: and in all ages entering into holy souls, she maketh them [c]friends of God, and [d]prophets.

28 For God loveth none but him that dwelleth with wisdom.

29 For she is more beautiful than the sun, and above all the [t]order of stars: being compared with the light, she is found before it.

30 For after this cometh night: but vice shall not prevail against wisdom.

8

1 Wisdom reacheth from one end to another mightily: and [*]sweetly doth she order all things.

2 I loved her, and sought her out from my youth, I desired [*][a]to make her my spouse, and I was a lover of her beauty.

3 In that she is [b]conversant with God, she magnifieth her nobility: yea, the Lord of all things himself loved her.

4 For she is [*]privy to the mysteries of the knowledge of God, and a [*]lover of his works.

5 If riches be a possession to be desired in this life; [c]what is richer than wisdom, [d]that worketh all things?

6 And if [e]prudence work; who of all that are is a more cunning workman than she?

7 And if a man love righteousness her labours are virtues: for she teacheth temperance and prudence, justice and [q]fortitude: which are such things, as men can have nothing more profitable in their life.

8 If a man desire much experience, she knoweth things of old, and conjectureth aright what is to come: she knoweth the subtilties of speeches, and can expound [f]dark sentences: she foreseeth signs and wonders, and the [g]events of seasons and times.

9 Therefore I purposed [h]to take her to me [b]to live with me, knowing that she [*]would be a counsellor of good things, and a comfort in cares and grief.

10 For her sake I shall have estimation among the multitude, and honour with the elders, [i]though I be young.

11 I shall be found of a quick conceit [k]in judgment, and shall be admired in the sight of [l]great men.

12 [m]When I hold my tongue, they shall bide my leisure, and when I speak, they shall give good ear unto me: if I talk much, they shall [n]lay their hands upon their mouth.

13 Moreover [o]by the means of her I shall obtain immortality, and leave behind me an everlasting memorial to them that come after me.

14 I shall [*]set the people in order, and [p]the nations shall be subject unto me.

15 Horrible tyrants shall be afraid, when they do but hear of me; I shall [*]be found good among the multitude, and [q]valiant in war.

16 [*]After I am come into mine house, I will repose myself with her: for her conversation hath no bitterness; and [b]to live with her hath no sorrow, but mirth and joy.

17 Now when I considered these things in myself, and [r]pondered them in my heart, how that to be allied unto wisdom [o]is immortality;

18 And great pleasure it is to have her friendship; and in the works of her hands are infinite riches; and in the exercise of conference with her, prudence; and in talking with her, a [*]good report; I went about seeking how to [*]take her to me.

19 For I was a witty child, and had a good spirit.

20 Yea rather, being good, [s]I came into a body undefiled.

21 Nevertheless, when I perceived that I could not otherwise [t]obtain her, except God gave her me; and that was a point of wisdom also to know whose gift she was; I [*][u]prayed unto the Lord, and besought him, and with my whole heart I said,

9

1 O God of my fathers, and Lord of mercy, [a]who hast made all things with thy word,

2 And ordained man through thy wisdom, that he should [b]have dominion over the creatures which thou hast made,

3 And order the world according to [c]equity and righteousness, and execute judgment with an upright heart:

4 [d]Give me wisdom, [e]that sitteth by thy throne; and reject me not from among thy children:

5 For [f]I thy servant and son of thine handmaid am a feeble person, and of a short time, and [g]too young for the understanding of judgment and laws.

6 For though a man be never so perfect among the children of men, yet if thy wisdom be not with him, [h]he shall be nothing regarded.

7 [i]Thou hast chosen me to be a king of thy people, and a judge of thy sons and daughters:

8 [k]Thou hast commanded me to build a temple upon [l]thy holy mount, and an altar in the city wherein thou dwellest, [m]a resemblance of the holy tabernacle, [n]which thou hast prepared from the beginning.

9 And [e][o]wisdom was with thee: which knoweth thy works, and was present when thou madest the world, and knew what was acceptable in thy sight, and right in thy commandments.

10 O send her out of thy [p]holy heavens, and from the throne of thy glory, that being present she may labour with me, that I may know what is pleasing unto thee.

11 For she knoweth and understandeth all things, and she shall lead me soberly in my doings, and preserve me [*]in her power.

12 So shall my works be acceptable, and then shall I judge thy people righteously, and be worthy to sit in my father’s seat.

13 [q]For what man is he that can know the counsel of God? or who can think what the will of the Lord is?

14 For the thoughts of mortal men are [*]miserable, and our devices are but uncertain.

15 For the corruptible body presseth down the soul, and [r]the [s]earthy tabernacle weigheth down the mind that museth upon many things.

16 And [t]hardly do we guess aright at things that are upon earth, and with labour do we find the things that are [*]before us: but the things that are in heaven who hath searched out?

17 And [q]thy counsel who hath known, [u]except thou give wisdom, and [u]send thy Holy Spirit from above?

18 For so the ways of them which lived on the earth were reformed, and men were taught the things that are pleasing unto thee, and [x]were saved through wisdom.

10

1 She preserved the [a]first formed father of the world, that was created alone, and brought him out of his fall,

2 And [b]gave him power to rule all things.

3 But [c]when the unrighteous went away from her in his anger, [c]he perished also in the fury wherewith he murdered his brother.

4 For whose cause [d]the earth being drowned with the flood, [e]wisdom again preserved it, and directed the course of [f]the righteous [g]in a piece of wood of small value.

5 Moreover, [h]the nations in their wicked conspiracy being confounded, [i]she found out the righteous, and preserved him [k]blameless unto God, and [l]kept him strong [*]against his tender compassion toward his son.

6 [m]When the ungodly perished, she delivered [n]the righteous man, who fled from the fire which fell down upon [*]the [o]five cities.

7 Of whose wickedness even to this day the waste land that smoketh is a testimony, and plants bearing fruit that never come to ripeness: and [p]a standing pillar of salt is a monument of an unbelieving soul.

8 For regarding not wisdom, they gat not only this hurt, that they knew not the things which were good; but also left behind them to the world a memorial of their foolishness: so that in the things wherein they offended they could not so much as be hid.

9 But wisdom delivered from pain those that attended upon her.

10 When [q]the righteous fled from his brother’s wrath she guided him in right paths, [r]shewed him the kingdom of God, and gave him knowledge of holy things, [s]made him rich in his travels, and multiplied the fruit of his labours.

11 [t]In the covetousness of such as oppressed him she stood by him, and made him rich.

12 [u]She defended him from his enemies, and kept him safe from those that lay in wait, and [x]in a sore conflict she gave him the victory; that he might know that goodness is stronger than all.

13 [y]When the righteous was sold, she forsook him not, but [z]delivered him from sin: [a]she went down with him into the pit,

14 And [b]left him not in bonds, till she brought him the sceptre of the kingdom, and [*][c]power against those that oppressed him: as for [d]them that had accused him, she shewed them to be liars, and gave him perpetual glory.

15 [e]She delivered the [*]righteous people and [f]blameless seed from the nation that oppressed them.

16 [g]She entered into the soul of [h]the servant of the Lord, and [i]withstood dreadful kings [i]in wonders and signs;

17 [j]Rendered to the [*]righteous a reward of their labours, guided them in a marvellous way, and was unto them for [k]a cover by day, and [l]a [*]light of stars in the night season;

18 [m]Brought them through the Red sea, and led them through much water:

19 [n]But she drowned their enemies, and [o]cast them up out of the bottom of the deep.

20 Therefore [p]the righteous spoiled the ungodly, and [q]praised thy holy name, O Lord, and magnified with one accord thine hand, that fought for them.

21 For wisdom opened the mouth of the dumb, and made the tongues of them that cannot speak [r]eloquent.

11

1 She prospered their works in the hand of the holy [a]prophet.

2 [b]They went through the wilderness that was not inhabited, and pitched tents in places where there lay no way.

3 [c]They stood against their enemies, and were avenged of their adversaries.

4 When they were thirsty, they called upon thee, and [d]water was given them out of the flinty rock, and their thirst was quenched out of the hard stone.

5 For by what things their enemies were punished, by the same they in their need were benefited.

6 For instead of a perpetual running river [e]troubled with foul blood,

7 For a manifest reproof of [f]that commandment, whereby the infants were slain, thou gavest unto them abundance of water [g]by a means which they hoped not for:

8 Declaring by that thirst then [h]how thou hadst punished their adversaries.

9 For when they were tried albeit but in mercy chastised, they knew how the ungodly were judged in wrath and tormented, [i]thirsting in another manner than the just.

10 For these thou didst admonish and try, [j]as a father: but the other, as a severe king, thou didst condemn and punish.

11 Whether they were absent or present, they were vexed alike.

12 For a double grief came upon them, and a groaning for the remembrance of things past.

13 For when they heard by their own punishments the other to be benefited, [k]they [*]had some feeling of the Lord.

14 For whom they respected with scorn, [l]when he was long before thrown out at the casting forth of the infants, him in the end, [m]when they saw what came to pass, they admired.

15 But for the foolish devices of their wickedness, wherewith being deceived they worshipped [n]serpents void of reason, and [o]vile beasts, [p]thou didst send a multitude of unreasonable beasts upon them for vengeance;

16 That they might know, that [q]wherewithal a man sinneth, by the same also shall he be punished.

17 For thy Almighty hand, that made the world [r]of matter without form, wanted not means [s]to send among them a multitude of bears or fierce lions,

18 Or unknown wild beasts, [t]full of rage, newly created, breathing out either a fiery vapour, or filthy scents of scattered smoke, or shooting horrible sparkles out of their eyes:

19 Whereof not only the harm might dispatch them at once, but also the terrible sight utterly destroy them.

20 Yea, and without these might they have fallen down with one blast, being persecuted of [u]vengeance, and scattered abroad through [v]the breath of thy power: but thou hast ordered all things in [w]measure and [ww]number and weight.

21 For thou canst shew thy great strength at all times when thou wilt; and [x]who may withstand the power of thine arm?

22 For the whole world before thee is as a [*]little grain of the balance, yea, [y]as a drop of the morning dew that falleth down upon the earth.

23 But thou hast mercy upon all; for thou canst do all things, and [z]winkest at the sins of men, because they should amend.

24 For thou lovest all the things that are, and abhorrest nothing which thou hast made: for never wouldest thou have made any thing, if thou hadst hated it.

25 And how could any thing have endured, if it had not been thy will? or been preserved, if not [a]called by thee?

26 But [b]thou sparest all: for they are thine, O Lord, thou lover of souls.

12

1 For thine incorruptible Spirit is in all things.

2 Therefore chastenest thou them by little and little that [a]offend, and warnest them by putting them in remembrance wherein they have offended, that leaving their wickedness they may believe on thee, O Lord.

3 For it was thy will to destroy by the hands of our fathers both those [*]old inhabitants of thy holy land,

4 Whom [b]thou hatedst for doing most odious works of [*][c]witchcrafts, and wicked sacrifices;

5 And also those [d]merciless murderers of children, and devourers of man’s flesh, and the feasts of blood,

6 With their priests out of the midst of their idolatrous crew, and [d]the parents, that killed with their own hands souls destitute of help:

7 That the land, which thou esteemedst above all other, might receive a worthy [*]colony of God’s children.

8 Nevertheless even those [e]thou sparedst as men, and didst send [f]wasps, forerunners of thine host, to destroy them by little and little.

9 Not that thou wast unable to bring the ungodly under the hand of the righteous in battle, or to destroy them at once with cruel beasts, or with one rough word:

10 But executing thy judgments upon them [g]by little and little, thou gavest them place of repentance, not being ignorant that they were a naughty generation, and that their malice was bred in them, and that their cogitation would never be changed.

11 For it was [h]a cursed seed from the beginning; neither didst thou for fear of any man give them pardon for those things wherein they sinned.

12 [i]For who shall say, [j]What hast thou done? or who shall withstand thy judgment? or who shall [k]accuse thee for the nations that perish, whom thou made? or who shall come [*]to stand against thee, [*]to be revenged for the unrighteous men?

13 For neither is there any God but thou that [l]careth for all, to whom thou mightest shew that thy judgment is not unright.

14 Neither shall king or tyrant be able [m]to set his face against thee for any whom thou hast punished.

15 Forsomuch then as thou art righteous thyself, thou orderest all things righteously: [n]thinking it not agreeable with thy power to condemn him that hath not deserved to be punished.

16 For thy power is the beginning of righteousness, and because thou art the Lord of all, [e]it maketh thee to be gracious unto all.

17 For when men will not believe that thou art of a [*]full power, thou shewest thy strength, and among them that know it thou makest their boldness manifest.

18 But thou, mastering thy power, judgest with [o]equity, and orderest us [e]with great favour: for [p]thou mayest use power when thou wilt.

19 But by such works hast thou taught thy people that the just man should be merciful, and hast made thy children to be of a good hope that thou givest repentance for sins.

20 [q]For if thou didst punish the enemies of thy children, and the condemned to death, with such deliberation, giving them [r]time and place, whereby they might be delivered from their malice:

21 With how great [s]circumspection didst thou judge thine own sons, [t]unto whose fathers thou hast sworn, and made covenants of good promises?

22 Therefore, whereas thou dost chasten us, thou scourgest our enemies a thousand times more, to the intent that, [u]when we judge, we should carefully think of thy goodness, and when we ourselves are judged, we should look for mercy.

23 Wherefore, whereas men have lived dissolutely and unrighteously, [v]thou hast tormented them with their own [*][w]abominations.

24 For [v]they went astray very far in the ways of error, and [x]held them for gods, which even among the beasts of their enemies were despised, being deceived, as children of no understanding.

25 Therefore unto them, as to children without the use of reason, thou didst send a judgment to mock them.

26 But they that would not be reformed by that correction, [y]wherein he dallied with them, shall feel a judgment worthy of God.

27 For, look, for what things they grudged, when they were punished, that is, for them whom they thought to be gods; now [z]being punished in them, when they saw it, they acknowledged him to be the true God, whom before they denied to know: and [a]therefore came extreme damnation upon them.

13

1 [a]Surely vain are all men by nature, who are ignorant of God, and could not out of the good things that are seen know him that is: neither by considering the works did they acknowledge the [b]workmaster;

2 But deemed either fire, or wind, or the swift air, or [c]the circle of the stars, or the violent water, or [c]the lights of heaven, to be the gods which govern the world.

3 With whose beauty if they being delighted [d]took them to be gods; let them know how much better the Lord of them is: for the first author of beauty hath created them.

4 But if they were astonished at their power and virtue, let them understand by them, how much mightier he is that made them.

5 [e]For by the greatness and beauty of the creatures proportionably the maker of them is seen.

6 But yet for this they are the less to be blamed: for they peradventure err, seeking God, and desirous to find him.

7 [f]For being conversant in his works they [*]search him diligently, and believe their sight: because the things are beautiful that are seen.

8 Howbeit neither are they to be pardoned.

9 For if they were able to know so much, that they could aim at the world; how did they not sooner find out the Lord thereof?

10 But miserable are they, and in [g]dead things is their hope, who call them gods, which are [h]the works of men’s hands, gold and silver, [i]to shew art in, and resemblances of beasts, or a stone good for nothing, the work of an ancient hand.

11 [j]Now a [*]carpenter that felleth timber, after he hath sawn down a tree meet for the purpose, and taken off all the bark skilfully round about, and hath wrought it handsomely, and made [k]a vessel thereof fit for the service of man’s life;

12 And [l]after spending the [*][m]refuse of his work to dress his meat, hath filled himself;

13 And taking the very [m]refuse among those which served to no use, being a crooked piece of wood, and full of knots, hath carved it diligently, when he had nothing else to do, and formed it by the skill of his understanding, and fashioned it to the image of a man;

14 Or made it like some [n]vile beast, laying it over with vermilion, and with paint colouring it red, and covering every spot therein;

15 And [o]when he had made a convenient room for it, set it in a wall, and made it fast with iron:

16 For he provided for it that it might not fall, knowing that it was unable to help itself; for it is an image, and hath need of help:

17 [p]Then maketh he prayer for his goods, for his wife and children, and is not ashamed to speak to that which hath no life.

18 For health he calleth upon that which is weak: for life prayeth to that which is [g]dead; for [q]aid humbly beseecheth [*]that which hath least means to help: and for a good journey he asketh of [r]that which cannot set a foot forward:

19 And for gaining and getting, and for good success of his hands, asketh ability to do of him, that is most unable to do any thing.

14

1 Again, one preparing himself to sail, and about to pass through the raging waves, calleth upon a piece of wood more rotten than the [*]vessel that carrieth him.

2 For verily desire of gain devised [*]that, and the workman built it by his skill.

3 But thy providence, O Father, governeth it: for thou [a]hast made a way in the sea, and a safe path in the waves;

4 Shewing that thou canst save from all danger: yea, though a man went to sea without art.

5 Nevertheless thou wouldest not that the works of thy wisdom should be idle, and therefore do men commit their lives to a small piece of wood, and passing the rough sea [b]in a weak vessel are saved.

6 For in the old time also, [c]when the proud giants perished, the hope of the world governed by thy hand escaped in a weak vessel, and left to all ages a seed of generation.

7 For blessed is [d]the wood whereby righteousness cometh.

8 But that which is made with hands is cursed, [e]as well it, as he that made it: he, because he made it; and it, because, being corruptible, it was called god.

9 For [f]the ungodly and his ungodliness are both alike hateful unto God.

10 For that which is made shall be punished together with him that made it.

11 Therefore [g]even [*]upon the idols of the Gentiles shall there be a [h]visitation: because in the creature of God they are become an abomination, and [*][i]stumblingblocks to the souls of men, and a [*][i]snare to the feet of the unwise.

12 [j]For the [k]devising of idols was the beginning of spiritual fornication, and the invention of them the corruption of life.

13 For neither were they from the beginning, neither shall they be for ever.

14 For by the vain glory of men they entered into the world, and therefore shall they come shortly to an end.

15 For a father afflicted with untimely mourning, when he hath made an image of his child soon taken away, now honoured him as a god, which was then a dead man, and delivered to those that were under him [l]ceremonies and [l]sacrifices.

16 Thus [*]in process of time an ungodly custom grown strong was kept as a law, and graven images were worshipped by the commandments of [*]kings.

17 Whom men could not honour [*]in presence, because they dwelt far off, they took the counterfeit of his visage from far, and made an express image of a king whom they honoured, to the end that by this their [m]forwardness they might flatter him that was absent, as if he were present.

18 Also the singular diligence of the artificer did help to set forward the ignorant to more [n]superstition.

19 For he, peradventure willing to please one in authority, forced all his skill to make the resemblance [*]of the best fashion.

20 And so the multitude, allured by the grace of the work, took him now for a [o]god, which a little before was but honoured.

21 And this was [p]an occasion to deceive the world: for men, serving either calamity or tyranny, did ascribe unto stones and stocks [q]the incommunicable [*]name.

22 Moreover this was not enough for them, that they erred in the knowledge of God; but whereas they lived in the great war of ignorance, those so great plagues called they peace.

23 For whilst [r]they slew their children in [l]sacrifices, or used secret [l]ceremonies, or made [s]revellings of strange rites;

24 They kept neither lives nor marriages any longer undefiled: but either one slew another traiterously, or grieved him by adultery.

25 [t]So that there reigned in all men [*]without exception blood, manslaughter, theft, and dissimulation, corruption, unfaithfulness, tumults, perjury,

26 Disquieting of good men, [u]forgetfulness of good turns, defiling of souls, changing of [*]kind, disorder in marriages, [v]adultery, and [w]shameless uncleanness.

27 [x]For the [n]worshipping of idols [*]not to be named is the beginning, the cause, and the end, of all evil.

28 For either they are mad when they be merry, or [y]prophesy lies, or live unjustly, or else lightly forswear themselves.

29 For [z]insomuch as their trust is in idols, which have no life; though they swear falsely, yet they look not to be hurt.

30 Howbeit for both causes shall they be justly punished: both because they thought not well of God, [*]giving heed unto idols, and also unjustly swore in deceit, despising holiness.

31 For it is not the power of them by whom they swear: but it is the just vengeance of sinners, that punisheth always the offence of the ungodly.

15

1 But thou, O God, art gracious and true, longsuffering, and in mercy ordering all things,

2 For if we sin, we are thine, knowing thy power: but we will not sin, knowing that we are counted thine.

3 For to know thee is perfect righteousness: yea, to know thy power is [a]the root of immortality.

4 For neither did the mischievous [b]invention of men deceive us, nor an image spotted with divers colours, the painter’s fruitless labour;

5 The sight whereof [*]enticeth fools to lust after it, and so they desire the form of a dead image, that hath no breath.

6 Both they that make them, they that desire them, and they that worship them, are lovers of evil things, and are worthy to have such things to trust upon.

7 For [c]the potter, tempering soft earth, fashioneth every vessel with much labour for our service: yea, [c]of the same clay he maketh both the vessels that serve for clean uses, and likewise also all such as serve to the contrary: but what is the use of either sort, the potter himself is the judge.

8 And employing his labours lewdly, he maketh a vain god of the same clay, even he which a little before was made of earth himself, and within a little while after returneth to the same, [d]out of which he was taken, [e]when his life which was lent him shall be demanded.

9 Notwithstanding his care is, not that he shall [*]have much labour, nor that his life is short: but striveth to excel goldsmiths and silversmiths, and endeavoureth to do like the workers in brass, and counteth it his glory to make counterfeit things.

10 [f]His heart is ashes, his hope is more vile than earth, and his life of less value than clay:

11 Forasmuch as he knew not his Maker, and him that inspired into him an active soul, and [g]breathed in a living spirit.

12 But they counted our life [h]a pastime, and our [*]time here a market for gain: for, say they, we must be getting every way, though it be by evil means.

13 [*]For this man, [i]that of earthly matter maketh brittle vessels and graven images, knoweth himself to offend above all others.

14 And all the enemies of thy people, that hold them in subjection, are most foolish, and are more miserable than very babes.

15 For they counted all the idols of the heathen to be gods: [k]which neither have the use of eyes to see, nor noses to draw [*]breath, nor ears to hear, nor fingers of hands to handle; and as for their feet, they are slow to go.

16 For man made them, and [l]he that borrowed his own spirit fashioned them: but no man can make a god like unto himself.

17 For being mortal, he worketh [m]a dead thing with wicked hands: for he himself is better than [n]the things which he worshippeth: whereas he lived once, but they never.

18 Yea, [o]they worshipped those beasts also that are most hateful: for being compared together, some are worse than others.

19 Neither are they beautiful, so much as to be desired [p]in respect of beasts: but [q]they went without the praise of God and his blessing.

16

1 Therefore [a]by the like were they punished worthily, and by the multitude of beasts tormented.

2 Instead of which punishment, [aa]dealing graciously with thine own people, thou preparedst for them meat of a strange taste, even [b]quails to stir up their appetite:

3 To the end that they, desiring food, might [c]for the ugly sight of the beasts sent among them lothe even that, which they must needs desire; but these, suffering penury [n]for a short space, might be made partakers of a strange taste.

4 For it was requisite, that upon them exercising tyranny should come penury, [d]which they could not avoid: but to these it should only be shewed how their enemies were tormented.

5 For when [e]the horrible fierceness of beasts came upon [*]these, and [f]they perished with the stings of crooked serpents, thy wrath endured not for ever:

6 But they were troubled [n]for a small season, that they might be admonished, [g]having a sign of salvation, [m]to put them in remembrance of the commandment of thy law.

7 For he that turned himself toward it was not saved by the thing that he saw, [h]but by thee, that art [i]the Saviour of all.

8 And in this thou madest thine enemies confess, that it is thou who deliverest from all evil:

9 For them the bitings of [j]grasshoppers and [k]flies killed, neither was there found any remedy for their life: [l]for they were worthy to be punished by such.

10 But thy sons not the very teeth of venomous dragons overcame: for thy mercy was ever by them, and healed them.

11 For they were [*]pricked, [m]that they should remember thy words; and were [n]quickly saved, that not falling into deep forgetfulness, they might be [*]continually mindful of thy goodness.

12 For it was neither herb, nor [o]mollifying plaister, that restored them to health: but [p]thy word, O Lord, which healeth all things.

13 [q]For thou hast power of life and death: [r]thou leadest to the gates of hell, and bringest up again.

14 [s]A man indeed killeth through his malice: and [t]the spirit, when it is gone forth, returneth not; neither the soul received up cometh again.

15 [s]But it is not possible to escape thine hand.

16 For the ungodly, [u]that denied to know thee, were scourged [v]by the strength of thine arm: [w]with strange rains, hails, and showers, were they persecuted, [d]that they could not avoid, and [w]through fire were they consumed.

17 For, which is most to be wondered at, [x]the fire had more force in the water, that quencheth all things: for [y]the world fighteth for the righteous.

18 For sometime the flame was mitigated, that it might not burn up [z]the beasts that were sent against the ungodly; but themselves might see and perceive that they were persecuted with the judgment of God.

19 And at another time it burneth even in the midst of water above the power of fire, that it might destroy the fruits of an unjust land.

20 Instead whereof [a]thou feddest thine own people with [b]angels’ food, and didst send them [c]from heaven bread prepared without their labour, able to content every man’s delight, and agreeing to every taste.

21 For thy [d][*]sustenance declared thy sweetness unto thy children, and serving to the appetite of the eater, [*]tempered itself to every man’s liking.

22 [e]But snow and [g]ice endured the fire, and melted not, that they might know [w][x]that fire burning in the hail, and [w]sparkling in the rain, [f]did destroy the fruits of the enemies.

23 But [g]this again did even forget his own strength, that [h]the righteous might be nourished.

24 [i]For the creature that serveth thee, who art the Maker increaseth his strength against the unrighteous for their punishment, and abateth his strength for the benefit of such as put their trust in thee.

25 Therefore even then [i]was it altered into all [*]fashions, and was obedient to thy grace, that nourisheth all things, according to the desire [*]of them that had need:

26 That thy children, O Lord, [j]whom thou lovest, [k]might know, that it is not the growing of fruits that nourisheth man: but that it is thy word, which preserveth them that put their trust in thee.

27 For that which was not destroyed of the fire, [l]being warmed with a little sunbeam, soon melted away:

28 That it might be known, that [m]we must prevent the sun to give thee thanks, and at the dayspring [n]pray unto thee.

29 For the hope of [o]the unthankful shall melt away as the winter’s hoar frost, and shall run away as unprofitable water.

17

1 For [a]great are thy judgments, and cannot be expressed: therefore [*]unnurtured souls have erred.

2 For when unrighteous men thought to oppress the holy nation; [b]they being shut up [*]in their houses, the prisoners of darkness, and fettered with the bonds of a long night, lay there [*]exiled from the eternal providence.

3 For while they supposed to lie hid in their secret sins, they were scattered [*]under a dark veil of forgetfulness, being horribly astonished, and troubled with strange [*]apparitions.

4 For neither might the corner that held them keep them from fear: but noises as of waters falling down sounded about them, and sad visions appeared unto them with heavy countenances.

5 No power of the fire might give them light: neither could the bright flames of the stars endure to lighten that horrible night.

6 Only there appeared unto them a fire kindled of itself, very dreadful: for being much terrified, [i]they thought the things which they saw to be worse than the sight they saw not.

7 As for [c]the illusions of art magick, they were put down, and [d]their vaunting in wisdom was reproved with disgrace.

8 For they, that promised to drive away terrors and troubles from a sick soul, were sick themselves of [e]fear, worthy to be laughed at.

9 For though no terrible thing did fear them; yet being scared with beasts that passed by, and hissing of [f]serpents,

10 They died for fear, [*]denying that they saw the air, [g]which could of no side be avoided.

11 For wickedness, condemned by her own witness, is very timorous, and being pressed with conscience, [h]always forecasteth grievous things.

12 For fear is nothing else but a betraying of the succours which reason offereth.

13 And the expectation from within, being less, [i]counteth the ignorance more than the cause which bringeth the torment.

14 But they sleeping the same sleep that night, [*]which was indeed intolerable, and which came upon them out of the bottoms of [k]inevitable hell,

15 Were partly vexed with monstrous [l]apparitions, and partly fainted, [m]their heart failing them: for a sudden fear, and not looked for, came upon them.

16 So then whosoever there fell down was [n]straitly kept, shut up in a prison without iron bars,

17 [o]For whether he were husbandman, or shepherd, or a labourer in the [*]field, he was overtaken, and endured that necessity, which could not be avoided: for they were all bound with one chain of darkness.

18 [p]Whether it were a [pp]whistling wind, or a melodious noise of birds among the spreading branches, or a pleasing fall of water running violently,

19 Or a [*][q]terrible sound of stones cast down, or a running that could not be seen of skipping beasts, or a roaring voice of most [q]savage wild beasts, or a rebounding echo from the hollow mountains; these things made them to swoon for fear.

20 [o]For the whole world shined with clear light, and none were hindered in their labour:

21 Over them only was spread an heavy night, an image of that [r]darkness which should afterward receive them: but yet were they unto themselves more grievous than the darkness.

18

1 [a]Nevertheless thy [h]saints had a very great light, whose voice they [b]hearing, and not seeing their shape, because they also had not suffered the same things, they counted them happy.

2 But for that they did not hurt them now, of whom they had been wronged before, they thanked them, and besought them pardon for that they [c]had been enemies.

3 Instead whereof [d]thou gavest them a burning pillar of fire, both to be a guide of the unknown journey, and an [e]harmless sun to entertain them honourably.

4 [f]For they were worthy to be deprived of light and imprisoned in darkness, who had kept thy sons shut up, by whom the [*]uncorrupt light of the law was to be given unto the world.

5 And [g]when they had determined to slay the babes of [h]the saints, [i]one child being cast forth, and saved, to reprove them, [k]thou tookest away the multitude of their children, and [l]destroyedst them altogether in a mighty water.

6 [m]Of that night were our fathers certified afore, that [n]assuredly knowing [o]unto what oaths they had given credence, they might afterwards be of good cheer.

7 So of thy people was accepted both the salvation of the righteous, and destruction of the enemies.

8 For [p]wherewith thou didst punish our adversaries, [q]by the same thou didst glorify us, whom thou hadst called.

9 For the [h]righteous children of good men [r]did sacrifice [s]secretly, and with one consent made [*]a holy law, that the saints should be like partakers of the same good and evil, the fathers now singing out the songs of praise.

10 But on the other side there sounded [t]an ill according cry of the enemies, and a lamentable noise was carried abroad for children that were bewailed.

11 [u]The master and the servant were punished after one manner; and like as the king, so suffered the common person.

12 [t]So they all together had innumerable dead with one kind of death; neither were the living sufficient to bury them: for in one moment the noblest offspring of them was destroyed.

13 For whereas they would not believe any thing [w]by reason of the enchantments; upon the destruction of the firstborn, [x]they acknowledged this people to be the sons of God.

14 For while all things were in quiet silence, and [k]that night was in the midst of her swift course,

15 [k]Thine Almighty word leaped down from heaven [y]out of thy royal throne, as [z]a fierce man of war into the midst of a land of destruction,

16 And brought thine [a]unfeigned commandment as [b]a sharp sword, and standing up filled all things with death; and [c]it touched the heaven, but it stood upon the earth.

17 Then suddenly [*][d]visions of horrible dreams troubled them sore, and terrors came upon them unlooked for.

18 And one thrown here, and another there, half dead, shewed the cause of his death.

19 For the dreams that troubled them did foreshew this, lest they should perish, and not know why they were afflicted.

20 Yea, [q]the tasting of death touched [e]the righteous also, and [f]there was a destruction of the multitude in the wilderness: [f]but the wrath endured not long.

21 For then [g]the blameless man made haste, and stood forth to defend them; and bringing [i]the shield of his proper ministry, even prayer, and [h]the propitiation of incense, set himself against the wrath, and so brought the calamity to an end, declaring that he was thy servant.

22 So he overcame the destroyer, not with strength of body, nor force of [i]arms, but with a word subdued he him that punished, [k]alleging the oaths and covenants made with the fathers.

23 For when the dead were now fallen down by heaps one upon another, [l]standing between, he stayed the wrath, and [*]parted the way to the living.

24 For [m]in the long garment was the whole world, and [n]in the four rows of the stones was the glory of the fathers graven, and thy Majesty [o]upon the diadem of his head.

25 Unto these [p]the destroyer gave place, and was afraid of them: for it was enough that they only [q]tasted of the wrath.

19

1 As for the ungodly, wrath came upon them without mercy [a]unto the end: for he knew before what they would do;

2 How that [b]having given them leave to depart, and [c]sent them hastily away, [d]they would repent and pursue them.

3 For whilst they were yet mourning and making lamentation at the graves of the dead, they added another foolish device, and pursued them as fugitives, whom they had [*]intreated to be gone.

4 For the destiny, whereof they were worthy, drew them unto this end, and made them forget the things that had already happened, that they might fulfil the punishment which was [e]wanting to their [f]torments:

5 And that [g]thy people might pass a wonderful way: but they might find a strange death.

6 [h]For the whole creature in his proper kind was fashioned again anew, [i]serving the peculiar commandments that were given unto them, that thy children might be kept without hurt:

7 As namely, [k]a cloud shadowing the camp; and where water stood before, dry land appeared; and [g][l]out of the Red sea a way without impediment; and out of the violent stream a green field:

8 Wherethrough all the people went that were defended with thy hand, seeing thy marvellous strange wonders.

9 For [m]they went at large like horses, and [n]leaped like lambs, praising thee, O Lord, who hadst delivered them.

10 For they were yet mindful of the things that were done while they sojourned in the strange land, how the ground brought forth [*]flies instead of cattle, and [o]how the river cast up a multitude of frogs instead of fishes.

11 But afterwards [p]they saw a new generation of fowls, when, being led with their appetite, they asked delicate meats.

12 For quails came up unto them from the sea for their [*]contentment.

13 And punishments came upon the sinners not without former [q]signs [r]by the force of thunders: for they suffered justly according to their own wickedness, [s]insomuch as they used a more hard and hateful behaviour toward strangers.

14 For [t]the Sodomites did not receive those, whom they knew not when they came: but [u]these brought friends into bondage, that had well deserved of them.

15 And not only so, but peradventure some [x]respect shall be had [t]of those, because they used strangers not friendly:

16 But [u]these very grievously afflicted them, [y]whom they had received with feastings, and were already made partakers of the same laws with them.

17 Therefore [z]even with blindness were these stricken, as [a]those were at the doors of [b]the righteous man: when, being compassed about with horrible great darkness, [c]every one sought the passage of his own doors.

18 For the elements were changed [*]in themselves by a kind of harmony, like as in a [cc]psaltery notes change the name of the tune, and yet are always sounds; which may well be perceived by the sight of [d]the things that have been done.

19 For [e]earthly things were turned into watery, and [f]the things, that before swam in the water, now went upon the ground.

20 [g]The fire had power in the water, forgetting his own virtue: and the water forgat his own quenching nature.

21 On the other side, [h]the flames wasted not the flesh of the corruptible living things, though they walked therein; neither [i]melted they [k]the icy kind of heavenly meat that was of nature apt to melt.

22 For in all things, O Lord, thou didst magnify thy people, and glorify them, neither didst thou lightly regard them: but didst assist them [l]in every time and place.

a 1.1 So Deut. 1. 16. 1 Kings 3. 3, 9. Ps. 45. 7. Isai. 56. 1.

b 1.2 Deut. 4. 29. 2 Chr. 15. 4.

* 1.3 Or, maketh manifest. ver. 5, 8. So ver. 9.

c 1.5 Comp. Jer. 4. 22.

* 1.5 Or, is rebuked, or, sheweth itself. ver. 3, 8. ch. 2. 11 (Gk.).

d 1.6 So Gal. 5. 22.

* 1.6 Or, lips.

e 1.6 Jer. 17. 10.

f 1.6 So Esther 15. 2. & 16. 4.

g 1.7 Comp. Isai. 6. 3.

h 1.7 See Esther 13. 2.

* 1.7 Or, upholdeth.

i 1.7 Ps. 139. 4.

k 1.8 ver. 3 marg. (Gk.).

* 1.9 Or, reproving. ch. 2. 14. So ver. 3, 5, 8.

l 1.10 So ch. 5. 17. See Ex. 20. 5.

m 1.10 Phil. 2. 14.

m 1.11 Phil. 2. 14.

n 1.11 2 Cor. 12. 20. 1 Pet. 2. 1 (Gk.).

o 1.11 So Matt. 12. 36.

* 1.11 Or, slandereth.

oo 1.11 See Ecclus. 21. 2.

p 1.12 Comp. Deut. 4. 23, 24.

p 1.12 Comp. Deut. 4. 23, 24.

q 1.13 So ch. 2. 23, 24.

r 1.13 So Esdr. 8. 59. See Ezek. 18. 32.

s 1.14 Gen. 1. 31.

t 1.16 So Rom. 6. 23.

u 1.16 Isai. 28. 15.

x 1.16 Comp. ch. 2. 24 (Gk.).

a 2.1 ch. 1. 16.

b 2.1 So Job 7. 1. & 14. 1.

c 2.1 Comp. Matt. 22. 23. 1 Cor. 15. 32.

d 2.1 1 Esdr. 3. 3. Tobit 2. 9. Judith 13. 1. 2 Macc. 8. 25. Luke 12. 36 in the Gk.

e 2.2 Obad. 16. Ecclus. 44. 9. So Job 10. 19.

f 2.2 Ps. 102. 3. Comp. ch. 5. 14.

g 2.3 Eccles. 3. 20. See Ecclus. 17. 1.

* 2.3 Or, moist.

h 2.4 Eccles. 2. 16. & 9. 5.

i 2.4 Job 7. 9.

* 2.4 Or, oppressed.

j 2.5 ch. 5. 9. 1 Chr. 29. 15. So Job 8. 9.

* 2.5 Or, he.

k 2.5 Comp. Dan. 6. 17. Matt. 27. 66.

l 2.6 See Isai. 22. 13.

* 2.6 Or, earnestly. Luke 7. 4. Titus 3. 13 in the Gk.

ll 2.8 So Ecclus. 32. 2.

* 2.9 Or, jollity. See 1 Esdr. 3. 20 (Engl.).

m 2.9 Comp. Eccles. 3. 22.

n 2.11 ch. 1. 5 marg.

o 2.12 Comp. Prov. 1. 11.

p 2.14 So John 7. 7. Ephes. 5. 13.

q 2.14 ch. 1. 9 marg.

r 2.15 Comp. Isai. 53. 3.

* 2.16 Or, false coin.

s 2.16 So Jer. 6. 30.

t 2.16 Numb. 23. 10. Ps. 116. 15.

u 2.16 Comp. Matt. 27. 43.

w 2.17 ch. 8. 8. & 11. 14. 1 Cor. 10. 13. Heb. 13. 7 in the Gk.

x 2.18 Ps. 22. 8, 9.

u 2.18 Comp. Matt. 27. 43.

y 2.19 Comp. Jer. 11. 19. & 18. 18.

z 2.19 ch. 12. 18. Baruch 2. 27. Song 19 in the Gk. See Acts 24. 4.

a 2.19 So 2 Tim. 2. 24 marg.

b 2.20 Comp. Gen. 37. 20.

c 2.20 Gk. as ch. 3. 7, 9, 13. & 4. 15. & 14. 11. & 19. 15. Ecclus. 18. 20. & 23. 24. & 34. 6. Luke 19. 44. 1 Pet. 2. 12.

d 2.21 So ch. 4. 12.

e 2.22 Matt. 13. 11.

* 2.22 Gr. preferred, or, esteemed the reward.

f 2.23 So ch. 1. 13.

g 2.23 See Gen. 1. 26. So Ecclus. 17. 3.

h 2.24 Gen. 3. 13.

i 2.24 Comp. ch. 1. 16 (Gk.).

a 3.1 Deut. 33. 3.

b 3.2 ch. 5. 4 (Gk.). So ch. 4. 17.

c 3.2 ch. 7. 6 (Gk.). See Luke 9. 31.

d 3.3 Ecclus. 40. 9. 1 Macc. 2. 7. Rom. 3. 16 in the Gk.

e 3.4 Comp. Rom. 8. 24. 2 Cor. 5. 1. 1 Pet. 1. 13.

f 3.5 Comp. Heb. 12. 11.

* 3.5 Or, benefited. ch. 11. 5, 13. & 16. 2 (Gk.).

g 3.5 See Ex. 15. 25.

* 3.5 Or, meet. Matt. 3. 8. Acts 26. 20.

h 3.6 See Prov. 17. 3. & 1 Pet. 1. 7.

i 3.7 See ch. 2. 20.

k 3.7 Matt. 13. 43. Comp. Ps. 91. 15.

l 3.8 Ecclus. 4. 15. Matt. 19. 28. 1 Cor. 6. 2.

m 3.8 See Rev. 19. 6.

n 3.9 Comp. ch. 6. 12. Ps. 119. 27. John 7. 17. See Job 32. 8.

* 3.9 Or, and such as be faithful shall remain with him in love.

o 3.9 Acts 11. 23 (Gk.).

p 3.9 ch. 4. 15.

p 3.9 ch. 4. 15.

i 3.9 See ch. 2. 20.

q 3.9 See Esther 16. 21.

r 3.10 So Matt. 25. 41.

s 3.11 Prov. 1. 7 (Gk.).

* 3.12 Or, light, or, unchaste. Gk. as ver. 2. ch. 5. 4.

t 3.13 Heb. 13. 3.

t 3.13 Heb. 13. 3.

u 3.13 So Isai. 56. 3–5. Comp. Matt. 19. 12.

i 3.13 See ch. 2. 20.

u 3.14 So Isai. 56. 3–5. Comp. Matt. 19. 12.

* 3.14 Gr. the chosen. 1 Pet. 2. 4.

* 3.14 Or, amongst the people.

u 3.14 So Isai. 56. 3–5. Comp. Matt. 19. 12.

v 3.15 So Ecclus. 1. 6, 20. Comp. ch. 15. 3.

w 3.16 Isai. 57. 3.

x 3.16 ch. 4. 5 (Gk.). Comp. 2 Sam. 12. 14.

* 3.16 Or, be partakers of holy things: Comp. Deut. 23. 2. ch. 4. 13 marg.

y 3.18 ver. 11. Comp. ver. 4.

z 3.18 Phil. 2. 1. So ch. 19. 12.

* 3.18 Or, hearing. Acts 25. 21 & marg.

* 4.1 Or, approved. See Nahum 1. 7.

a 4.1 So Acts 24. 16.

b 4.2 So ch. 5. 16. See James 1. 12.

c 4.2 1 Tim. 6. 12. 2 Tim. 4. 7 in the Gk.

d 4.3 Ecclus. 23. 25. See Job 18. 16.

e 4.4 Matt. 7. 19, 27.

e 4.4 Matt. 7. 19, 27.

f 4.5 ch. 3. 16 (Gk.).

g 4.5 So Rom. 11. 17, 19, 20.

h 4.6 Comp. Ecclus. 41. 7.

* 4.6 Gr. sleeps. ch. 7. 2.

i 4.7 ch. 6. 13. & 16. 28. See Matt. 17. 25 Engl.

j 4.10 ver. 14. So Gen. 5. 24 (Gk.). Ecclus. 44. 16. Heb. 11. 5.

k 4.11 Comp. Isai. 57. 1.

l 4.12 So ch. 2. 21.

* 4.12 Gr. pervert.

m 4.13 See Heb. 5. 9.

* 4.13 Or, sanctified, or, consummated. Heb. 12. 23. Comp. ch. 3. 16 marg.

j 4.14 ver. 14. So Gen. 5. 24 (Gk.). Ecclus. 44. 16. Heb. 11. 5.

n 4.15 ch. 3. 9.

nn 4.15 See ch. 2. 20.

o 4.16 ch. 15. 9.

oo 4.16 Matt. 12. 41, 42. Luke 11. 31, 32.

p 4.16 Comp. Isai. 65. 20.

q 4.17 Comp. ch. 3. 2.

r 4.19 So Ps. 9. 6.

* 4.20 Or, to the casting up of the account. Comp. Matt. 18. 23, 24. & 25. 19.

a 5.1 See Luke 21. 36.

b 5.3 2 Esdr. 16. 19. See Rom. 8. 35.

* 5.3 Or, parable. Gk. as Matt. 13. 3, &c.

c 5.4 ch. 3. 2 (Gk.).

* 5.7 Or, filled ourselves, or, surfeited.

d 5.7 Comp. Job 12. 24. Ps. 107. 4, 40.

e 5.9 See ch. 2. 5.

f 5.9 Job 9. 25. See 2 Chr. 30. 6.

g 5.10 Job 9. 26. So Prov. 30. 19.

g 5.11 Job 9. 26. So Prov. 30. 19.

* 5.11 Or, flieth.

h 5.11 ch. 19. 13. Acts 1. 3 in the Gk.

i 5.12 ver. 21 (Gk.). So Phil. 3. 14.

k 5.14 So Job 8. 14. Prov. 10. 25, 28. & 11. 7.

* 5.14 Gr. thistledown. Ps. 1. 4 (Gk.).

l 5.14 Ps. 103. 16. James 1. 10, 11.

* 5.14 Or, chaff.

m 5.14 Ps. 68. 2. Comp. ch. 2. 2.

n 5.15 See Gen. 15. 1. & Rev. 22. 12.

* 5.16 Or, palace: unless the word be taken unproperly, as 2 Macc. 2. 17.

o 5.16 Isai. 62. 3. So ch. 4. 2.

p 5.16 So Ps. 91. 4.

q 5.17 See ch. 1. 19.

r 5.17 To ver. 20, Eph. 6. 13–17.

t 5.17 So ver. 17, 21–23.

s 5.18 Isai. 59. 17.

ss 5.18 ch. 18. 16 (Gk.).

* 5.19 Or, equity. ch. 9. 3. Rather as ch. 6. 10. & 10. 15, 17. & 14. 30.

t 5.20 So ver. 17, 21–23.

u 5.21 Comp. 2 Esdr. 16. 13.

i 5.21 ver. 21 (Gk.). So Phil. 3. 14.

v 5.22 Josh. 10. 11. Comp. Ecclus. 43. 15.

w 5.22 Gen. 6. 17. Dan. 9. 26.

x 5.23 ch. 11. 20 (Gk.).

y 5.23 Job 27. 20, 21.

y 5.23 Job 27. 20, 21.

z 5.23 So ch. 8. 11. See Luke 1. 52.

a 6.1 Ps. 2. 10.

b 6.3 So Rom. 13. 1, 2. See Prov. 8. 15.

c 6.4 Comp. Rom. 13. 4.

d 6.6 Comp. Luke 12. 47, 48.

e 6.6 Comp. Matt. 21. 41 (Gk.).

f 6.7 See 1 Esdr. 4. 39.

g 6.7 So Ps. 145. 9. ch. 12. 13.

h 6.9 ch. 12. 2 (Gk.). Heb. 6. 6.

* 6.10 Or, justified. Comp. Rev. 22. 11.

* 6.10 Or, a defence. Acts 22. 1. Phil. 1. 7, 17.

i 6.12 See Prov. 14. 6. So Deut. 30. 11–14. ch. 3. 9. Ecclus. 14. 21. & 21. 11. John 7. 17.

j 6.13 See ch. 4. 7.

k 6.14 Prov. 8. 17.

l 6.15 ch. 7. 23 (Gk.).

* 6.17 Or, nurture. ch. 3. 11. & 7. 14 (Gk.).

* 6.17 Or, nurture. ch. 3. 11. & 7. 14 (Gk.).

m 6.18 Comp. Rom. 13. 10.

n 6.20 Comp. ver. 21.

o 6.21 ch. 7. 8.

n 6.21 Comp. ver. 21.

p 6.23 Comp. ch. 7. 13 marg.

q 6.24 See Prov. 11. 14 (Gk.).

a 7.1 Gen. 2. 7. See Ecclus. 17. 1.

b 7.2 Job 10. 10.

c 7.2 ch. 4. 6.

d 7.3 See Acts 14. 15.

e 7.4 Luke 2. 7, 12.

f 7.6 See Job 1. 21.

g 7.6 See ch. 3. 2.

h 7.7 1 Kings 3. 7–9.

i 7.7 Acts 7. 59.

k 7.8 ch. 6. 21.

l 7.8 See Job 28. 15. Comp. ch. 8. 5.

* 7.9 Gr. stone of inestimable Price.

m 7.9 Job 28. 16–19. Prov. 3. 15.

n 7.10 Comp. Prov. 4. 22.

o 7.10 ver. 26. 2 Esdr. 14. 47 marg.

p 7.11 1 Kings 3. 13. Prov. 3. 16. Ecclus. 51. 28. Comp. Matt. 6. 33.

p 7.11 1 Kings 3. 13. Prov. 3. 16. Ecclus. 51. 28. Comp. Matt. 6. 33.

* 7.13 Gr. without guile.

* 7.13 Gr. without envy. ch. 6. 23. Comp. James 1. 5.

pp 7.13 SeeEcclus. 20. 30.

q 7.14 Ecclus. 40. 18.

* 7.14 Or, enter friendship with God.

qq 7.14 So ver. 27.

r 7.14 2 Cor. 10. 18.

rr 7.14 ch. 6. 17 (Gk.).

* 7.15 Or, God grant.

* 7.15 Or, are to be spoken of.

s 7.18 Deut. 33. 14 (Gk.). So Job 38. 33. James 1. 17.

t 7.19 ver. 29 (Gk.).

u 7.20 So Ecclus. 27. 5. See Luke 2. 35.

v 7.22 So ch. 8. 5. Comp. Prov. 8. 30.

* 7.22 Gr. only-begotten.

w 7.22 ch. 10. 21 (Gk.).

x 7.22 Tit. 1. 8 (Gk.).

y 7.23 ch. 6. 15 (Gk.).

* 7.25 Or, vapour. James 4. 14.

* 7.25 Or, stream.

z 7.25 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

a 7.26 Heb. 1. 3.

aa 7.26 See Ecclus. 12. 11.

b 7.26 See 2 Cor. 4. 4.

* 7.27 Or, createth.

c 7.27 So ver. 14. See James 2. 23.

d 7.27 See Gen. 20. 7. Comp. Tobit 4. 12.

t 7.29 ver. 29 (Gk.).

* 8.1 Or, profitably. Comp. ver. 7.

* 8.2 Or, to marry her to myself. So ver. 9. Comp. ver. 18.

a 8.2 Cant. 4. 8.

b 8.3 Gk. as ver. 9, 16. So Bel and Drag. 2 marg.

* 8.4 Or, teacher.

* 8.4 Or, chooser.

c 8.5 ch. 7. 8, 9. Prov. 8. 18.

d 8.5 So ch. 7. 22.

e 8.6 Comp. Exod. 31. 3, 6.

q 8.7 So ver. 7 (Gk.).

f 8.8 See Prov. 1. 6.

g 8.8 See ch. 2. 17.

h 8.9 ver. 2 marg.

b 8.9 Gk. as ver. 9, 16. So Bel and Drag. 2 marg.

* 8.9 Gr. will.

i 8.10 ch. 9. 5. 1 Kin. 3. 7.

k 8.11 1 Kin. 3. 28.

l 8.11 See ch. 5. 23.

m 8.12 Job 29. 8, 9, 10, 11.

n 8.12 So Ecclus. 5. 12. See Judg. 18. 19.

o 8.13 ver. 17.

* 8.14 Or, govern. Gk. as ver. 1. ch. 15. 1.

p 8.14 1 Kin. 4. 21, 24.

* 8.15 Or, appear.

q 8.15 So ver. 7 (Gk.).

* 8.16 Or, Being entered into mine house.

b 8.16 Gk. as ver. 9, 16. So Bel and Drag. 2 marg.

r 8.17 Comp. Prov. 7. 3.

o 8.17 ver. 17.

* 8.18 Or, fame.

* 8.18 Or, marry her. See ver. 2.

s 8.20 Comp. John 9. 2.

t 8.21 Ecclus. 6. 27 (Gk.).

* 8.21 Or, went.

u 8.21 ch 16. 28. See Rom. 11. 2.

a 9.1 Gen. 1. 3, 6, 9, &c. Ps. 33. 9. John 1. 3.

b 9.2 Gen. 1. 28. Ps. 8. 6.

c 9.3 ch. 5. 19 marg.

d 9.4 1 Kings 3. 9.

e 9.4 So ch. 15. 18. See John 1. 1.

f 9.5 See Ps. 116. 16.

g 9.5 See ch. 8. 10.

h 9.6 Acts 19. 27 (Gk.).

i 9.7 1 Chr. 28. 5. 2 Chr. 1. 9.

k 9.8 2 Sam. 7. 12, 13.

l 9.8 Ps. 99. 9.

m 9.8 So Heb. 8. 5.

n 9.8 See Matt. 25. 34.

e 9.9 So ch. 15. 18. See John 1. 1.

o 9.9 Prov. 8. 22, 27. John 1. 2, 3, 10.

p 9.10 Ps. 20. 6.

* 9.11 Or, by her power, or, glory.

q 9.13 ver. 17. So Ecclus. 1. 6. See Rom. 11. 34.

* 9.14 Or, fearful. Ecclus. 2. 12. & 22. 18. 1 Macc. 3. 56. Matt. 8. 26. Mark 4. 40. Rev. 21. 8.

r 9.15 2 Cor. 5. 1, 4. See Job 4. 19.

s 9.15 1 Cor. 15. 47. 48, 49 (Engl.).

t 9.16 See 2 Esdr. 4. 9.

* 9.16 Gr. athand. So ch. 19. 3 (Gk.).

q 9.17 ver. 17. So Ecclus. 1. 6. See Rom. 11. 34.

u 9.17 1 Cor. 2. 10, 11.

u 9.17 1 Cor. 2. 10, 11.

x 9.18 ch. 10. 4.

a 10.1 So 1 Tim. 2. 13.

b 10.2 Gen. 1. 28. & 2. 20.

c 10.3 Gen. 4. 5, 8, 11–13.

c 10.3 Gen. 4. 5, 8, 11–13.

d 10.4 Gen. 7. 19, 21–23. 2 Pet. 2. 5.

e 10.4 ch. 9. 18. So ver. 11.

f 10.4 Gen. 6. 9.

g 10.4 So ch. 14. 5, 6.

h 10.5 Gen. 11. 9.

i 10.5 Gen. 12. 1.

k 10.5 ch. 18. 21. ver. 15. So ch. 2. 22. See Luke 1. 6.

l 10.5 Gen. 22. 10.

* 10.5 Or, in.

m 10.6 Gen. 19. 16, 17, 22.

n 10.6 ch. 19. 17. 2 Pet. 2. 7.

* 10.6 Gr. Pentapolis.

o 10.6 Gen. 10. 19. & 13. 10. & 19. 22. Deut. 29. 23. Hos. 11. 8.

p 10.7 Gen. 19. 26. Luke 17. 32.

q 10.10 Gen. 28. 5, 10.

r 10.10 Gen. 28. 12–22.

s 10.10 Gen. 30. 43.

t 10.11 Gen. 31. 1–16.

u 10.12 Gen. 32. 6, 7. & 33. 4.

x 10.12 Gen. 32. 24–30.

y 10.13 Gen. 37. 28. Acts 7. 9.

z 10.13 Gen. 39. 7–9.

a 10.13 Gen. 37. 24 or Gen. 39. 20.

b 10.14 Gen. 41. 14, 40, 41. Acts 7. 10.

* 10.14 Or, the power of them that rule d over him.

c 10.14 Construction as Matt. 10. 1.

d 10.14 Gen. 39. 17.

e 10.15 Ex. 1. 12. & 12. 42.

* 10.15 Or, holy. ver. 17. ch. 5. 19. & 6. 10. & 14. 30. Song 65 (text).

f 10.15 ver. 5.

g 10.16 Ex. 3. 10. & 4. 12.

h 10.16 Ex. 14. 31. Ps. 105. 26. See Heb. 3. 5.

i 10.16 Ex. 5. 1. & 7. 10. & ch. 8–ch. 13. Ps. 105. 27–36.

i 10.16 Ex. 5. 1. & 7. 10. & ch. 8–ch. 13. Ps. 105. 27–36.

j 10.17 Ex. 12. 35.

* 10.17 Or, holy. ver. 17. ch. 5. 19. & 6. 10. & 14. 30. Song 65 (text).

k 10.17 Ps. 105. 39. See Ecclus. 14. 27.

l 10.17 Ps. 78. 14.

* 10.17 Or, flame. ch. 16. 18.

m 10.18 Ex. 14. 21, 22, 29. Ps. 78. 13.

n 10.19 Ex. 14. 27, 28.

o 10.19 So 2 Macc. 1. 12 (Gk.).

p 10.20 ch. 16. 23. & 18. 20. Gk. not as ver. 15, 17.

q 10.20 Ex. 15. 1.

r 10.21 ch. 7. 22 (Gk.).

a 11.1 See Deut. 34. 10.

b 11.2 Ex. 16. 1.

c 11.3 Ex. 17. 10, 11, 13. 2 Esdr. 1. 10.

d 11.4 Ex. 17. 6. Numb. 20. 11.

e 11.6 Ex. 7. 17.

f 11.7 Ex. 1. 16, 22. ch. 18. 5.

g 11.7 Ps. 78. 16.

h 11.8 Ex. 7. 20.

i 11.9 ver. 6.

j 11.10 So Heb. 12. 7. See Deut. 8. 5.

k 11.13 See Ex. 8. 8.

* 11.13 Or, perceived.

l 11.14 Ex. 2. 3.

m 11.14 See ch. 2. 17.

n 11.15 ch. 17. 9. Gk. as Rom. 1. 23.

o 11.15 ch. 13. 14. Comp. ch. 15. 18.

p 11.15 Ex. 8. 2, 17, 24.

q 11.16 ch. 12. 23, 24. & 16. 1.

r 11.17 Gen. 1. 2.

s 11.17 See Lev. 26. 22. Comp. Jer. 8. 17.

t 11.18 So ch. 16. 5.

u 11.20 Acts 28. 4.

v 11.20 ch. 5. 23 (Gk.).

w 11.20 Comp. Ecclus. 16. 25.

ww 11.20 Comp. Ecclus. 1. 9.

x 11.21 So 2 Chr. 20. 6.

* 11.22 Or, little weight. Isai. 40. 15 (Gk.).

y 11.22 Hos. 6. 4. & 13. 3.

z 11.23 See 2 Pet. 3. 9.

a 11.25 Rom. 4. 17. See Ps. 147. 4.

b 11.26 ch. 12. 8, 16 (Gk.). So ch. 12. 18 (Gk.).

a 12.2 See ch. 6. 9.

* 12.3 Or, ancient.

b 12.4 See Deut. 18. 12.

* 12.4 Or, sorceries. Rev. 9. 21. & 18. 23.

c 12.4 Gal. 5. 20.

d 12.5 ch. 14. 23. See Lev. 18. 21.

d 12.6 ch. 14. 23. See Lev. 18. 21.

* 12.7 Or, new inhabitance.

e 12.8 ch. 11. 26.

f 12.8 See Ex. 23. 28.

g 12.10 Ex. 23. 30. Deut. 7. 22.

h 12.11 Gen. 9. 25.

i 12.12 See Rom. 9. 20. Comp. Job 36. 23.

j 12.12 So Heb. 12. 7. See Deut. 8. 5.

k 12.12 Rom. 8. 33.

* 12.12 Or, in thy presence.

* 12.12 Or, a revenger. Rom. 13. 4.

l 12.13 1 Pet. 5. 7. So ch. 6. 7.

m 12.14 Ecclus. 19. 5. Acts 27. 15 in the Gk.

n 12.15 Comp. Job 10. 2, 3.

e 12.16 ch. 11. 26.

* 12.17 Or, perfect.

o 12.18 See ch. 2. 19.

e 12.18 ch. 11. 26.

p 12.18 So Ps. 135. 6.

q 12.20 Comp. Rom. 9. 22.

r 12.20 So ch. 19. 22.

s 12.21 So Ephes. 5. 15. See Tobit 4. 14.

t 12.21 Deut. 7. 8. & 13. 17, &c.

u 12.22 Matt. 7. 2. See Matt. 5. 7.

v 12.23 ch. 11. 15, 16. & 16. 1. So ver. 27.

* 12.23 Or, abominable idols. 1 Kin. 11. 5, 7. 2 Kin. 23. 13 in the Gk.

w 12.23 ch. 14. 11.

v 12.24 ch. 11. 15, 16. & 16. 1. So ver. 27.

x 12.24 ch. 13. 3 (Gk.). See Rom. 1. 23.

y 12.26 Gk. as ch. 15. 12.

z 12.27 ver. 23.

a 12.27 Comp. 1 Thess. 2. 16.

a 13.1 To end ch. 15, Rom. 1. 19–32.

b 13.1 Ecclus. 38. 27 (Engl.).

c 13.2 Deut. 4. 19. & 17. 3.

c 13.2 Deut. 4. 19. & 17. 3.

d 13.3 ch. 12. 24 (Gk.).

e 13.5 So Rom. 1. 20.

f 13.7 So Rom. 1. 21.

* 13.7 Or, seck.

g 13.10 ver. 18. ch. 15. 17.

h 13.10 See Baruch 6. 4.

i 13.10 Comp Acts. 17. 29.

j 13.11 See Isai. 40. 19.

* 13.11 Or, timber-wright.

k 13.11 So Baruch 6. 59. 2 Tim. 2. 21.

l 13.12 Isai. 44. 15, 16.

* 13.12 Or, chips.

m 13.12 ver. 13.

m 13.13 ver. 13.

n 13.14 ch. 11. 15.

o 13.15 Isai. 46. 7. Comp. Baruch 6. 26, 27.

p 13.17 Isai. 44. 17, 19.

g 13.18 ver. 18. ch. 15. 17.

q 13.18 Acts 26. 22 (Gk.). Comp. Baruch 6. 4.

* 13.18 Gr. that hath no experience at all.

r 13.18 Jer. 10. 5.

* 14.1 Or, ship.

* 14.2 That is, vessel, or, ship.

a 14.3 Comp. Ex. 14. 22. Ps. 107. 23–30.

b 14.5 So ch. 10. 4.

c 14.6 Gen. 6. 4. & 7. 10, 18, 21, 22. Ecclus. 16. 7.

d 14.7 Comp. 1 Pet. 3. 20 or 2 Esdr. 5. 5.

e 14.8 Ps. 115. 8. See Baruch 6. 4.

f 14.9 Ps. 5. 5.

g 14.11 Ex. 12. 12 text. Num. 33. 4. Jer. 10. 11. & 46. 25. See Isai. 46. 1.

* 14.11 Or, to, or, by.

h 14.11 Jer. 10. 15. See ch. 2. 20.

* 14.11 Gr. scandals. See Matt. 13. 41.

i 14.11 Ps. 69. 22 (Gk.). Rom. 11. 9. Comp. Jer. 10. 8. Hab. 2. 18.

* 14.11 Or, trap.

i 14.11 Ps. 69. 22 (Gk.). Rom. 11. 9. Comp. Jer. 10. 8. Hab. 2. 18.

j 14.12 So ver. 27.

k 14.12 See ch. 15. 4.

l 14.15 ver. 23.

l 14.15 ver. 23.

* 14.16 Gr. in time.

* 14.16 Or, tyrants. ch. 6. 21. & 12. 14. Ecclus. 11. 5. Gk. not as ver. 17.

* 14.17 Or, in sight. ch. 15. 19.

m 14.17 2 Cor. 7. 11 (Gk.).

n 14.18 ver. 27 (Gk.). See Acts 26. 5.

* 14.19 Gr. to the better.

o 14.20 ch. 15. 17 (Gk.). See 2 Thess. 2. 4.

p 14.21 So Ecclus. 8. 11 (Gk.).

q 14.21 Comp. Isai. 42. 8.

* 14.21 That is, of God.

r 14.23 See ch. 12. 5.

l 14.23 ver. 23.

l 14.23 ver. 23.

s 14.23 2 Macc. 6. 4. Rom. 13. 13 (Gk.). Gal. 5. 21. 1 Pet. 4. 3.

t 14.25 So Rom. 1. 29–31.

* 14.25 Or, confusedly.

u 14.26 See ch. 16. 29.

* 14.26 Or, sex. Comp. Rom. 1. 26, 27.

v 14.26 See Acts 15. 20.

w 14.26 See Mark 7. 22.

x 14.27 So Rom. 1. 25. ver. 12.

n 14.27 ver. 27 (Gk.). See Acts 26. 5.

* 14.27 Gr. nameless. Ex. 23. 13. Ps. 16. 4.

y 14.28 See Jer. 5. 31.

z 14.29 Comp. Baruch 6. 35.

* 14.30 Or, devoted.

a 15.3 See ch. 3. 15.

b 15.4 ch. 14. 12. Acts 8. 22 (Gk.).

* 15.5 Or, turneth a reproach to the foolish.

c 15.7 See Rom. 9. 21.

c 15.7 See Rom. 9. 21.

d 15.8 Gen. 3. 19.

e 15.8 Luke 12. 20. Comp. ver. 16.

* 15.9 Or, be sick, or, die. ch. 4. 16.

f 15.10 Isai. 44. 20 (Gk.).

g 15.11 Gen. 2. 7.

h 15.12 ch. 12. 26 (Gk.).

* 15.12 Gr. life.

* 15.13 Or, So.

i 15.13 ver. 8.

k 15.15 Ps. 115. 5–7. & 135. 16, 17.

* 15.15 Or, air.

l 15.16 Comp. ver. 8.

m 15.17 ch. 13. 10, 18.

n 15.17 ch. 14. 20 (Gk.). See 2 Thess. 2. 4.

o 15.18 Comp. ch. 11. 15.

p 15.19 ch. 14. 7 (Gk.).

q 15.19 Comp. Gen. 1. 25, 31. & 3. 14.

a 16.1 ch. 11. 15, 16. & 12. 23.

aa 16.2 See ch. 3. 5.

b 16.2 Ex. 16. 13. Num. 11. 31. So ch. 19. 11.

c 16.3 Ex. 8. 5, 28. Comp. ver. 18.

n 16.3 ch. 14. 20 (Gk.). See 2 Thess. 2. 4.

d 16.4 ver. 16.

e 16.5 So ch. 11. 18. Ecclus. 39. 30.

* 16.5 That is, thy people.

f 16.5 Numb. 21. 6. 1 Cor. 10. 9. Ecclus. 39. 30.

n 16.6 ch. 14. 20 (Gk.). See 2 Thess. 2. 4.

g 16.6 Numb. 21. 9.

m 16.6 ch. 13. 10, 18.

h 16.7 John 3. 14.

i 16.7 See 1 Tim. 4. 10.

j 16.9 Exod. 10. 4 (Gk.). Rev. 9. 3, 7 (Gk.). Comp. Ex. 10. 17.

k 16.9 So Ex. 8. 24. Ps. 78. 45.

l 16.9 Rev. 16. 6. Comp. ch. 18. 4.

* 16.11 Gr. stung.

m 16.11 So ver. 6.

n 16.11 So ver. 3, 6.

* 16.11 Or, never drawn from. Ecclus. 41. 1 (Gk.).

o 16.12 Isai. 1. 6 (Gk.).

p 16.12 Ps. 107. 20.

q 16.13 Ps. 105. 27–45.

r 16.13 See Tobit 13. 2. Comp. Rev. 1. 18.

s 16.14 Comp. Matt. 10. 28.

t 16.14 So Eccles. 8. 8.

s 16.15 Comp. Matt. 10. 28.

u 16.16 Ex. 5. 2.

v 16.16 So 2 Esdr. 15. 11. See Deut. 4. 34.

w 16.16 Ex. 9. 23, 24.

d 16.16 ver. 16.

w 16.16 Ex. 9. 23, 24.

x 16.17 ch. 19. 20. So ver. 22.

y 16.17 Comp. Judg. 5. 20. ver. 24.

z 16.18 ch. 19. 21. Comp. ver. 3.

a 16.20 Ex. 16. 14. Numb. 11. 7.

b 16.20 Ps. 78. 25. 2 Esdr. 1. 19.

c 16.20 John 6. 31.

d 16.21 Judg. 6. 4 (Gk. & Engl.).

* 16.21 That is, manna.

* 16.21 Or, was tempered.

e 16.22 ch. 19. 21.

g 16.22 Comp. ver. 22. ch. 19. 21 with Ex. 16. 14.

w 16.22 Ex. 9. 23, 24.

x 16.22 ch. 19. 20. So ver. 22.

w 16.22 Ex. 9. 23, 24.

f 16.22 ver. 19.

g 16.23 Comp. ver. 22. ch. 19. 21 with Ex. 16. 14.

h 16.23 ch. 10. 20. & 18. 20.

i 16.24 ch. 19. 6.

i 16.25 ch. 19. 6.

* 16.25 Or, things.

* 16.25 Or, of them that prayed. ch. 18. 2 (Gk.).

j 16.26 Deut. 4. 37. & 7. 13. & 10. 15.

k 16.26 See Deut. 8. 3.

l 16.27 Ex. 16. 21.

m 16.28 See Ps. 88. 13. & ch. 4. 7. See Ecclus. 32. 14.

n 16.28 ch. 8. 21.

o 16.29 Luke 6. 35. 2 Tim. 3. 2. So ch. 14. 26.

a 17.1 Ex. 6. 6. & 7. 4.

* 17.1 Or, souls that will not be reformed.

b 17.2 Ex. 10. 22, 23. ch. 19. 17.

* 17.2 Or, under their roofs.

* 17.2 Or, fugitives. ch. 19. 3.

* 17.3 Or, in.

* 17.3 Or, sights.

i 17.6 ch. 19. 6.

c 17.7 Ex. 7. 11, 12. & 8. 7, 19. & 9. 11. So ch. 18. 13.

d 17.7 So 2 Tim. 3. 8, 9.

e 17.8 Heb. 5. 7 (text).

f 17.9 ch. 11. 15.

* 17.10 Or, refusing to look upon.

g 17.10 Comp. Ex. 10. 21.

h 17.11 So Job 15. 22.

i 17.13 Comp. ver. 6.

* 17.14 Or, kwherein they could do nothing.

k 17.14 Gk. as marg. Comp. Eccles. 9. 10.

l 17.15 Matt. 14. 26. Mark 6. 49 in the Gk.

m 17.15 Comp. Luke 21. 26.

n 17.16 2 Cor. 11. 32 (Gk.).

o 17.17 So ch. 19. 17.

* 17.17 Or, desert.

p 17.18 Comp. Lev. 26. 36. Ps. 53. 5.

pp 17.18 So Song 27.

* 17.19 Or, hideous.

q 17.19 Gk. the same.

q 17.19 Gk. the same.

o 17.20 So ch. 19. 17.

r 17.21 2 Pet. 2. 17. Jude 13. See Matt. 8. 12.

a 18.1 Ex. 10. 23.

h 18.1 So Job 15. 22.

b 18.1 So Acts 9. 7.

c 18.2 2 Macc. 3. 4 (Gk.).

d 18.3 See Ex. 13. 21.

e 18.3 Comp. PS. 121. 6.

f 18.4 Comp. ch. 16. 10.

* 18.4 Or, incorruptible. ch. 12. 1.

g 18.5 See ch. 11. 7.

h 18.5 ver. 1, 9 (Gk.). See Ps. 50. 5 (Gk. & Engl.).

i 18.5 Ex. 2. 3, 5.

k 18.5 Ex. 12. 29. So ver. 14, 15.

l 18.5 Ex. 14. 24, 25, 27.

m 18.6 Ex. 11. 4.

n 18.6 Acts 2. 36.

o 18.6 Gen. 15. 13.

p 18.8 ver. 10.

q 18.8 ver. 9.

h 18.9 ver. 1, 9 (Gk.). See Ps. 50. 5 (Gk. & Engl.).

r 18.9 Ex. 12. 21–28.

s 18.9 Ex. 12. 22.

* 18.9 Or, a covenant of God, or, league. Comp. Ps. 50. 5.

t 18.10 Ex. 12. 30.

u 18.11 Ex. 11. 5. & 12. 29.

t 18.12 Ex. 12. 30.

w 18.13 So ch. 17. 7.

x 18.13 Ex. 12. 33.

k 18.14 Ex. 12. 29. So ver. 14, 15.

k 18.15 Ex. 12. 29. So ver. 14, 15.

y 18.15 See ch. 9. 4.

z 18.15 Ex. 15. 3.

a 18.16 ch. 5. 18 (Gk.).

b 18.16 Comp. Rev. 1. 16.

c 18.16 1 Chr. 21. 16.

* 18.17 Or, imaginations.

d 18.17 So ch. 17. 4.

q 18.20 ver. 20 (Gk.).

e 18.20 ch. 10. 20. & 16. 23.

f 18.20 Numb. 16. 45, 48, 49.

f 18.20 Numb. 16. 45, 48, 49.

g 18.21 See ch. 10. 5.

i 18.21 Gk. as ver. 21.

h 18.21 Num. 16. 46, 47.

i 18.22 Gk. as ver. 21.

k 18.22 Comp. Ex. 32. 13. Ecclus. 36. 8.

l 18.23 Num. 16. 48.

* 18.23 Or, cut off.

m 18.24 Ex. 28. 2, 6. & 31. 10. So Ecclus. 45. 10. & 50. 11.

n 18.24 Ex. 28. 17.

o 18.24 Ex. 28. 36–38. So Ecclus. 45. 12.

p 18.25 Heb. 11. 28. So Ps. 78. 49. See Tobit 3. 8.

q 18.25 ver. 20 (Gk.).

a 19.1 See 1 Thess. 2. 16.

b 19.2 Ex. 12. 33, 39.

c 19.2 Judith 10. 15 (Gk.). See Acts 15. 3.

d 19.2 Ex. 14. 5, 6.

* 19.3 Or, cast out by intreaty.

e 19.4 See Titus 1. 5.

f 19.4 See Luke 16. 23.

g 19.5 Ex. 14. 28, 29.

h 19.6 ch. 16. 24, 25.

i 19.6 Acts 13. 36 marg.

k 19.7 Ex. 13. 21, 22.

g 19.7 Ex. 14. 28, 29.

l 19.7 Ps. 106. 9.

m 19.9 So Isai. 63. 13. Comp. Hab. 3. 15.

n 19.9 See Ps. 114. 4. So Ps. 77. 20. & 78. 52. Isai. 63. 11.

* 19.10 Or, lice. Ex. 8. 16, &c.

o 19.10 Ex. 8. 3, 6.

p 19.11 See ch. 16. 2.

* 19.12 Or, comfort. 1 Cor. 14. 3. So ch. 3. 18.

q 19.13 ch. 5. 11. Acts 1. 3 in the Gk.

r 19.13 Comp. Ps. 77. 17, 18, rather than ch. 16. 16, 22.

s 19.13 Ex. 1. 11. & 5. 6–9.

t 19.14 Gen. 19. 4–8. Comp. Ecclus. 16. 8.

u 19.14 Gen. 41. 55–57. Ex. 1. 8.

x 19.15 See ch. 2. 20.

t 19.15 Gen. 19. 4–8. Comp. Ecclus. 16. 8.

u 19.16 Gen. 41. 55–57. Ex. 1. 8.

y 19.16 Gen. 45. 16–20.

z 19.17 Ex. 10. 23. ch. 17. 2.

a 19.17 Gen. 19. 11.

b 19.17 ch. 10. 6. 2 Pet. 2. 7.

c 19.17 So ch. 17. 17.

* 19.18 Gr. by themselves. So Heb. 1. 3.

cc 19.18 See Ecclus. 40. 21.

d 19.18 ver. 19–21.

e 19.19 Ex. 12. 38. & 14. 29.

f 19.19 Ex. 8. 3.

g 19.20 ch. 16. 17.

h 19.21 ch. 16. 18.

i 19.21 ch. 16. 22, 23.

k 19.21 Comp. Ex. 16. 14.

l 19.22 So ch. 12. 20.

Zechariah

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14

Zechariah

1

1  In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the LORD unto Zechariah, the son of [‡]Berechiah, the son of Iddo the prophet, saying, 2  The LORD hath been [†]sore displeased with your fathers. 3  Therefore say thou unto them, Thus saith the LORD of hosts; [*]Turn ye unto me, saith the LORD of hosts, and I will turn unto you, saith the LORD of hosts. 4  Be ye not as your fathers, unto whom the former prophets have cried, saying, Thus saith the LORD of hosts; [*]Turn ye now from your evil ways, and from your evil doings: but they did not hear, nor hearken unto me, saith the LORD. 5  Your fathers, where are they? and the prophets, do they live for ever? 6  But my words and my statutes, which I commanded my servants the prophets, did they not [∥]take hold of your fathers? and they returned and said, [*]Like as the LORD of hosts thought to do unto us, according to our ways, and according to our doings, so hath he dealt with us.

7 ¶ Upon the four and twentieth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Sebat, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the LORD unto Zechariah, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo the prophet, saying, 8  I saw by night, and behold a man riding upon a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle trees that were in the bottom; and behind him were there red horses, [∥]speckled, and white. 9  Then said I, O my lord, what are these? And the angel that talked with me said unto me, I will shew thee what these be. 10  And the man that stood among the myrtle trees answered and said, These are they whom the LORD hath sent to walk to and fro through the earth. 11  And they answered the angel of the LORD that stood among the myrtle trees, and said, We have walked to and fro through the earth, and, behold, all the earth sitteth still, and is at rest.

12 ¶ Then the angel of the LORD answered and said, O LORD of hosts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which thou hast had indignation these threescore and ten years? 13  And the LORD answered the angel that talked with me with good words and comfortable words. 14  So the angel that communed with me said unto me, Cry thou, saying, Thus saith the LORD of hosts; I am [*]jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great jealousy. 15  And I am very sore displeased with the heathen that are at ease: for I was but a little displeased, and they helped forward the affliction. 16  Therefore thus saith the LORD; I am returned to Jerusalem with mercies: my house shall be built in it, saith the LORD of hosts, and a line shall be stretched forth upon Jerusalem. 17  Cry yet, saying, Thus saith the LORD of hosts; My cities through [†]prosperity shall yet be spread abroad; and the LORD shall yet comfort Zion, and shall yet choose Jerusalem.

18 ¶ Then lifted I up mine eyes, and saw, and behold four horns. 19  And I said unto the angel that talked with me, What be these? And he answered me, These are the horns which have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem. 20  And the LORD shewed me four carpenters. 21  Then said I, What come these to do? And he spake, saying, These are the horns which have scattered Judah, so that no man did lift up his head: but these are come to fray them, to cast out the horns of the Gentiles, which lifted up their horn over the land of Judah to scatter it.

2

1  I lifted up mine eyes again, and looked, and behold a man with a measuring line in his hand. 2  Then said I, Whither goest thou? And he said unto me, To measure Jerusalem, to see what is the breadth thereof, and what is the length thereof. 3  And, behold, the angel that talked with me went forth, and another angel went out to meet him, 4  And said unto him, Run, speak to this young man, saying, Jerusalem shall be inhabited as towns without walls for the multitude of men and cattle therein: 5  For I, saith the LORD, will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and will be the glory in the midst of her.

6 ¶ Ho, ho, come forth, and flee from the land of the north, saith the LORD: for I have spread you abroad as the four winds of the heaven, saith the LORD. 7  Deliver thyself, O Zion, that dwellest with the daughter of Babylon. 8  For thus saith the LORD of hosts; After the glory hath he sent me unto the nations which spoiled you: for he that [*]toucheth you toucheth the apple of his eye. 9  For, behold, I will shake mine hand upon them, and they shall be a spoil to their servants: and ye shall know that the LORD of hosts hath sent me.

10 ¶ [*]Sing and rejoice, O daughter of Zion: for, lo, I come, and I [*]will dwell in the midst of thee, saith the LORD. 11  And many nations shall be joined to the LORD in that day, and shall be my people: and I will dwell in the midst of thee, and thou shalt know that the LORD of hosts hath sent me unto thee. 12  And the LORD shall inherit Judah his portion in the holy land, and shall choose Jerusalem again. 13  Be silent, O all flesh, before the LORD: for he is raised up out of [†]his holy habitation.

3

1  And he shewed me Joshua the high priest standing before the angel of the LORD, and [∥]Satan standing at his right hand [†]to resist him. 2  And the LORD said unto Satan, [*]The LORD rebuke thee, O Satan; even the LORD that hath chosen Jerusalem rebuke thee: is not this a brand plucked out of the fire? 3  Now Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and stood before the angel. 4  And he answered and spake unto those that stood before him, saying, Take away the filthy garments from him. And unto him he said, Behold, I have caused thine iniquity to pass from thee, and I will clothe thee with change of raiment. 5  And I said, Let them set a fair mitre upon his head. So they set a fair mitre upon his head, and clothed him with garments. And the angel of the LORD stood by. 6  And the angel of the LORD protested unto Joshua, saying, 7  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; If thou wilt walk in my ways, and if thou wilt keep my [∥]charge, then thou shalt also judge my house, and shalt also keep my courts, and I will give thee [†]places to walk among these that stand by.

8  Hear now, O Joshua the high priest, thou, and thy fellows that sit before thee: for they are [†]men wondered at: for, behold, I will bring forth my servant the [*]BRANCH. 9  For behold the stone that I have laid before Joshua; upon one stone shall be seven eyes: behold, I will engrave the graving thereof, saith the LORD of hosts, and I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day. 10  In that day, saith the LORD of hosts, shall ye call every man his neighbour under the vine and under the fig tree.

4

1  And the angel that talked with me came again, and waked me, as a man that is wakened out of his sleep, 2  And said unto me, What seest thou? And I said, I have looked, and behold a candlestick all of gold, [†]with a bowl upon the top of it, and his seven lamps thereon, and [∥]seven pipes to the seven lamps, which are upon the top thereof: 3  And two olive trees by it, one upon the right side of the bowl, and the other upon the left side thereof. 4  So I answered and spake to the angel that talked with me, saying, What are these, my lord? 5  Then the angel that talked with me answered and said unto me, Knowest thou not what these be? And I said, No, my lord. 6  Then he answered and spake unto me, saying, This is the word of the LORD unto Zerubbabel, saying, Not by [∥]might, nor by power, but by my spirit, saith the LORD of hosts. 7 Who art thou, O great mountain? before Zerubbabel thou shalt become a plain: and he shall bring forth the headstone thereof with shoutings, crying, Grace, grace unto it. 8  Moreover the word of the LORD came unto me, saying, 9  The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this house; his hands shall also finish it; and thou shalt know that the LORD of hosts hath sent me unto you. 10  For who hath despised the day of small things? [∥]for they shall rejoice, and shall see the [†]plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel with those seven; [*]they are the eyes of the LORD, which run to and fro through the whole earth.

11 ¶ Then answered I, and said unto him, What are these two olive trees upon the right side of the candlestick and upon the left side thereof? 12  And I answered again, and said unto him, What be these two olive branches which [†]through the two golden pipes [∥]empty [†]the golden oil out of themselves? 13  And he answered me and said, Knowest thou not what these be? And I said, No, my lord. 14  Then said he, These are the two [†]anointed ones, that stand by the Lord of the whole earth.

5

1  Then I turned, and lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and behold a flying roll. 2  And he said unto me, What seest thou? And I answered, I see a flying roll; the length thereof is twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof ten cubits. 3  Then said he unto me, This is the curse that goeth forth over the face of the whole earth: for [∥]every one that stealeth shall be cut off as on this side according to it; and every one that sweareth shall be cut off as on that side according to it. 4  I will bring it forth, saith the LORD of hosts, and it shall enter into the house of the thief, and into the house of him that sweareth falsely by my name: and it shall remain in the midst of his house, and shall consume it with the timber thereof and the stones thereof.

5 ¶ Then the angel that talked with me went forth, and said unto me, Lift up now thine eyes, and see what is this that goeth forth. 6  And I said, What is it? And he said, This is an ephah that goeth forth. He said moreover, This is their resemblance through all the earth. 7  And, behold, there was lifted up a [∥]talent of lead: and this is a woman that sitteth in the midst of the ephah. 8  And he said, This is wickedness. And he cast it into the midst of the ephah; and he cast the weight of lead upon the mouth thereof. 9  Then lifted I up mine eyes, and looked, and, behold, there came out two women, and the wind was in their wings; for they had wings like the wings of a stork: and they lifted up the ephah between the earth and the heaven. 10  Then said I to the angel that talked with me, Whither do these bear the ephah? 11  And he said unto me, To build it an house in the land of Shinar: and it shall be established, and set there upon her own base.

6

1  And I turned, and lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and, behold, there came four chariots out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of brass. 2  In the first chariot were red horses; and in the second chariot black horses; 3  And in the third chariot white horses; and in the fourth chariot grisled and [∥]bay horses. 4  Then I answered and said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these, my lord? 5  And the angel answered and said unto me, These are the four [∥]spirits of the heavens, which go forth from standing before the Lord of all the earth. 6  The black horses which are therein go forth into the north country; and the white go forth after them; and the grisled go forth toward the south country. 7  And the bay went forth, and sought to go that they might walk to and fro through the earth: and he said, Get you hence, walk to and fro through the earth. So they walked to and fro through the earth. 8  Then cried he upon me, and spake unto me, saying, Behold, these that go toward the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country.

9 ¶ And the word of the LORD came unto me, saying, 10  Take of them of the captivity, even of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah, which are come from Babylon, and come thou the same day, and go into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah; 11  Then take silver and gold, and make crowns, and set them upon the head of Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest; 12  And speak unto him, saying, Thus speaketh the LORD of hosts, saying, Behold the man whose name is The [*]BRANCH; and he shall [∥]grow up out of his place, and he shall build the temple of the LORD: 13  Even he shall build the temple of the LORD; and he shall bear the glory, and shall sit and rule upon his throne; and he shall be a priest upon his throne: and the counsel of peace shall be between them both. 14  And the crowns shall be to Helem, and to Tobijah, and to Jedaiah, and to Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in the temple of the LORD. 15 And they that are far off shall come and build in the temple of the LORD, and ye shall know that the LORD of hosts hath sent me unto you. And this shall come to pass, if ye will diligently obey the voice of the LORD your God.

7

1  And it came to pass in the fourth year of king Darius, that the word of the LORD came unto Zechariah in the fourth day of the ninth month, even in Chisleu; 2  When they had sent unto the house of God Sherezer and Regem-melech, and their men, [†]to pray before the LORD, 3  And to speak unto the priests which were in the house of the LORD of hosts, and to the prophets, saying, Should I weep in the fifth month, separating myself, as I have done these so many years?

4 ¶ Then came the word of the LORD of hosts unto me, saying, 5  Speak unto all the people of the land, and to the priests, saying, When ye [*]fasted and mourned in the fifth and seventh month, even those seventy years, did ye at all fast unto me, even to me? 6  And when ye did eat, and when ye did drink, [∥]did not ye eat for yourselves, and drink for yourselves? 7 [∥] Should ye not hear the words which the LORD hath cried [†]by the former prophets, when Jerusalem was inhabited and in prosperity, and the cities thereof round about her, when men inhabited the south [‡]and the plain?

8 ¶ And the word of the LORD came unto Zechariah, saying, 9  Thus speaketh the LORD of hosts, saying, [†]Execute true judgment, and shew mercy and compassions every man to his brother: 10  And [*]oppress not the widow, nor the fatherless, the stranger, nor the poor; and let none of you imagine evil against his brother in your heart. 11  But they refused to hearken, and [†]pulled away the shoulder, and [†]stopped their ears, that they should not hear. 12  Yea, they made their hearts as an adamant stone, lest they should hear the law, and the words which the LORD of hosts hath sent in his spirit [†]by the former prophets: therefore came a great wrath from the LORD of hosts. 13 Therefore it is come to pass, that as he cried, and they would not hear; so [*]they cried, and I would not hear, saith the LORD of hosts: 14  But I scattered them with a whirlwind among all the nations whom they knew not. Thus the land was desolate after them, that no man passed through nor returned: for they laid the [†]pleasant land desolate.

8

1  Again the word of the LORD of hosts came to me, saying, 2  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; [*]I was jealous for Zion with great jealousy, and I was jealous for her with great fury. 3  Thus saith the LORD; I am returned unto Zion, and will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem: and Jerusalem shall be called a city of truth; and the mountain of the LORD of hosts the holy mountain. 4  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; There shall yet old men and old women dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, and every man with his staff in his hand [†]for very age. 5  And the streets of the city shall be full of boys and girls playing in the streets thereof. 6  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; If it be [∥]marvellous in the eyes of the remnant of this people in these days, should it also be marvellous in mine eyes? saith the LORD of hosts. 7  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; Behold, I will save my people from the east country, and from [†]the west country; 8  And I will bring them, and they shall dwell in the midst of Jerusalem: and they shall be my people, and I will be their God, in truth and in righteousness.

9 ¶ Thus saith the LORD of hosts; Let your hands be strong, ye that hear in these days these words by the mouth of the prophets, which were in the day that the foundation of the house of the LORD of hosts was laid, that the temple might be built. 10  For before these days [∥]there was no [*]hire for man, nor any hire for beast; neither was there any peace to him that went out or came in because of the affliction: for I set all men every one against his neighbour. 11 But now I will not be unto the residue of this people as in the former days, saith the LORD of hosts. 12  For the seed shall be [†]prosperous; the vine shall give her fruit, and the ground shall give her increase, and the heavens shall give their dew; and I will cause the remnant of this people to possess all these things. 13 And it shall come to pass, that as ye were a curse among the heathen, O house of Judah, and house of Israel; so will I save you, and ye shall be a blessing: fear not, but let your hands be strong. 14  For thus saith the LORD of hosts; As I thought to punish you, when your fathers provoked me to wrath, saith the LORD of hosts, and I repented not: 15  So again have I thought in these days to do well unto Jerusalem and to the house of Judah: fear ye not.

16 ¶ These are the things that ye shall do; [*]Speak ye every man the truth to his neighbour; [†]execute the judgment of truth and peace in your gates: 17  And let none of you imagine evil in your hearts against his neighbour; and love no false oath: for all these are things that I hate, saith the LORD.

18 ¶ And the word of the LORD of hosts came unto me, saying, 19  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; The fast of the fourth month, and the fast of the fifth, and the fast of the seventh, and the fast of the tenth, shall be to the house of Judah joy and gladness, and cheerful [∥]feasts; therefore love the truth and peace. 20  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; It shall yet come to pass, that there shall come people, and the inhabitants of many cities: 21  And the inhabitants of one city shall go to another, saying, [*]Let us go [∥][†]speedily [†]to pray before the LORD, and to seek the LORD of hosts: I will go also. 22  Yea, many people and strong nations shall come to seek the LORD of hosts in Jerusalem, and to pray before the LORD. 23  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; In those days it shall come to pass, that ten men shall take hold out of all languages of the nations, even shall take hold of the skirt of him that is a Jew, saying, We will go with you: for we have heard that God is with you.

9

1  The burden of the word of the LORD in the land of Hadrach, and Damascus shall be the rest thereof: when the eyes of man, as of all the tribes of Israel, shall be toward the LORD. 2  And Hamath also shall border thereby; Tyrus, and Zidon, though it be very [*]wise. 3  And Tyrus did build herself a strong hold, and heaped up silver as the dust, and fine gold as the mire of the streets. 4  Behold, the Lord will cast her out, and he will smite her power in the sea; and she shall be devoured with fire. 5  Ashkelon shall see it, and fear; Gaza also shall see it, and be very sorrowful, and Ekron; for her expectation shall be ashamed; and the king shall perish from Gaza, and Ashkelon shall not be inhabited. 6  And a bastard shall dwell in Ashdod, and I will cut off the pride of the Philistines. 7  And I will take away his [†]blood out of his mouth, and his abominations from between his teeth: but he that remaineth, even he, shall be for our God, and he shall be as a governor in Judah, and Ekron as a Jebusite. 8  And I will encamp about mine house because of the army, because of him that passeth by, and because of him that returneth: and no oppressor shall pass through them any more: for now have I seen with mine eyes.

9 ¶ [*]Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion; shout, O daughter of Jerusalem: behold, thy King cometh unto thee: he is just, and [∥]having salvation; lowly, and riding upon an ass, and upon a colt the foal of an ass. 10  And I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim, and the horse from Jerusalem, and the battle bow shall be cut off: and he shall speak peace unto the heathen: and his dominion shall be [*]from sea even to sea, and from the river even to the ends of the earth. 11  As for thee also, [∥]by the blood of thy covenant I have sent forth thy [*]prisoners out of the pit wherein is no water.

12 ¶ Turn you to the strong hold, ye prisoners of hope: even to day do I declare that I will render double unto thee; 13  When I have bent Judah for me, filled the bow with Ephraim, and raised up thy sons, O Zion, against thy sons, O Greece, and made thee as the sword of a mighty man. 14  And the LORD shall be seen over them, and his arrow shall go forth as the lightning: and the Lord GOD shall blow the trumpet, and shall go with whirlwinds of the south. 15  The LORD of hosts shall defend them; and they shall devour, and [∥]subdue with sling stones; and they shall drink, and make a noise as through wine; and they [∥]shall be filled like bowls, and as the corners of the altar. 16  And the LORD their God shall save them in that day as the flock of his people: for they shall be as the stones of a crown, lifted up as an ensign upon his land. 17 For how great is his goodness, and how great is his beauty! corn shall make the young men [∥]cheerful, and new wine the maids.

10

1  Ask ye of the LORD rain in the time of the latter rain; so the LORD shall make [∥]bright clouds, and give them showers of rain, to every one grass in the field. 2  For the [*][†]idols have spoken vanity, and the diviners have seen a lie, and have told false dreams; they comfort in vain: therefore they went their way as a flock, they [∥]were troubled, because there was no shepherd. 3  Mine anger was kindled against the shepherds, and I [†]punished the goats: for the LORD of hosts hath visited his flock the house of Judah, and hath made them as his goodly horse in the battle. 4  Out of him came forth the corner, out of him the nail, out of him the battle bow, out of him every oppressor together.

5 ¶ And they shall be as mighty men, which tread down their enemies in the mire of the streets in the battle: and they shall fight, because the LORD is with them, and [∥]the riders on horses shall be confounded. 6  And I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph, and I will bring them again to place them; for I have mercy upon them: and they shall be as though I had not cast them off: for I am the LORD their God, and will hear them. 7 And they of Ephraim shall be like a mighty man, and their heart shall rejoice as through wine: yea, their children shall see it, and be glad; their heart shall rejoice in the LORD. 8  I will hiss for them, and gather them; for I have redeemed them: and they shall increase as they have increased. 9  And I will sow them among the people: and they shall remember me in far countries; and they shall live with their children, and turn again. 10  I will bring them again also out of the land of Egypt, and gather them out of Assyria; and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon; and place shall not be found for them. 11  And he shall pass through the sea with affliction, and shall smite the waves in the sea, and all the deeps of the river shall dry up: and the pride of Assyria shall be brought down, and the sceptre of Egypt shall depart away. 12  And I will strengthen them in the LORD; and they shall walk up and down in his name, saith the LORD.

11

1  Open thy doors, O Lebanon, that the fire may devour thy cedars. 2  Howl, fir tree; for the cedar is fallen; because [‡]the [∥]mighty are spoiled: howl, O ye oaks of Bashan; for [∥]the forest of the vintage is come down.

3 ¶ There is a voice of the howling of the shepherds; for their glory is spoiled: a voice of the roaring of young lions; for the pride of Jordan is spoiled.

4  Thus saith the LORD my God; Feed the flock of the slaughter; 5  Whose possessors slay them, and hold themselves not guilty: and they that sell them say, Blessed be the LORD; for I am rich: and their own shepherds pity them not. 6  For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land, saith the LORD: but, lo, I will [†]deliver the men every one into his neighbour’s hand, and into the hand of his king: and they shall smite the land, and out of their hand I will not deliver them. 7  And I will feed the flock of slaughter, [∥]even you, O poor of the flock. And I took unto me two staves; the one I called Beauty, and the other I called [∥]Bands; and I fed the flock. 8  Three shepherds also I cut off in one month; and my soul [†]lothed them, and their soul also abhorred me. 9  Then said I, I will not feed you: [*]that that dieth, let it die; and that that is to be cut off, let it be cut off; and let the rest eat every one the flesh [†]of another.

10 ¶ And I took my staff, even Beauty, and cut it asunder, that I might break my covenant which I had made with all the people. 11  And it was broken in that day: and [∥]so the poor of the flock that waited upon me knew that it was the word of the LORD. 12  And I said unto them, [†]If ye think good, give me my price; and if not, forbear. So they [*]weighed for my price thirty pieces of silver. 13  And the LORD said unto me, Cast it unto the [*]potter: a goodly price that I was prised at of them. And I took the thirty pieces of silver, and cast them to the potter in the house of the LORD. 14  Then I cut asunder mine other staff, even [∥]Bands, that I might break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 ¶ And the LORD said unto me, Take unto thee yet the instruments of a foolish shepherd. 16  For, lo, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, which shall not visit those that be [∥]cut off, neither shall seek the young one, nor heal that that is broken, nor [∥]feed that that standeth still: but he shall eat the flesh of the fat, and tear their claws in pieces. 17 [*] Woe to the idol shepherd that leaveth the flock! the sword shall be upon his arm, and upon his right eye: his arm shall be clean dried up, and his right eye shall be utterly darkened.

12

1  The burden of the word of the LORD for Israel, saith the LORD, which stretcheth forth the heavens, and layeth the foundation of the earth, and formeth the spirit of man within him. 2  Behold, I will make Jerusalem a cup of [∥]trembling unto all the people round about, [∥]when they shall be in the siege both against Judah and against Jerusalem.

3 ¶ And in that day will I make Jerusalem a burdensome stone for all people: all that burden themselves with it shall be cut in pieces, though all the people of the earth be gathered together against it. 4  In that day, saith the LORD, I will smite every horse with astonishment, and his rider with madness: and I will open mine eyes upon the house of Judah, and will smite every horse of the people with blindness. 5  And the governors of Judah shall say in their heart, [∥]The inhabitants of Jerusalem shall be my strength in the LORD of hosts their God.

6 ¶ In that day will I make the governors of Judah like an hearth of fire among the wood, and like a torch of fire in a sheaf; and they shall devour all the people round about, on the right hand and on the left: and Jerusalem shall be inhabited again in her own place, even in Jerusalem. 7  The LORD also shall save the tents of Judah first, that the glory of the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem do not magnify themselves against Judah. 8  In that day shall the LORD defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and he that is [∥][†]feeble among them at that day shall be as David; and the house of David shall be as God, as the angel of the LORD before them.

9 ¶ And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will seek to destroy all the nations that come against Jerusalem. 10  And I will pour upon the house of David, and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the spirit of grace and of supplications: and they shall [*]look upon me whom they have pierced, and they shall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only son, and shall be in bitterness for him, as one that is in bitterness for his firstborn. 11  In that day shall there be a great [*]mourning in Jerusalem, [*]as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon. 12  And the land shall mourn, [†]every family apart; the family of the house of David apart, and their wives apart; the family of the house of Nathan apart, and their wives apart; 13  The family of the house of Levi apart, and their wives apart; the family of Shimei apart, and their wives apart; 14  All the families that remain, every family apart, and their wives apart.

13

1  In that day there shall be a fountain opened to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem for sin and for [†]uncleanness.

2 ¶ And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the LORD of hosts, that I will [*]cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they shall no more be remembered: and also I will cause the prophets and the unclean spirit to pass out of the land. 3 And it shall come to pass, that when any shall yet prophesy, then his father and his mother that begat him shall say unto him, Thou shalt not live; for thou speakest lies in the name of the LORD: and his father and his mother that begat him shall thrust him through when he prophesieth. 4  And it shall come to pass in that day, that the prophets shall be ashamed every one of his vision, when he hath prophesied; neither shall they wear [†]a rough garment [†]to deceive: 5  But he shall say, I am no prophet, I am an husbandman; for man taught me to keep cattle from my youth. 6 And one shall say unto him, What are these wounds in thine hands? Then he shall answer, Those with which I was wounded in the house of my friends.

7 ¶ Awake, O sword, against my shepherd, and against the man that is my fellow, saith the LORD of hosts: [*]smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered: and I will turn mine hand upon the little ones. 8 And it shall come to pass, that in all the land, saith the LORD, two parts therein shall be cut off and die; but the third shall be left therein. 9  And I will bring the third part through the fire, and will [*]refine them as silver is refined, and will try them as gold is tried: they shall call on my name, and I will hear them: I will say, It is my people: and they shall say, The LORD is my God.

14

1  Behold, the day of the LORD cometh, and thy spoil shall be divided in the midst of thee. 2  For I will gather all nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city shall be taken, and the houses rifled, and the women ravished; and half of the city shall go forth into captivity, and the residue of the people shall not be cut off from the city. 3  Then shall the LORD go forth, and fight against those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle.

4 ¶ And his feet shall stand in that day upon the mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem on the east, and the mount of Olives shall cleave in the midst thereof toward the east and toward the west, and there shall be a very great valley; and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north, and half of it toward the south. 5  And ye shall flee to the valley of [∥]the mountains; [∥]for the valley of the mountains shall reach unto Azal: yea, ye shall flee, like as ye fled from before the [*]earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah: and the LORD my God shall come, and all the saints with thee. 6  And it shall come to pass in that day, that the light shall not be [†]clear, nor [†]dark: 7  But [∥]it shall be [*]one day which shall be known to the LORD, not day, nor night: but it shall come to pass, that at [*]evening time it shall be light.

8  And it shall be in that day, that living [*]waters shall go out from Jerusalem; half of them toward the [∥]former sea, and half of them toward the hinder sea: in summer and in winter shall it be. 9  And the LORD shall be king over all the earth: in that day shall there be one LORD, and his name one. 10  All the land shall be [∥]turned as a plain from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem: and it shall be lifted up, and [∥]inhabited in her place, from Benjamin’s gate unto the place of the first gate, unto the corner gate, and from the tower of Hananeel unto the king’s winepresses. 11 And men shall dwell in it, and there shall be no more utter destruction; but Jerusalem [∥]shall be safely inhabited.

12 ¶ And this shall be the plague wherewith the LORD will smite all the people that have fought against Jerusalem; Their flesh shall consume away while they stand upon their feet, and their eyes shall consume away in their holes, and their tongue shall consume away in their mouth. 13  And it shall come to pass in that day, that a great tumult from the LORD shall be among them; and they shall lay hold every one on the hand of his neighbour, and his hand shall rise up against the hand of his neighbour. 14  And [∥]Judah also shall fight [∥]at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the heathen round about shall be gathered together, gold, and silver, and apparel, in great abundance. 15  And so shall be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camel, and of the ass, and of all the beasts that shall be in these tents, as this plague.

16 ¶ And it shall come to pass, that every one that is left of all the nations which came against Jerusalem shall even go up from year to year to worship the King, the LORD of hosts, and to keep the feast of tabernacles. 17 And it shall be, that whoso will not come up of all the families of the earth unto Jerusalem to worship the King, the LORD of hosts, even upon them shall be no rain. 18  And if the family of Egypt go not up, and come not, [†]that have no rain; there shall be the plague, wherewith the LORD will smite the heathen that come not up to keep the feast of tabernacles. 19  This shall be the [∥]punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all nations that come not up to keep the feast of tabernacles.

20 ¶ In that day shall there be upon the [∥]bells of the horses, HOLINESS UNTO THE LORD; and the pots in the LORD’s house shall be like the bowls before the altar. 21  Yea, every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah shall be holiness unto the LORD of hosts: and all they that sacrifice shall come and take of them, and seethe therein: and in that day there shall be no more the [*]Canaanite in the house of the LORD of hosts.

‡ 1.1 [1611 Barachiah]

† 1.2 Heb. with displeasure.

* 1.3 Mal. 3. 7

* 1.4 Is. 31 6 Jer. 3 12. &c 18 11 Ezek. 18 30. Hos. 14. 1.

∥ 1.6 Or, overtake

* 1.6 Lam 1. 18.

∥ 1.8 Or, bay.

* 1.14 ch. 8. 2.

† 1.17 Heb. good.

* 2.8 Deut 32 10 Ps 17 8.

* 2.10 Is. 12. 6. &c 54. 1

* 2.10 Lev. 26 12. Ezek. 37. 27. 2 Cor. 6. 16.

† 2.13 Heb. the habitation of his holiness.

∥ 3.1 That is, an adversary

† 3.1 Heb to be his adversary.

* 3.2 Jude 9.

∥ 3.7 Or, ordinance.

† 3.7 Heb. walks.

† 3.8 Heb. men of wonder.

* 3.8 Is. 11. 1. Jer 23. 5. &c 33. 15. ch 6. 12. Luke 1. 78.

† 4.2 Heb. with her bowl.

∥ 4.2 Or, seven several pipes to the lamps, &c.

∥ 4.6 Or, army.

∥ 4.10 Or, sith the seven eyes of the Lord shall rejoice.

† 4.10 Heb. stone of tin.

* 4.10 ch. 3. 9.

† 4.12 Heb. by the hand.

∥ 4.12 Or, empty out of themselves oil into the gold

† 4.12 Heb. the gold.

† 4.14 Heb. sons of oil.

∥ 5.3 Or, everyone of this people that stealeth holdeth himself guiltless, as it doth.

∥ 5.7 Or, weighty piece.

∥ 6.3 Or, strong.

∥ 6.5 Or, winds.

* 6.12 ch 3. 8.

∥ 6.12 Or, branch up from under him.

† 7.2 Heb. to intreat the face of the Lord.

* 7.5 Is. 58. 5.

∥ 7.6 Or, be not ye they that, &c

∥ 7.7 Or, Are not these the words.

† 7.7 Heb. by the hand of, &c.

‡ 7.7 [1611 of]

† 7.9 Heb. Judge judgment of truth.

* 7.10 Ex. 22. 21. Is 1 23. Jer. 5. 28

† 7.11 Heb. they gave a back-sliding shoulder.

† 7.11 Heb. made heavy.

† 7.12 Heb. by the hand of

* 7.13 Prov. 1. 28. Is 1 15. Jer. 11. 11. &c 14. 12.

† 7.14 Heb. land of desire

* 8.2 ch. 1. 14.

† 8.4 Heb. for multitude of days.

∥ 8.6 Or, hard, or, difficult.

† 8.7 Heb. the country of the going down of the sun.

∥ 8.10 Or, the hire of man became nothing, &c.

* 8.10 Hag. 1. 6.

† 8.12 Heb of peace.

* 8.16 Eph 4. 25.

† 8.16 Heb. judge truth, and the judgment of peace.

∥ 8.19 Or, solemn, or, set times.

* 8.21 Is. 2. 3. Mic. 4. 1, 2

∥ 8.21 Or, continually.

† 8.21 Heb. going.

† 8.21 Heb. to intreat the face of the Lord.

* 9.2 Ezek 28 3, &c.

† 9.7 Heb. bloods.

* 9.9 Is. 62. 11. Matt 21 5. John 12. 15.

∥ 9.9 Or, saving himself.

* 9.10 Ps 72. 8.

∥ 9.11 Or, whose covenant is by blood.

* 9.11 Is. 61. 1.

∥ 9.15 Or, subdue the stones of the sling.

∥ 9.15 Or, shall fill both the bowls, &c.

∥ 9.17 Or, grow, or, speak

∥ 10.1 Or, lightnings.

* 10.2 Jer. 10. 8 Hab. 3. 18.

† 10.2 Heb. teraphims.

∥ 10.2 Or, answered that, &c.

† 10.3 Heb. visited upon.

∥ 10.5 Or, they shall make the riderson horses ashamed.

‡ 11.2 [1611 all the mighty]

∥ 11.2 Or, gallants.

∥ 11.2 Or, the defenced forest.

† 11.6 Heb. make to be found.

∥ 11.7 Or, verily the poor.

∥ 11.7 Or, Binders.

† 11.8 Heb. was straitened for them.

* 11.9 Jer. 15. 2.

† 11.9 Heb. of his fellow, or, neighbour.

∥ 11.11 Or, the poor of the flock, &c. certainly knew.

† 11.12 Heb. If it be good in your eyes.

* 11.12 Matt. 26. 15.

* 11.13 Matt. 27 9.

∥ 11.14 Or, Binders

∥ 11.16 Or, hidden.

∥ 11.16 Or, bear.

* 11.17 Jer 23. 1. Ezek. 34 2. John 10. 12.

∥ 12.2 Or, slumber, or, poison.

∥ 12.2 Or, and also against Judah shall he be which shall be in siege against Jerusalem.

∥ 12.5 Or, There is strength to me and to the inhabitants, &c.

∥ 12.8 Or, abject.

† 12.8 Heb. fallen.

* 12.10 John 19. 34. 37. Rev. 1. 7.

* 12.11 Acts 2. 37

* 12.11 2 Chr. 35 24

† 12.12 Heb. families, families.

† 13.1 Heb. separation for uncleanness.

* 13.2 Ezek. 30 13.

† 13.4 Heb. a garment of hair.

† 13.4 Heb. to lie.

* 13.7 Matt. 26. 31. Mark 14. 27.

* 13.9 1 Pet. 1. 6, 7.

∥ 14.5 Or, my mountains.

∥ 14.5 Or, when he shall touch the valley of the mountains to the place he separated.

* 14.5 Amos 1. 1.

† 14.6 Heb. precious.

† 14.6 Heb. thickness.

∥ 14.7 Or, the day shall be one.

* 14.7 Rev. 22. 5.

* 14.7 Is. 60. 19. Rev. 21. 23.

* 14.8 Ezek. 47. 1. Joel 3. 18. Rev. 22. 1.

∥ 14.8 Or, eastern.

∥ 14.10 Or, compassed.

∥ 14.10 Or, shall abide.

∥ 14.11 Or, shall abide.

∥ 14.14 Or, thou also, O Judah, shalt.

∥ 14.14 Or, against.

† 14.18 Heb. upon whom there is not.

∥ 14.19 Or, sin

∥ 14.20 Or, bridles.

* 14.21 Is. 35. 8 Joel 3. 17. Rev. 21. 27. &c 22. 15.

Zephaniah

1
2
3

Zephaniah

1

1  The word of the LORD which came unto Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hizkiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah. 2 [†] I will utterly consume all things from off [†]the land, saith the LORD. 3  I will consume man and beast; I will consume the fowls of the heaven, and the fishes of the sea, and the [∥]stumblingblocks with the wicked; and I will cut off man from off the land, saith the LORD. 4  I will also stretch out mine hand upon Judah, and upon all the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place, and the name of the Chemarims with the priests; 5  And them that worship the host of heaven upon the housetops; and them that worship and that swear [∥]by the LORD, and that swear by Malcham; 6  And them that are turned back from the LORD; and those that have not sought the LORD, nor enquired for him.

7  Hold thy peace at the presence of the Lord GOD: for the day of the LORD is at hand: for the LORD hath prepared a sacrifice, he hath [†]bid his guests. 8  And it shall come to pass in the day of the LORD’s sacrifice, that I will [†]punish the princes, and the king’s children, and all such as are clothed with strange apparel. 9  In the same day also will I punish all those that leap on the threshold, which fill their masters’ houses with violence and deceit. 10  And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the LORD, that there shall be the noise of a cry from the fish gate, and an howling from the second, and a great crashing from the hills. 11  Howl, ye inhabitants of Maktesh, for all the merchant people are cut down; all they that bear silver are cut off. 12  And it shall come to pass at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with candles, and punish the men that are [†]settled on their lees: that say in their heart, The LORD will not do good, neither will he do evil. 13  Therefore their goods shall become a booty, and their houses a desolation: they shall also build houses, but [*]not inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, but not drink the wine thereof.

14  The great day of the LORD is near, it is near, and hasteth greatly, even the voice of the day of the LORD: the mighty man shall cry there bitterly. 15  That day is a day of [*]wrath, a day of trouble and distress, a day of wasteness and desolation, a day of darkness and gloominess, a day of clouds and thick darkness, 16  A day of the trumpet and alarm against the fenced cities, and against the high towers. 17  And I will bring distress upon men, that they shall walk like blind men, because they have sinned against the LORD: and their blood shall be poured out as dust, and their flesh as the dung. 18 [*] Neither their silver nor their gold shall be able to deliver them in the day of the LORD’s wrath; but the whole land shall be [*]devoured by the fire of his jealousy: for he shall make even a speedy riddance of all them that dwell in the land.

2

1  Gather yourselves together, yea, gather together, O nation [∥]not desired; 2  Before the decree bring forth, before the day pass as the chaff, before the fierce anger of the LORD come upon you, before the day of the LORD’s anger come upon you. 3  Seek ye the LORD, all ye meek of the earth, which have wrought his judgment; seek righteousness, seek meekness: it may be ye shall be hid in the day of the LORD’s anger.

4 ¶ For Gaza shall be forsaken, and Ashkelon a desolation: they shall drive out Ashdod at the noon day, and Ekron shall be rooted up. 5  Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea coast, the nation of the Cherethites! the word of the LORD is against you; O Canaan, the land of the Philistines, I will even destroy thee, that there shall be no inhabitant. 6  And the sea coast shall be dwellings and cottages for shepherds, and folds for flocks. 7  And the coast shall be for the remnant of the house of Judah; they shall feed thereupon: in the houses of Ashkelon shall they lie down in the evening: [∥]for the LORD their God shall visit them, and turn away their captivity.

8 ¶ I have heard the reproach of Moab, and the revilings of the children of Ammon, whereby they have reproached my people, and magnified themselves against their border. 9 Therefore as I live, saith the LORD of hosts, the God of Israel, Surely Moab shall be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, even the breeding of nettles, and saltpits, and a perpetual desolation: the residue of my people shall spoil them, and the remnant of my people shall possess them. 10  This shall they have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of the LORD of hosts. 11  The LORD will be terrible unto them: for he will [†]famish all the gods of the earth; and men shall worship him, every one from his place, even all the isles of the heathen.

12 ¶ Ye Ethiopians also, ye shall be slain by my sword. 13  And he will stretch out his hand against the north, and destroy Assyria; and will make Nineveh a desolation, and dry like a wilderness. 14  And flocks shall lie down in the midst of her, all the beasts of the nations: both the [∥][*]cormorant and the bittern shall lodge in the [∥]upper lintels of it; their voice shall sing in the windows; desolation shall be in the thresholds: [∥]for he shall uncover the cedar work. 15 This is the rejoicing city that dwelt carelessly, that said in her heart, [*]I am, and there is none beside me: how is she become a desolation, a place for beasts to lie down in! every one that passeth by her shall hiss, and wag his hand.

3

1  Woe to [∥][†]her that is filthy and polluted, to the oppressing city! 2  She obeyed not the voice; she received not [∥]correction; she trusted not in the LORD; she drew not near to her God. 3 [*] Her princes within her are roaring lions; her judges are evening wolves; they gnaw not the bones till the morrow. 4  Her [*]prophets are light and treacherous persons: her priests have polluted the sanctuary, they have done [*]violence to the law. 5  The just LORD is in the midst thereof; he will not do iniquity: [†]every morning doth he bring his judgment to light, he faileth not; but the unjust knoweth no shame. 6  I have cut off the nations: their [∥]towers are desolate; I made their streets waste, that none passeth by: their cities are destroyed, so that there is no man, that there is none inhabitant. 7  I said, Surely thou wilt fear me, thou wilt receive instruction; so their dwelling should not be cut off, howsoever I punished them: but they rose early, and corrupted all their doings.

8 ¶ Therefore wait ye upon me, saith the LORD, until the day that I rise up to the prey: for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may assemble the kingdoms, to pour upon them mine indignation, even all my fierce anger: for all the earth shall be devoured with the fire of my [*]jealousy. 9  For then will I turn to the people a pure [†]language, that they may all call upon the name of the LORD, to serve him with one [†]consent. 10  From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia my suppliants, even the daughter of my dispersed, shall bring mine offering. 11  In that day shalt thou not be ashamed for all thy doings, wherein thou hast transgressed against me: for then I will take away out of the midst of thee them that rejoice in thy pride, and thou shalt no more be haughty [†]because of [‡]my holy mountain. 12  I will also leave in the midst of thee an afflicted and poor people, and they shall trust in the name of the LORD. 13  The remnant of Israel shall not do iniquity, nor speak lies; neither shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth: for they shall feed and lie down, and none shall make them afraid.

14 ¶ Sing, O [*]daughter of Zion; shout, O Israel; be glad and rejoice with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem. 15  The LORD hath taken away thy judgments, he hath cast out thine enemy: the king of Israel, even the LORD, is in the midst of thee: thou shalt not see evil any more. 16  In that day it shall be said to Jerusalem, Fear thou not: and to Zion, Let not thine hands be [∥]slack. 17  The LORD thy God in the midst of thee is mighty; he will save, he will rejoice over thee with joy; [†]he will rest in his love, he will joy over thee with singing. 18  I will gather them that are sorrowful for the solemn assembly, who are of thee, to whom [†]the reproach of it was a burden. 19  Behold, at that time I will undo all that afflict thee: and I will save her that [*]halteth, and gather her that was driven out; and [†]I will get them praise and fame in every land [†]where they have been put to shame. 20  At that time will I bring you again, even in the time that I gather you: for I will make you a name and a praise among all people of the earth, when I turn back your captivity before your eyes, saith the LORD.

† 1.2 Heb. By taking away I will make an end.

† 1.2 Heb the face of the land.

∥ 1.3 Or, idols.

∥ 1.5 Or, to the Lord.

† 1.7 Heb. sanctified, or, prepared.

† 1.8 Heb. visit upon.

† 1.12 Heb. curded, or, thickened.

* 1.13 Deut. 28, 30, 39 Amos 5. 11.

* 1.15 Jer. 30. 7. Joel 2. 11. Amos 5. 18.

* 1.18 Prov. 11. 4. Ezek. 7. 19.

* 1.18 ch. 3. 8.

∥ 2.1 Or, not desirous.

∥ 2.7 Or, when, &c.

† 2.11 Heb. make lean.

∥ 2.14 Or, pelican.

* 2.14 Is. 34. 11.

∥ 2.14 Or, knops, or, chapiters.

∥ 2.14 Or, when he hath uncovered.

* 2.15 Is. 47 8.

∥ 3.1 Or, gluttonous

† 3.1 Heb. craw.

∥ 3.2 Or, instruction.

* 3.3 Ezek. 22. 27. Mic. 3 11.

* 3.4 Jer. 23. 11. Hos. 9 7.

* 3.4 Ezek. 22. 26.

† 3.5 Heb. morning by morning.

∥ 3.6 Or, corners.

* 3.8 ch. 1. 18.

† 3.9 Heb. lip.

† 3.9 Heb. shoulder.

† 3.11 Heb in my holy.

‡ 3.11 [1611 mine]

* 3.14 Is. 12 6. &c 54. 1.

∥ 3.16 Or, faint.

† 3.17 Heb he will be silent.

† 3.18 Heb. the burden upon it was reproach

* 3.19 Mic. 4. 7.

† 3.19 Heb. I will set them for a praise.

† 3.19 Heb. of their shame.